GOOD GOOD AFTERNOON. >> WELCOME TO THE JUNE 17TH
2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR SARTOR SADR PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL
SHERYL PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT MR.
PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA ALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA.
AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW MATERIAL ONI HAVE NEVER CEDED
LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY.
AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING
ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL OWNING COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD, INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I'D LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
AT US OF GOV TV AND TODAY ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA WHO
RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE
TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE. MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
APPROVAL OF MINUTES. >> YES WE HAVE APPROVAL.
>> ACTUALLY DO WE HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
WE DO. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO
ATTEND THIS MEETING HERE IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER.
IF YOU ARE UNABLE TO MAKE IT, YOU MAY WATCH THE PROCEEDING ON
AS OF GOVEE TV'S CHANNEL 26 OR VIEW THE LIVESTREAM AT W W W
DOT AS OF JIO VTV.ORG. IF YOU ARE UNABLE TO MAKE IT
AND YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT YOU CAN DO SO
IN TWO WAYS BY SENDING AN EMAIL TO BE OFFSET AS IF YOUR WORK OR
USE THE POSTAL SERVICE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B GOODLATTE PLACE CITY
HALL ROOM 240 FOUR SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 9410 TWO.
>> AND I WILL JUST STATE FOR THOSE OF YOU HOLDING SIGNS
WE'VE BEEN READING THOSE SIGNS WE APPRECIATE THE MESSAGING
THAT YOU'RE PROVIDING THE BOARD THERE IS AN APPROVED BOARD RULE
WHICH REQUIRES NO SIGNS IN THE CHAMBER.
BUT SINCE YOU HAVE THEM IN YOUR HAND SO THAT YOU'RE NOT
BLOCKING THE INDIVIDUALS BEHIND YOU, JUST TRY TO LOWER THEM
AND KEEP THEM RIGHT HERE NEAR YOUR CHIN.
THAT WOULD BE A REQUEST REQUESTED IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO
MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION REQUEST UNDER THE AMERICANS
WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR IF YOU NEED LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE PLEASE
CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE IN ROOM 244 JUST TO THE RIGHT
OR YOU CAN CALL (415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU MEMBERS THANK YOU,
MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF MEETING MINUTES SO
WHAT
WAS
THE NEW FUNDING? I
ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, WE'RE GOING TO RECESS UNTIL 3 P.M. >>
AND S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
NEWS
. ALL RIGHT, WE ARE BACK.
WE ARE RECONVENING AND WE ARE GOING TO RECESS UNTIL 330
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO LOCAL GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
AND S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
HELLO COLLEAGUES WE ARE BACK FOR A SECOND AND NOW WE ARE
GOING TO RECESS UNTIL 4:00
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
. >> ALL RIGHT, WE'RE BACK.
MADAM CLERK, I BELIEVE THAT WE WERE AT APPROVAL OF MINUTES.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. YES.
APPROVAL OF THE MAY 13TH, 2025 BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, I DON'T SEE ANYONE WITH CHANGES.
CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED
BY SÖDER SECONDED BY WALTON AND MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED?
SUPERVISOR SARTOR SARTOR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR.
CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY
DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO ENGARDIO I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR I MELGAR EITHER ARE LEBANESE ALL RIGHT WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER YES
IT IS NOW TIME TO CELEBRATE MERITORIOUS COMMENDATIONS FOR
MEMBERS OF OUR COMMUNITY AND WE HAVE A NUMBER OF THEM PLANNED
BUT I THINK SOME OF THEM MAY MAY BE COMING BACK NEXT WEEK OR
MAY NOT BE GOING TODAY. BUT I'LL JUST RUN THROUGH
SUPERVISOR CHAN FROM DISTRICT 11.
>> THANK YOU. PRESIDENT MADAM AND GOOD
AFTERNOON EVERYONE. >> STAN, DO YOU WANT TO COME TO
THE PODIUM TODAY? >> I'M CELEBRATING AND HONORING
FIREFIGHTER STAN LEE WHO IS CONCLUDING AN EXTRAORDINARY 30
YEAR CAREER DEDICATED TO SERVING OUR COMMUNITY.
STAN BEGAN HIS JOURNEY WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT
IN 1995. >> THROUGHOUT HIS CAREER HE
SERVED IN A WIDE RANGE OF ROLES INCLUDING RESCUE SQUAD MEMBER,
FIRE INVESTIGATOR, ACTING LIEUTENANT WITH THE EARTHQUAKE
SAFETY AND EMERGENCY RESPONSE BOND PROGRAM AND TRAINING
SPECIALIST. >> OVER THE YEARS, STAN
RESPONDED TO MORE THAN 400 WALKING FIRES AND EVEN
SUSTAINED INJURIES WHILE ON DUTY ALWAYS KEEPING OUR
COMMUNITY SAFE. >> BEYOND HIS WORK ON THE FRONT
LINES, STAN HAS BEEN A TIRELESSLY LEADER IN THE
COMMUNITY HE SERVES ON THE LEE'S FAMILY ASSOCIATION OF SAN
FRANCISCO ORGANIZED CHRISTMAS TOY GIVEAWAY IN CHINATOWN
AND HELPED THE DIRECTOR OF FIREFIGHTER LOCAL SEVEN 19.
>> HE WAS ALSO THE COACH AND CO-CAPTAIN OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT LOCAL 798 CHINESE LION DANCE TEAM
AND SERVED AS A CAPTAIN OF SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT
HOCKEY TEAM FOR OVER 20 YEARS. >> STAN WAS A LONGTIME MEMBER
OF THE EXECUTIVE BOARD MEMBER OF ASIAN FIREFIGHTER
ASSOCIATION WHERE HE BUILT A STRONG FOUNDATION OF VOLUNTEERS
AND AN ENVIRONMENT OF COLLABORATION, SUPPORT
AND COMMUNITY SERVICES FOR MEMBERS INSPIRED BY STANDS
LEGACY AND GRATEFUL FOR THE POSITIVE CHANGE THAT HE HAS
CHAMPIONED. >> WHAT IS MORE, STAND HELP EFA
LAUNCH A CHARITABLE FOUNDATION TO FACILITATE GIVING BACK TO
THE COMMUNITY. >> YOU MAY HAVE SEEN STAN AT
THE STREET FAIRS TOYS R CHINESE MERCHANTS CELEBRATION BRINGING
ENERGY, CULTURE AND COMPASSION TO EVERY EVENT.
>> MOST NOTABLY MANY OF US SAW STAN IN THE NEWS IN 2023 WHERE
HE ORGANIZED A VOLUNTEER GROUP OF FIREFIGHTERS TO TRAVEL TO
MAUI TO ASSIST WITH WILDFIRE RELIEF JUMPING INTO ACTION EVEN
BEFORE OFFICIAL A REQUEST IT HAD BEEN MADE ON THE GROUND.
>> STAN AND HIS TEAM HANDED OUT FOOD AND WATER EACH TO AT A
LOCAL RELIEF CENTER AND COOK AND SERVE MORE THAN 2000 MEALS
PER DAY. LATER WHEN A GRASS FIRE BROKE
OUT NEARBY, THEY STEPPED IN TO EXTINGUISH IT AND IN DECEMBER
STAN RETURNED TO LIFE. JONAH BRINGING HOLIDAY CHEER BY
DRIBBLING TOYS, FOOD AND CLOTHING TO FAMILIES
IN NEED. STAN, YOUR COURAGE, YOUR
DEDICATION, YOUR SENSE OF DUTY HAVE NOT ONLY MAKES SAN
FRANCISCO SAFER AND POW BUT YOU HAVE TOUCHED LIFE FAR BEYOND
OUR CITY YOUR LEGACY. IT'S ONE OF THE SERVICES
LEADERSHIP AND HEART. WE ALSO EXTEND OUR HEARTFELT
THANK YOU TO YOU AND YOUR FAMILIES WHO ARE HERE TODAY.
THANK YOU AND YOUR FRIENDS AND WHO ALSO HAVE SUPPORTED YOU
THROUGHOUT THIS REMARKABLE JOURNEY AS YOU STEP INTO
RETIREMENT MAY THIS NEXT CHAPTER BRING YOU JOY
AND FULFILLMENT IN CHINESE WE ALWAYS GO BY THIS TOYI BY YAO
HIMANI LOCKED OKAY JONG THROUGH YOUR DOOR YOU RETIRE YOUR
SPIRIT OF SERVICES CONTINUE AND MAY YOU FIND CONTINUE TO
FIND JOY IN ALL THINGS THAT YOU DO.
THANK YOU AND CONGRATULATION AND I'M NOW GOING TO PASS TO MY
TO OUR SUPERVISOR CONNIE CHEN THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR
TAKING THIS LEAD TO HONOR STAN LEE TODAY.
AND STAN, I YOU KNOW, I DON'T HAVE A LOT TO ADD OTHER THAN
THE FACT THAT TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE NOT JUST AS A ELECTED
LEADER OF THE CITY BUT REALLY AS A COMMUNITY MEMBER FOR THE
CHINESE-AMERICAN COMMUNITY FOR THE ASIAN AMERICAN COMMUNITY,
YOU MAKE US SO PROUD. YOU ARE SUCH A GREAT
REPRESENTATIVE OF WHO WE ARE AS A COMMUNITY NOT JUST FOR YOUR
PUBLIC SERVICE WITH THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AS
OUR FIREFIGHTER PROTECTING OUR FAMILIES, OUR CITIES ASSETS
AND MANY, MANY OTHER THINGS BUT ALSO THAT YOU AS A MEMBER OF
OUR COMMUNITY YOU SERVE OUR COMMUNITY IN SO MANY OTHER WAY
BUT ALSO EXTENDING MY GRATITUDE TO YOUR FAMILY, TO YOUR THREE
KIDS WHO I KNOW THAT YOU KNOW THEY BECAUSE OF YOUR SERVICE
BOTH WITH THE CITY BUT ALSO WITH THE COMMUNITY MUST HAVE
TAKEN YOU AWAY FROM THEM, YOU KNOW, FROM TIME TO TIME AND THE
SACRIFICE THAT NOT ONLY THAT YOU PERSONALLY MADE BUT YOUR
FAMILY ACTUALLY MAY THROUGH THROUGHOUT YOUR CAREER AS A
FIREFIGHTER AND SO FOR THAT WE ARE GRATEFUL TO YOU AND TO YOUR
FAMILY AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR BEING HERE TODAY.
I AGREE WITH SUPERVISOR CHEN THAT WE DON'T WHILE YOU MAY BE
OFFICIALLY RETIRING, WE DON'T THANK YOUR SPIRITS IN YOUR
SERVICE ARE RETIRING. WE KNOW THAT YOU'RE GOING TO
CONTINUE TO SERVE THE COMMUNITY AND BE WITH US SO THAT FOR THAT
WE'RE ALSO GRATEFUL. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SARTOR
. >> THANK YOU STAN.
CONGRATULATIONS. AND FIRST AND FOREMOST THANK
YOU FOR YOUR DECADES OF COURAGEOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. YOU KNOW STANDS THE KIND OF
PERSON THAT YOU WOULD SEE HIM ONE HOUR IN UNIFORM ON THE JOB
AND THEN YOU'D SEE HIM THE NEXT HOUR DOING SOMETHING THAT I
THINK IS EQUALLY IF NOT MORE IMPORTANT THAN SERVING THE
COMMUNITY. HE'S ALWAYS OUT VOLUNTEERING AT
BLOCK PARTIES AND AT FESTIVALS AND AT THE HOLIDAYS AND I'M SAD
THAT WE'LL BE LOSING YOU IN THIS ROLE.
BUT I KNOW YOU WILL PUT ALL YOUR TIME AND EFFORT TOWARDS
SERVING SAN FRANCISCO IN ANOTHER CAPACITY AND I WOULD
SAY IT IS NOT A NIGHT MARKET IN CHINATOWN WITHOUT STOPPING
BY YOUR BOOTH AND SEEING HOW GREAT OF A DJ YOU ARE.
SO THANK YOU FOR YOUR MUSIC AND YOUR SERVICE TO SAN
FRANCISCO. THANK YOU SUPERVISORS BELIEVE
ME IT TAKES A VILLAGE. I COULDN'T BE THE PERSON I WAS
ABOUT SAN FRANCISCO RIGHT? I WAS I WASN'T BORN HERE BUT I
WAS RAISED THERE MOVED HERE WHEN I WAS A HALF A YEAR OLD,
GREW UP IN PORTOLA, WENT TO SCHOOL, VISITED THE VALLEY,
GRADUATED FROM GALILEO HIGH SCHOOL.
THIS IS MY CITY. I LOVE THIS CITY.
AND AS SUPERVISOR CHEN MENTIONED I DID HAS SOME MISHAP
AT WORK AND BASICALLY THAT MISHAP GAVE ME A SECOND LEASE
IN LIFE AND I PUT ALL THAT EFFORT INTO HELPING COMMUNITY
MY WHO WAS FILMING ME TURN ME ON TO LINDA FONG FROM
IMAGINATION. SHE SHE TURNED ME ON TO GIVING
TOYS AWAY IN CHINATOWN AND IT WAS A BUG I JUST COULDN'T STOP
MYSELF. >> RIGHT.
WE START WITH 500 TOYS ONE YEAR NEXT YEAR WE HAD 4000 LAST YEAR
WE DID 3000 RIGHT? WE GAVE AWAY FIVE INCH TOYS
IN LAHAINA. BUT THE THING IS LIKE LIKE YOU
GUYS MENTIONED I AM RETIRING BUT THAT DOESN'T MEAN I STOPPED
BEING A SAN FRANCISCAN AND BELIEVE ME OUR PLAN ON A
BIGGER CHRISTMAS SEASON HOPING TO DO EVENT IN CHINATOWN MAYBE
TO LOOKING AT THIS STAGE VALLEY AND EXCELSIOR AGAIN YOU KNOW I
TRIED IN THE TENDERLOIN IT DIDN'T WORK OUT THAT WELL BUT
NOW I'M ALWAYS TRYING TO FIGURE OUT HOW TO BENEFIT THE CITY
AND EVEN IN RETIREMENT I'M ON I'M STILL SAN FRANCISCAN.
I LOVE THE CITY AND I APPRECIATE THE HONOR THIS BREAD
BESTOWED UPON ME. THANK YOU.
WELL
,DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD, YOU'VE YOUR FOLKS ARE
GOING TO COME BACK NEXT WEEK. OKAY, GREAT.
>> AND DISTRICT SEVEN SUPERVISOR OR MELGAR YOU WERE
HONORING ON A VALID ZICK AND YOU DID IT OUT IN THE
ROTUNDA AND I THANK YOU FOR THAT AND IF YOU WANT TO SAY
ANYTHING BUT OKAY THANK YOU FOR HONORING HER ON HER RETIREMENT
AND THEN DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN COLLEAGUES I HAVE TWO IN MEMORIAM TODAY
FOUR CHAIRS, INDIVIDUALS WHOSE LOSSES DEEPLY TOUCHED THE LIVES
OF SOME OF OUR CITY HALL FRIENDS AND FAMILY MEMBERS MANY
OF WHOM ARE HERE WITH US TODAY. SO I APPRECIATE YOU INDULGING
ME TO OFFER THESE IN MEMORIAM NOW FIRST I ASK THAT WE ADJOURN
TODAY'S MEETING TO HONOR THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF RODNEY JEAN
BOUTON, A BELOVED MUNI OPERATOR, A DEVOTED HUSBAND
AND A PROUD SON OF SAN FRANCISCO WHOSE PRESENCE LIT UP
EVERY ROOM AND EVERY ROUTE HE TOUCHED.
BORN ON OCTOBER 13TH, 1959 ALONGSIDE HIS TWIN BROTHER
RODERICK RODNEY WAS AFFECTIONATELY KNOWN AS PEEWEE
AND THOSE WHO KNEW HIM REMEMBER HIS BOLD SPIRIT, HIS INFECTIOUS
LAUGHTER AND THE UNMISTAKABLE JOY HE BROUGHT TO LIFE.
HE BEGAN HIS CAREER WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO MUNICIPAL
TRANSPORTATION AGENCY IN 2014 FIRST AS A 60 FOOT MOTOR COACH
OPERATOR AT FLYNN DIVISION AND LATER AS A TROLLEY COACH
OPERATOR AT THE PRESIDIO DIVISION.
HIS COLLEAGUES DESCRIBED HIM AS POSITIVE AND UPBEAT THE KIND OF
MUNI OPERATOR OPERATOR WE ALL LOVED TO BE GREETED BY SAN
FRANCISCO RIDERS SOMEONE WHO DIDN'T JUST DRIVE A BUS BUT
BUILT A COMMUNITY EVERY DAY. THROUGH HIS KINDNESS, HIS HUMOR
AND HIS CARE. RODNEY'S LIFE EXTENDED BEYOND
HIS YEARS OF PUBLIC SERVICE. HOWEVER HE WAS ENDLESSLY
CURIOUS AND HIS FRIENDS SAY A TRUE RENAISSANCE MAN, A SKILLED
CARPENTER, ENTREPRENEUR, MARTIAL ARTIST AND MUSICIAN WHO
PLAYED MULTIPLE INSTRUMENTS AND COULD COMMAND A ROOM WITH
BOTH HIS SINGING VOICE AND HIS STORYTELLING.
HE LIVED FOR ADVENTURE AND NEW EXPERIENCES WHETHER THAT MEANT
SWIMMING, SCUBA DIVING, HANG GLIDING OR SKYDIVING.
HE LOVED TO FISH, DRAW CHALLENGE ANYONE TO A GAME OF
BACKGAMMON, MONOPOLY OR SPADES. AT HIS CORE RODNEY WAS A MAN OF
DEEP CHRISTIAN FAITH. HIS RELATIONSHIP WITH GOD
ANCHORED HIS LIFE WHICH WAS INESTIMABLE.
BLESSED TOO BY HIS 40 PLUS YEAR MARRIAGE TO HIS SOUL MATE RODE
A MAN HE LIVED HIS BELIEFS DAILY THROUGH QUIET GENEROSITY,
UNWAVERING LOVE AND A COMMITMENT TO UPLIFTING OTHERS
EVEN IN DEATH. RODNEY CONTINUED HIS LEGACY OF
GIVING BACK BY DONATING HIS BODY TO THE UCSF WILLARD WILLED
BODY PROGRAM TO SUPPORT FUTURE MEDICAL EDUCATION AND RESEARCH.
RODNEY BOWDEN LIVED JOYFULLY GAVE FREELY AND LOVED WITHOUT
LIMITS. HIS PASSING LEAVES A PROFOUND
VOID IN THE HEARTS OF HIS FAMILY, FRIENDS AND COLLEAGUES
MANY HERE TODAY AND THE COUNTLESS RIDES WHOSE COMMUTES
HE MADE BETTER BY THE WARMTH OF HIS HUMANITY AND GOOD HUMOR.
HIS LEGACY OF FAITH, SERVICE, KINDNESS AND ADVENTURE LIVES ON
IN ALL WHO KNEW HIM. WE HONOR HIM TODAY NOT ONLY FOR
THE YEARS HE GAVE TO OUR CITY BUT FOR THE WAY HE LIVED FULLY
,BOLDLY AND WITH A HEART ALWAYS OPEN TO OTHERS.
ON BEHALF OF A GRATEFUL CITY, WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST
CONDOLENCES TO HIS WIFE RHONDA ,HIS FAMILY, HIS FELLOW
OPERATORS AND EVERYONE WHOSE LIVES RODNEY BALLARD MADE
BETTER. MAY HIS MEMORY CONTINUE TO
INSPIRE US AND MAY HE REST IN PEACE.
SECOND, I ASK THAT WE ALSO ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING TO
HONOR THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF ANOTHER DEVOTED PUBLIC SERVANT.
RETIRED DEPUTY SHERIFF RHONDA MARIE GAINS A DEEPLY RESPECTED
AND BELOVED MEMBER OF THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE WHO PASSED
AWAY ON MAY 28TH, 2025. RHONDA DEVOTED HER LIFE TO
PUBLIC SAFETY. BEGINNING HER DISTINGUISHED
CAREER WITH THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE ON NOVEMBER 30TH, 1992.
FOLLOWING HER GRADUATION FROM THE SANTA ROSA POLICE ACADEMY
OVER THE YEARS SHE SERVED AT COUNTY JAIL NUMBER TWO
AND COUNTY JAIL NUMBER ONE BEFORE CONTINUING HER SERVICE
IN COURT SERVICES. IN EVERY ASSIGNMENT RHONDA
CARRIED HERSELF WITH GRACE, PROFESSIONALISM AND UNWAVERING
DEDICATION TO THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
RHONDA WAS KNOWN FOR HER WARM, FRIENDLY DEMEANOR AND THE
GENUINE CONNECTIONS SHE BUILT THROUGHOUT THE DEPARTMENT.
SHE LEAVES A LASTING IMPRESSION NOT JUST OF HER WORK BUT
THROUGH THE KINDNESS, JOY AND FRIENDSHIP SHE SO FREELY
OFFERED TO THOSE AROUND HER. RHONDA EXEMPLIFIED WHAT IT
MEANS TO BE A PUBLIC SERVANT STEADY, COMPASSIONATE
AND COMMITTED TO JUSTICE AND CARE IN EQUAL MEASURE.
HER PASSING IS A HEARTBREAKING LOSS AND YET EVEN THOSE LOVED
ONES AND FAMILIES WHO GRIEVE ALSO CELEBRATE THE PROFOUND
IMPACT SHE HAD ON HER COLLEAGUES.
HER COMMUNITY AND THE INSTITUTIONS SHE SERVED SO
FAITHFULLY FOR MORE THAN THREE DECADES.
AS WE REMEMBER, RHONDA, HER FAMILY ASKS THAT WE ALL DRAW AS
INSPIRATION FOR OUR OWN PUBLIC SERVICE CAREERS THE EXAMPLE SHE
SO ABLY LIVED IN HERS EXPRESSING VALUES OF KINDNESS,
INTEGRITY AND GENEROSITY OF SPIRIT.
WE OFFER OUR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO RHONDA'S FAMILY,
FRIENDS AND FORMER COLLEAGUES WHO HAD THE HONOR OF WORKING
ALONGSIDE HER. MAY SHE REST IN PEACE AND MAY
HER LEGACY CONTINUE TO INSPIRE ALL WHO SERVE OUR CITY.
THANKS. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THE DISTRICT EIGHT HONOREE REBECCA ROTH IS
GOING TO COME BACK NEXT WEEK. AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK,
LET'S GO TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER ORDERS.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ITEMS 25 THROUGH 28 COMPRISE
THE PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE CERTIFICATION
OF THE AIR. THE FINAL ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT
REPORT FOR THE PROPOSED 3400 LAGUNA STREET PROJECT ISSUED BY
THE PLANNING COMMISSION THROUGH ITS MOTION DATED APRIL 17TH,
2025 WHICH WOULD ALLOW FOR THE DEMOLITION OF TWO OF THE FIVE
EXISTING BUILDINGS AND CONSTRUCT TWO NEW BUILDINGS
IN THE SAME LOCATIONS AS THE DEMOLISHED STRUCTURES.
THE PROPOSED PROJECT WOULD RENOVATE TWO OF THE EXISTING
BUILDINGS AND MAKE IMPROVEMENTS TO THE JULIA MORGAN BUILDING.
THE PROJECT WOULD ADD APPROXIMATELY 58,000FT2 OF
INSTITUTIONAL USE AND INCREASE THE NUMBER OF RESIDENTIAL CARE
SUITES FROM 86 TO 109. ITEM 26 IS THE MOTION TO AFFIRM
THE PLANNING COMMISSION CERTIFICATION OF THE FDR.
ITEM 27 CONDITIONALLY REVERSES THE COMMISSION'S CERTIFICATION
AND SUBJECT TO THE ADOPTION OF WRITTEN FINDINGS.
ITEM 28 IS THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS FOR
ITEMS 29 THROUGH 32. THIS IS THE PUBLIC HEARING OF
PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE APPROVAL OF A CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT AT 3400 LAGUNA STREET
DESCRIBED ABOVE. >> ITEM 30 IS THE MOTION TO
APPROVE THE DECISION OF THE PLANNING COMMISSION APPROVING A
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION. >> ITEM 31 IS THE MOTION TO
DISAPPROVE THE COMMISSION'S DECISION AND THIS ITEM IS AN
HAS AN EIGHT VOTE THRESHOLD ASSOCIATED WITH IT.
ITEM 32 IS THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS
IN THE DISAPPROVAL OF THE PROPOSED CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION. AND THE THIRD ITEM ASSOCIATED
IS OUR ITEM 33 THROUGH 36 THE PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS
INTERESTED IN THE APPROVAL OF A CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
FOR THE 3400 LAGUNA STREET PROJECT.
DESCRIBED ABOVE ITEM 34 IS THE MOTION TO APPROVE THE DECISION
OF THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION TO APPROVE THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS. ITEM 35 IS THE MOTION TO
DISAPPROVE THE COMMISSION'S DECISION AND ITEM 36 IS THE
MOTION TO DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, WE HAVE BEFORE US
THREE APPEAL HEARINGS WITH TWO APPELLANTS ON THE PROPOSED
PROJECT AT 3400 LAGUNA STREET. AS OUR CLERK WENT THROUGH THEM
ITEMS 25 THROUGH 28 COMPRISED THE APPEAL OF THE FINAL
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT CERTIFICATION WITH ONE
APPELLANT ITEMS 29 THROUGH 32 COMPRISED THE APPEAL OF THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION APPROVALS WITH TWO APPELLANTS
AND ITEMS 33 THROUGH 36 ARE THE APPEAL OF THE HISTORIC
PRESERVATION COMMISSION'S DECISION ON A CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS. >> AFTER THE HEARING THE BOARD
WILL DO THREE THINGS FIRST VOTE ON WHETHER TO AFFIRM OR
CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE FINAL AIR CERTIFICATION.
>> TWO DETERMINE WHETHER TO APPROVE OR DISAPPROVE THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION. AND THREE FINALLY WHETHER TO
APPROVE OR DISAPPROVE THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
WITHOUT OBJECTION. SINCE WE HAVE TWO APPELLANTS
ONE BEING THE PROJECT SPONSOR AND AFTER CONSULTATION WITH OUR
CLERK AND OUR CITY ATTORNEY I'M PROPOSING THAT WE PROCEED AS
FOLLOWS. FIRST WE GIVE UP TO TEN MINUTES
FOR APPELLANTS. NUMBER ONE ON THE FINAL AIR
AND THE SIU TANYA ALBUQUERQUE. THEN WE WILL HAVE PUBLIC
COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF APPELLANT NUMBER ONE AND THEIR APPEALS ON
THE FINAL AIR IN THE QUEUE. >> THEN WE WILL HAVE GIVE UP TO
TEN MINUTES TO THE SECOND APPELLANT.
ALSO THE PROJECT SPONSOR ON THE SIU AND THE CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS. THEN WE WILL GET WE WILL HEAR
PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF APPELLANT NUMBER TWO AND THEIR
APPEALS ON THE SIU AND THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS.
THEN WE WILL HAVE UP TO TEN MINUTES FROM THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENTS. >> THEN WE WILL GO BACK TO THE
PROJECT SPONSOR FOR UP TO TEN MINUTES OF TO RESPOND TO THE
OTHER PARTY. AND FINALLY WE WILL GIVE EACH
OF THE APPELLANTS THREE MINUTE THREE MINUTES OF REBUTTAL.
>> COLLEAGUES, ARE THERE ANY OBJECTIONS TO PROCEEDING
IN THAT WAY? I DON'T SEE ANYONE SO SEEING NO
OBJECTIONS. THE PUBLIC HEARINGS WILL
PROCEED AS INDICATED AND ARE NOW OPEN.
>> AND I DON'T KNOW IF SUPERVISOR CHERYL HAS ANY
INTRODUCTORY COMMENTS. NOPE.
WE'LL JUST KEEP GOING. SO COLLEAGUES, I WOULD LIKE
WELL ACTUALLY I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE THE FIRST APPELLANTS
TANYA ALBUQUERQUE TO COME FORWARD AND PRESENT THEIR CASE
ON THE FINAL AIR AND THE CONDITIONAL USE.
>> AND YOU HAVE TEN MINUTES. I'M GOING TO SPLIT MY TIME SO
CAN YOU PLEASE SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THAT MICROPHONE?
>> YES. THAT BETTER?
YOU CAN MOVE IT. YEAH, IT'S TANGIBLE.
>> YOU'RE GOING TO SPLIT YOUR TIME WITH ANOTHER WITH OUR
APPELLATE ONE TIME. OKAY.
STEVE WILLIAMS. JUST LET ME KNOW WHEN I SHOULD
START. >> START?
I THINK I HAVE A PRESENTATION ON THERE.
SUPPOSED TO BE PRESENTED. MR..
MR.. OKAY.
OKAY. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS TANYA ALBUQUERQUE. I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF THE
NEIGHBORHOOD ORGANIZATION SAVE THE MARINA'S HERITAGE.
WE ARE APPEALING THE APPROVALS BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION OF A
MASSIVE CONSTRUCTION PROJECT BY HERITAGE ON THE MARINA AT 3400
LAGUNA AND OPPOSING THE HERITAGE APPEAL OF A DECISION
BY THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION.
AT THE APRIL 17TH JOINT HEARING 3400 LAGUNA IS SAN FRANCISCO'S
NEWEST HISTORIC LANDMARK. THE CENTERPIECE IS A CENTURY
OLD BEAUTIFUL JULIA MORGAN DESIGN MANSION.
THE HERITAGE PLANS TO TEAR DOWN TWO SMALL STRUCTURES
AND REPLACE THEM WITH FOUR STORY PLUS MODERN BUILDINGS
THAT WILL SURROUND AND TOWER OVER THE MANSION HIDING MUCH OF
IT AND MANY OF ITS PROTECTED AND DISTINGUISHED FEATURES FROM
PUBLIC VIEW. THESE NEW BUILDINGS WILL ADD
60,000FT2 TO THE PROPERTY BUT CREATE ONLY 23 NEW UNITS.
I WANT TO RESPOND TO THE HERITAGE'S APPEAL WHEN THE
HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION ISSUED THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS FOR THIS PROJECT.
THEY ATTACHED A CONDITION. IT IS CALLED CONDITION OF
APPROVAL ONE IT IS LIMITED AND REASONABLE.
IT SAYS BEFORE GETTING A BUILDING PERMIT THE HERITAGE
MUST WORK WITH THE HPC SUBCOMMITTEE CALLED THE
ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE ON MASSING AND ARCHITECTURAL
DETAILS. THE HERITAGE WANTS YOU TO GUT
CONDITION ONE BY TAKING AWAY THE AREA'S ROLE AND NOT
ALLOWING ANY CHANGES TO MASSING OF THE NEW BUILDINGS.
>> THE RECORD IS CLEAR THAT THE HPC WOULD NOT HAVE APPROVED THE
CERTIFICATE WITHOUT CONDITION ONE.
PUT SIMPLY IT WAS A COMPROMISE. THE HPC WANTED TO SUPPORT THE
OVERALL PROJECT BUT AS EXPERTS IN ARCHITECTURE AND HISTORIC
PRESERVATION THEY HAD SERIOUS CONCERNS ABOUT THE IMPACT ON
THIS LANDMARK. ESPECIALLY CONCERNING TO THEM
WAS THE SIZE AND HEIGHT OF THE PROPOSED BUILDING ON FRANCISCO
STREET WHICH WILL HIDE THE MANSION AND TOWER OVER IT.
THE HPC COMPARED THE CURRENT VIEW OF THE MANSION TO THE
HERITAGE'S PROPOSAL AND CAME UP WITH A REASONABLE SOLUTION THAT
ENABLES THE PROJECT TO MOVE FORWARD BUT WITH OVERSIGHT
AND MAYBE CHANGES AS NEEDED TO PRESERVE THIS LANDMARK.
NEXT SLIDE. GRANTED THE SITUATION IS NOT
TYPICAL. NORMALLY AN OWNER WOULD WORK
WITH THE RC AND THEN ASK THE FULL HPC TO APPROVE A
CERTIFICATE. >> THE HERITAGE CHOSE TO SKIP
THIS STEP AND TRIED TO JAM ALL APPROVALS TOGETHER IN ONE JOINT
HEARING IT THOUGHT IT COULD GET EVERYTHING IT WANTED WITHOUT
PUSHBACK. NOW IT'S COMPLAINING BECAUSE
THE HPC DIDN'T GO ALONG BUT BECAUSE THIS SITUATION IS
UNUSUAL THE HPC WAS EXTREMELY CAUTIOUS AND DELIBERATIVE.
THE HPC TURNED AGAIN AND AGAIN DURING THE HEARING TO THE
DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY AND COMMISSION STAFF FOR LEGAL
ASSURANCE THAT IT COULD MAKE THE CERTIFICATE CONDITIONAL.
THE ADVICE THEY GOT WAS YOU HAVE FULL AUTHORITY TO ADOPT
THIS CONDITION AND THE MORE GENERAL IT IS THE MORE
FLEXIBILITY YOU HAVE. NOW THE HERITAGE SAYS THIS
LIMITED AND COMMON SENSE CONDITION IS ILLEGAL DELEGATION
TO VAGUE AND VIOLATES THE PERMIT STREAMLINING ACT.
THESE CLAIMS ARE FALSE. EVERYONE AT THE HEARING THE
CITY ATTORNEY COMMISSION STAFF PLANNING COMMISSION AND HPC
MEMBERS BELIEVED AND RELIED ON THE FACT THAT THE HPC HAD THE
LEGAL AUTHORITY TO ADOPT CONDITION ONE.
IF YOU SIDE WITH THE HERITAGE ON THIS POINT YOU'RE TELLING
EVERY DEPARTMENT AND COMMISSION THAT THEY CANNOT RELY ON THE
LEGAL ADVICE GIVEN TO THEM BY THE CITY ATTORNEY.
THE HERITAGE ARGUES THAT CONDITION ONE NEXT SLIDE IS TOO
VAGUE, DOESN'T HAVE A DEADLINE, DOESN'T HAVE A WAY TO APPEAL.
BUT ITS PROPOSED REVISION TO CONDITIONAL ON ADDRESS NONE OF
THESE THINGS BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT THE HERITAGE'S REAL
CONCERNS WHICH ARE JUST AVOIDING ANY OVERSIGHT BY THE
I.R.S. AND MAKING SURE NO ONE TELLS THEM THIS PROJECT IS JUST
TOO BIG. CONDITION ONE IS IS CLEAR,
LIMITED AND REASONABLE. THE HERITAGE IS POSITION THAT
IT'S IMPOSSIBLE TO BUILD 23 UNITS WITH ANYTHING LESS THAN
60,000 NEW SQUARE FEET AND DISFIGURING A LANDMARK IS
THE UNREASONABLE ONE. THE HERITAGE ALSO SAYS
CONDITION ONE VIOLATES THE PERMIT STREAMLINING ACT BUT
THIS ACT DOESN'T APPLY TO POST DISCRETIONARY APPROVAL PRE
BUILDING PERMIT REVIEWS SUCH AS CONDITION ONE AT THE HEARING.
NO ONE INCLUDING NO ONE FROM S.F. PLANNING OBJECTED TO
CONDITION ONE NOW PLANNING CLAIMS IN ITS RESPONSE THAT DUE
TO TIME AND FACILITATION CONSTRAINTS THE REGULATORY
FRAMEWORK AND PROCEDURES WERE NOT READILY AVAILABLE AT THE
HEARING. >> IT'S OFFENSIVE FOR PLANNING
TO SAY THEY WERE UNPREPARED FOR THE HEARING.
THEY CHOSE TO SCHEDULE. WHAT PLANNING IS REALLY SAYING
IS THAT IT WASN'T PREPARED FOR THE HPC TO NOT GO ALONG WITH
RUBBERSTAMPING THIS PROJECT. >> IF YOU DISAGREE WITH THE
CITY ATTORNEY'S INTERPRETATION OF THE LAW, THE SOLUTION IS NOT
TO UNDERMINE THE HPC BY MAKING THE CONDITION TOOTHLESS AS
HERITAGE REQUESTS BUT INSTEAD INVALIDATE THE CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS AND HAVE THE HERITAGE FOLLOW THE TYPICAL
PROCESS OF WORKING WITH THE RC AND THEN HAVING ITS PROJECT
VOTED ON BY THE FULL HPC. WE STRONGLY SUPPORT THIS
ALTERNATIVE. >> WE BELIEVE THAT THE HPC
SHOULD HAVE APPROVED THE CERTIFICATE IN THE FIRST PLACE.
WE THINK THIS PROJECT DOESN'T COMPLY WITH THE LEGAL STANDARDS
FOR CONSTRUCTION ON AND AROUND A LANDMARK AND WE BELIEVE IT
VIOLATES THE NOTICE OF SPECIAL RESTRICTIONS ON THE PROPERTY.
BUT IF YOU UPHOLD THE CERTIFICATE THEN DON'T CHANGE
CONDITION ONE. THE HPC ONLY APPROVED THE
CERTIFICATE BECAUSE IT WAS ASSURED THAT CONDITION ONE WAS
FULLY ENFORCEABLE. THE CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS AND CONDITION ONE MUST STAND OR FALL
TOGETHER. >> PLEASE STOP MY TIME.
THANK YOU. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS STEVE WILLIAMS AND I'M HERE TO HELP REPRESENT
THE NEIGHBORS AND THE APPELLANTS IN THIS CASE THE
BOARD MUST ACT TODAY TO GRANT THE APPEAL AND SET ASIDE THE
NEW Q GIVEN TO HERITAGE BY PLANNING AND SET FORTH IN OUR
BRIEFING HERITAGE'S CURRENTLY IN VIOLATION OF ITS EXISTING Q
AND CANNOT UNDER THE PLANNING CODE OR STATE LAW BE GRANTED A
NEW CONDITIONAL USE UNTIL THE VIOLATIONS ARE ADDRESSED
AND CORRECTED? PLANNING SHOULD NOT HAVE
STARTED THE PROCESS WITHOUT FIRST ADDRESSING THE
VIOLATIONS. HERITAGE IS A RESIDENTIAL CARE
FACILITY. ALL OF ITS ACTIVITIES THESE
MUST FALL UNDER THE SIU. IT MAY ONLY OPERATE AS A
CONDITIONAL USE IN THIS RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT CANNOT OPERATE ANY OTHER WAY IN THIS NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT'S ORIGINAL. SEE YOU AS A CARE FACILITY WAS
GRANDFATHERED IN WHEN THE CITY REZONED IN THE 20S AND WAS
REVISITED IN 1953 62 AND 86 BECAUSE IT OPERATES ONLY AS A
CONDITIONAL USE AGAIN ALL ACTIVITIES IT UNDERTAKES IN THE
NEIGHBORHOOD MUST FALL WITHIN THE ALLOWABLE PARAMETERS
AND SPECIFIC LANGUAGE OF THE EXISTING SIU ANY SIGNIFICANT
ENLARGEMENT ALTERATION OR INTENSIFICATION BEYOND WHAT IS
SPECIFICALLY ALLOWED IN THE EXISTING SIU REQUIRES A NEW SIU
UNDER PLANNING CODE SECTION 178.
>> THE INCLUSION OF OTHER UNITS IS NOT SEPARATE.
IT'S PART OF THE HERITAGE FACILITY AND MUST BE ADDRESSED
AND INCLUDED IN ANY NEW SIU AND AS PART OF THE PROJECT
DESCRIPTION IN THE SIU AND THE AIR OUR HERITAGE HAS VIOLATED
SIU BY ACQUIRING NEW BUILDINGS AND MAKING THOSE BUILDINGS PART
OF ITS FACILITY. IT GREATLY ENLARGED, ALTERED
AND INTENSIFIED ITS COMMERCIAL OPERATION IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
BY ADDING OVER 11,000FT2 TO IT WITHOUT ANY CHANGE IN ITS SIU.
>> THE THRESHOLD FOR A NEW SIU IS AN ADDITION OF 500FT2
AND THAT'S UNDER SECTION 178 C. APPELLANTS HAVE POINTED OUT
IN ITS WRITTEN SUBMISSION AND MAPPED OUT IN ITS
BRIEFINGS. HERITAGE ACQUIRED THREE
BUILDINGS WITH TEN ADDITIONAL RESIDENTIAL UNITS AND HAS
TURNED ALL OF THOSE UNITS INTO AN INTEGRATED PART OF ITS
COMMERCIAL FACILITY. THESE UNITS ARE TEN NATURALLY
AFFORDABLE ALL RENT CONTROLLED FAMILY SIZE HOUSING UNITS THE
KIND OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING THAT EVERY MEMBER OF THIS BOARD HAS
PLEDGED TO PROTECT AND PRESERVE.
TODAY IS THE DAY WHEN YOU MUST HONOR AND FULFILL THAT PROMISE
THAT YOU MADE TO EVERY ONE OF YOUR CONSTITUENTS.
THE EXPLANATION PROVIDED BY HERITAGE THAT THESE UNITS ARE
MERELY BEING RENTED WITHOUT HERITAGE WITH HERITAGE AS A
LANDLORD. >> THESE STATEMENTS ARE SIMPLY
NOT TRUE. THESE TEN UNITS ARE
SPECIFICALLY OFFERED ONLY AND EXCLUDE CIVILLY TO THE
SENIOR CLIENTELE AS PART OF THE INSTITUTION.
ON ITS WEBSITE IT SPECIFICALLY STATES THAT THESE UNITS ARE
OFFERED EXACTLY ON THE SAME TERMS AS ALL THE OTHER UNITS
IN THE HISTORIC BUILDING SAME AMENITIES, SAME SECURITY, SAME
HOUSEKEEPING, IDENTICAL TO THE UNITS IN THE HISTORIC BUILDING.
TAKING THESE UNITS AWAY FROM THE CITY'S SUPPLY OF RENT
CONTROLLED HOUSING STOCK AND MAKING THEM PART OF THIS
INSTITUTION IS CLEARLY OUTSIDE OF THE PARAMETERS OF THE
EXISTING SIU. VIOLATES NUMEROUS PROVISIONS OF
THE PLANNING CODE. HERITAGE TOOK OVER THESE RENT
CONTROL UNITS WITHOUT ANY CHANGES TO IT.
SEE YOU TRANSFORM THEM FROM RESIDENTIAL INTO INSTITUTE
ADDITIONAL USE WITHOUT AN APPLICATION FOR THAT CONVERSION
AND WITHOUT AN APPLICATION FOR THE MERGER OF THE UNITS BOTH OF
WHICH ARE REQUIRED UNDER SECTION 317.
IGNORING THESE VIOLATIONS PLANNING HAS ADDRESSED THE THE
CLAIMS FROM APPELLANT RESPONSE FORUM PAGE SIX.
PLANNING DEPARTMENT RESPONSES THERE ARE NO VIOLATIONS OF THE
CONDITIONAL USE PLANNING SAYS ALL THESE UNITS WITHIN THE
BUILDINGS REMAIN AS RESIDENTIAL USES.
THIS IS NOT TRUE HERITAGE SUPPLIES NO RESIDENTIAL HOUSING
IT IS AN INSTITUTIONAL. >> PROJECT BEFORE YOU IF THEY
WERE HOUSING THEY WOULD HAVE TO SUPPLY 20% OF AFFORDABLE
HOUSING. THERE IS NO AFFORDABLE HOUSING
IN THIS. THIS ARE ALL LUXURY RESIDENTIAL
CARE UNITS. HERITAGE HAS DESTROYED THE
AFFORDABLE UNITS AND THOSE UNITS ARE NOW PART OF THE
INSTITUTION. THE ACTIONS TAKEN BY HERITAGE
ARE NO DIFFERENT FROM THAT TAKEN BY THE ACADEMY OF ART
UNIVERSITY ONLY ON A SMALLER SCALE TRANSFORMING RESIDENTIAL
UNITS INTO INSTITUTE NATIONAL UNITS.
>> CLEAR AND UNDENIABLE VIOLATIONS OF THE PLANNING CODE
BOARD MUST ACT TODAY TO CORRECT THESE VIOLATIONS AND IF YOU
WILL, FOR ANY QUESTIONS YOU MAY HAVE.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MR. WILLIAMS.
I DON'T SEE ANY QUESTIONS FROM COLLEAGUES SO WE WILL NOW
INVITE PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF THIS.
APPELLANTS ON THEIR APPEALS OF THE FINAL AIR AND SEE YOU IF
YOU WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS US IN SUPPORT OF THIS APPEAL.
THESE APPEALS LINE UP TO OUR LEFT YOUR RIGHT AND WE CAN HEAR
FROM OUR FIRST PERSON. >> IT'S ANOTHER EXAMPLE YOU
DISCRIMINATORY PRACTICES AND TRICKING DEVICES OR YOU
PRICE FIXING AND YOU PRICE GOUGING ON HOUSING YOU ALWAYS
CLAIM THAT YOU'RE GOING TO BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
THEN YOU CLAIM THAT YOU'RE GOING TO BUILD IT FOR SENIOR
CITIZENS. BUT YET WHEN YOU PROVE IN THE
PROCESS STARTS TO ACCEPT APPLICATIONS OUT OF THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE ON HOUSING. YOU SAID THE REQUIREMENT TO BE
A TENANT BASED ON THEIR AND MY SCALE AND YOU SAID THE
PERCENTAGE IS ALWAYS FROM 6070 TO 8090%.
THE AM PI SCALE WHICH IS A HIGHER.
COME BACK AND SCALE AND YOU IN VIOLATION OF YOUR OWN
CHARTER RULES PURSUANT TO RULE 14 OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO CHARTER THAT SAYS EACH AND EVERY HOUSING
OPPORTUNITY IS SUPPOSED TO BE FOR VERY LOW AND LOW INCOME
BRACKET PEOPLE. BUT YET WHEN YOU GET TO THE
FINAL STEP YOU DELIBERATELY MIS CATEGORIZE THE USE AND MAKE THE
REQUIREMENT TO BE A TENANT IN THE BUILDING UP TO 100
20,000, 80,000, 90,000 A YEAR WHEREAS THOSE VERY LOW AND LOW
INCOME BRACKET PEOPLE ARE NOT INCLUDED IN THE HOUSING
OPPORTUNITY. >> AND ABOUT YOU MESS WITH THIS
HISTORICAL BUILDING YOU DID THE SAME THING TO THE HISTORICAL
BUILDINGS IN THE FILLMORE AREA. YOU CLAIM THAT THE BLACKS WHO
HAD THOSE HISTORICAL HOMES WOULD BE ABLE TO MOVE BACK INTO
THEIR HOMES AND PAY THE SAME PRICE AND YOU ELIMINATE THOSE
HOMES AND BY THE SAME RESPONSE YOU BUILD SKYSCRAPERS IN OUR.
PRICE THEM WHERE THEY ENDED UP LOSING THEIR PROPERTY AND ENDED
UP HOMELESS OUT IN THE STREET. SO YOU ARE NOT KEEPING YOUR
WORD YOU GOT A PATTERN OF DOING THIS FOR THE PAST WELL OVER
SEVERAL DECADES AND THEN ABOUT YOU TALKING ABOUT PROTECTING A
HISTORICAL BUILDING IN SOME AREAS LIKE YOU DID IN THE
SUNSET BUT YOU'RE NOT DOING IT IN THIS AREA IN JAPANTOWN.
>> AND OBJECT TO IT THINGS. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISOR MY
NAME IS MIKE KEEBLE. I'M A RESIDENT IN THE MARINA.
I'M ANTICIPATING THAT THE HERITAGE ON THE MARINA WILL
ONCE AGAIN RAISE THE ECONOMIC NECESSITY ARGUMENT TO SUPPORT
ITS PROPOSED 60,000FT2 OF NEW CONSTRUCTION.
IN OUR MEETINGS WITH THE SUPERVISOR AND ALONG WITH THEIR
STAFF, WE AS A COMMUNITY ORGANIZER WERE CONTINUALLY TOLD
AND ADVISED THAT ECONOMIC NECESSITY IS NOT THE STANDARD
USED TO DETERMINE IF THIS PROPOSAL SHOULD RECEIVE
REGULATORY APPROVAL. IMPORTANTLY, HERITAGE HAS NEVER
EVEN SUPPORTED THAT ARGUMENT OF ECONOMIC NECESSITY THE HERITAGE
2023 TAX RETURN THE LAST AVAILABLE SHOWS THAT IT HAS
ASSETS OF OVER 121 MILLION. AGAINST JUST 1010 MILLION
IN LIABILITIES MAKING IT ONE OF THE RICHEST LIQUID NONPROFITS
IN SAN FRANCISCO ANY OPERATING LOSSES IT MAY HAVE SUSTAINED
OVER THE LAST SEVERAL YEARS WERE SELF INFLICTED AS THE
HERITAGE HAS IN RECENT YEARS SYSTEMATICALLY REMOVED 16 UNITS
REDUCING ITS UNIT COUNT FROM 102 TO 86.
AND AT THE SAME TIME IT LEFT ANOTHER 7600FT2 FORMERLY A
SKILLED NURSING FACILITY LAY VACANT THAT VACANT FACILITY
PROBABLY HAS THE CAPACITY FOR AT LEAST ANOTHER EIGHT UNITS.
HERITAGE HAS DONE OVER THE LAST SEVERAL YEARS REDUCED ITS
AVAILABLE SENIOR HOUSING BY APPROXIMATELY 24 UNITS.
>> YET THE PROPOSED NEW CONSTRUCTION WILL ALLOW AND ADD
ONLY 23 UNITS NEARLY TWICE ZERO SQUARE FEET PER UNIT.
THIS IS NOT AFFORDABLE SENIOR HOUSING.
HERITAGE PROPOSES TO UPGRADE FROM AN EXPENSIVE SENIOR
HOUSING TO ULTRA LUXURY UNITS THAT WILL BE AMONGST THE MOST
EXPENSIVE IN CALIFORNIA FOR THE GROWING POPULATIONS OF SENIORS
IN SAN FRANCISCO THE WEALTHIEST 1% WOULD HAVE A PLAN.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
I HAVE AUDIO AND VISUAL BUILD. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS TERRY PECKHAM. I'M RESIDENT OF THE MARINA
AND I'VE BEEN VERY INTERESTED IN THIS PROJECT.
I WANT TO GET TO MY VIDEO. I WAS AT THE MARCH ART THE
APRIL MEETING WITH THE H R C IT IS WITHOUT A DOUBT THAT THEY
WOULD NOT HAVE APPROVED THE CIA WITHOUT.
THAT CONDITION AND I THINK SOME OF THE CLIPS FROM THAT REALLY
REALLY POINT THAT FACT OUT SO I'D LIKE TO GET THAT STARTED
PROJECT AND WE HAVE MEMBERS OF THIS COMMISSION WHO HAVE
EXPRESSED SOME CONCERN THAT WE LOOK INTO FURTHER DETAIL.
>> SO I'M ASKING YOU AS THE COMMISSION STAFF AND THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE TO HELP US MOVE.
ON A GOOD POSITIVE STEP FORWARD.
CONSIDERING WHAT HAS BEEN EXPRESSED TODAY.
>> ALL RIGHT. STEP IN JUST FOR A SECOND TO
RESPOND. THANK YOU SO MUCH, MR. DEPUTY
CITY ATTORNEY KRISTEN JOHNSON. AGAIN.
SO I THINK THERE ARE TWO PATHS THAT ARE BEING DISCUSSED AND I
JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT EVERYBODY IS VERY CLEAR ON WHAT
THEY ARE. ONE OF THEM WOULD BE THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS COULD BE APPROVED WITH THE
CONDITION THAT STAFF GO BACK AND WORK WITH THE R C TO
FINALIZE SOME OF THE SPECIFIC DETAILS AND YOU COULD BE VERY
SPECIFIC ABOUT WHICH PORTIONS OF THE PROJECT DETAILS YOU
WANTED TO BE FOCUSED ON OR YOU COULD BE A LITTLE BIT MORE
GENERAL. >> THE OTHER PATH IS THE ONE
THAT I THINK THAT THE COMMISSION WAS JUST DISCUSSING
WHICH WOULD BE TO SORT OF PRESS PAUSE HERE ON THE PROJECT
APPROVALS, GO BACK FOR FURTHER WORK EITHER BEFORE THE FULL HPC
OR JUST BEFORE THE ARCHITECTURE COMMITTEE AND THEN HAVE IT COME
BACK TO THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
SO I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT EVERYBODY UNDERSTANDS
THOSE ARE THE TWO DIFFERENT PATHS THAT WE'RE TALKING ABOUT.
>> I MEAN I THINK IT'S ALL IN THE WORDING OF THE
CONDITIONS ON WHICH YOU SEND IT BACK.
>> I MEAN I THINK YOU CAN SET THE SCOPE OF THE REVIEW BY THE
I.R.S. BY YOUR CONDITIONS OF APPROVAL SO YOU CAN DETERMINE
HOW MUCH OF THE PROJECT THAT THEY ARE ACTUALLY LOOKING AT.
I THOUGHT THAT I UNDERSTOOD FROM SOME OF THE COMMISSIONERS
THAT THERE WERE VERY SPECIFIC ASPECTS OF THE PROJECT ROOFLINE
AND THINGS LIKE THAT THAT YOU WANTED CONSIDERED SO I THINK
YOU COULD TAILOR THE REFERRAL POLICY SO THAT IT'S NOT SORT OF
A GLOBAL DECISION. >> THANK YOU.
CAN WE HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER?
>> AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS TINA MATT THE
HERITAGE PROPOSAL TO REMOVE THE R C FROM THE APPROVAL PROCESS
CUTS THE HEART OUT OF CONDITION ONE AND IS COMPLETELY CONTRARY
TO THE H R C'S INTENTION. >> LET'S CONTINUE WITH THE
EXCERPTS THE COMMITTEE HAVE IN TERMS WHAT DO WE MEAN BY.
DETAILS THOSE DETAILS MEAN THAT.
THAT THE AGENCY HAS THE AUTHORITY TO SAY THE THE LAST X
NUMBER OF FEET OF THIS PROPOSED BUILDING MUST BE SHORTENED TO
TWO FLOORS OR THE LAST X NUMBER OF FEET OF THIS BUILDING WE
DON'T WANT AT ALL. WE JUST WANT THE BUILDING TO BE
SHORTER IN TERMS OF LENGTH. DO THEY HAVE THAT AUTHORITY?
THE ANSWER IS YES. IF YOU CONDITION IT IN YOUR
MOTION TODAY. THE WAY I UNDERSTAND IT, THE
MOTION IS TO APPROVE THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
BUT REQUIRE THAT THE PROJECT GO BACK BEFORE THE ARCHITECTURE
REVIEW COMMITTEE FOR FINAL MASSING AND DETAILS AND IT.
AND IT SHOULD BE THAT GENERIC I WELL I THINK IT GIVES IT MORE I
DON'T WANT THE I DON'T WANT THE ABILITY YES I DON'T WANT
SPECIFICITY IT HAS TO BE GENERIC IT'S THAT I SUGGESTING
THAT THE GENERAL IT IS THE MORE FLEXIBILITY YOU HAVE.
>> I ACCEPT THAT MOTION THANK YOU.
I THINK WE HAVE A MOTION IN A SECOND.
>> VERY GOOD COMMISSIONERS. IF THERE'S NO FURTHER
DELIBERATION AND THERE IS A MOTION THAT HAS BEEN SECONDED
TO APPROVE THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS ADDING A
CONDITION THAT THE PROJECT BE TURNED TO THE R C FOR FINAL
MASSING AND DETAILS ON THAT MOTION COMMISSIONER MORONEY I.
MR. BALDAUF I MR. VERGARA YES. COMMISSIONER WRIGHT EXCUSE ME
COMMISSIONER FOLEY I YOU KNOW AND I GET SWORN IN COMMISSION
PRESIDENT MATSUDA YES, SOME OF COMMISSIONERS THAT MOTION
PASSES 5 TO 1 WITH COMMISSIONER I GUESS WARREN VOTING AGAINST.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> CAN YOU TURN THEM OFF? GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS BART DRAPER AND I LIVE AT 1563 FRANCISCO STREET
DIRECTLY SOUTH OF THE HERITAGE .
>> I WANT TO BRING TO YOUR ATTENTION A LACK OF ANALYSIS
RELATED TO THE NOTICE OF SPECIAL RESTRICTIONS OR THE NSA
ARE ASSOCIATED WITH THIS PROPERTY AS YOU'RE PROBABLY
AWARE. ALL HISTORIC LANDMARKS
INCLUDING 3400 LAGUNA STREET HAVE AN INSIDE RECORDED TO
PREVENT HARMFUL OR HARMFUL CHANGES ON MARCH 18TH 2025 AN
NSR WAS FILED FOR 3400 LAGUNA INCORPORATING ORDINANCE NUMBER
3O2-24 WHICH DESIGNATES IT A LANDMARK.
>> THE ORDINANCE SPECIFIES THAT THE FACADES MASSING ROOFLINES
ORNAMENTATION AND LANDSCAPE SHAPING OF THE 1925 MORGAN
BUILDING AND THE 1929 STONE COTTAGE MUST BE PRESERVED OR
RESTORED IN KIND. >> THE HERITAGE AS PROPOSED
PROJECT WOULD VIOLATE THESE PROJECTS PROTECTIONS.
OBSCURING FACADES AND ROOF LINES OVERWHELMING THE MORGAN
BUILDING AND DAMAGING KEY ARCHITECTURAL ELEMENTS
EFFECTIVE EARLY UNDERMINING THE LANDMARK DESIGNATION.
DESPITE THIS THE NASSAU WAS NOT MENTIONED IN ANY OF THE FOUR
MOTIONS PREPARED FOR S.F. PLANNING BY S.F. PLANNING STAFF
FOR THE APRIL 17TH HEARING EVEN THOUGH IT HAD BEEN RECORDED A
MONTH EARLIER. AND PLANNING WAS INVOLVED
IN THE 2024 LANDMARK DESIGNATION PROCESS NEITHER THE
HERITAGE THE PLANNING COMMISSION OR THE HISTORIC
PRESERVATION COMMITTEE EVALUATED THE PROJECT AGAINST
THE NASSAU. THIS OVERSIGHT IS YET ANOTHER
REASON TO OVERTURN THE FINAL AIR THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION OR AT A MINIMUM TO DENY THE CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS. THE NSAS DESERVES SERIOUS
CONSIDERATION AND THE ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE
IS PROBABLY THE BEST PLACE TO DO THAT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS MARION YANG AND I'VE BEEN IN A THIS NEIGHBORHOOD FOR
OVER 40 YEARS. THE HERITAGE HOUSE IS A
NEIGHBORHOOD HISTORICAL LANDMARK.
>> WHY DO WE HAVE HISTORICAL BUILDING LANDMARKS?
IS IT NOT FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE PROPERTY OWNER?
IT'S BECAUSE SAN FRANCISCO RECOGNIZE IT FOR ITS BEAUTY
AND HISTORICAL SIGNIFICANCE. >> THIS JULIA MORGAN BUILDING
JUST HAD HIS HUNDREDTH ANNIVERSARY.
>> JULIA WAS ONE OF THE FEW WOMEN ARCHITECT DURING THE
1900S. >> THESE BUILDINGS ARE HER
LEGACY AND NEED TO BE ACCESSIBLE VISUALLY TO EVERYONE
. >> IT IS A PRIVILEGE TO OWN A
HISTORICAL LANDMARK BUT ONE THAT COMES WITH REASONABLE
LIMITATIONS ON WHAT WE CAN DO TO THE PROPERTY.
>> SAN FRANCISCO PLANNING CALLS THIS PROPERTY NECESSARY VERY
DESIRABLE COMPATIBLE WITH THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
THE NEIGHBORHOOD THE NEIGHBORHOOD DISAGREES.
>> THE NEIGHBORHOOD VALUES THE LANDMARK AND ONCE THE
ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE TO DO WHAT IS NECESSARY TO
PROTECT IT. >> TO EVEN GET THIS HEARING WE
NEEDED TO SUPPORT THE SUPPORT OF AT LEAST 20% OF THE OWNERS
OR RESIDENTS WITHIN 300FT OF THE HERITAGE WE WENT BEYOND THE
MINIMUM WE HAD 32% OF THE NEIGHBORS AND OVER 200 PEOPLE
SIGNED THE PEW PETITION. STILL GROWING IN THE DAYS
LEADING UP TO THE HEARING, OVER 125 CONCERNED CITIZENS HAVE
WRITTEN EVERY SUPERVISOR ASKING YOU TO SUPPORT AND ON OUR
APPEAL TO DENY TO HERITAGE PRIOR TO THE APRIL 17TH HEARING
SAN FRANCISCO PLANNING GOT 123 LETTERS AGAINST THIS PROJECT
IN JUST TEN DAYS. >> THE NEIGHBORHOOD IS SENDING
THE BOARD TO SUPERVISE A MESSAGE.
>> WE ARE SUPPORTIVE OF SENIOR HOUSING.
>> WE ARE NOT ANTI DEVELOP. WE WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. HELLO MY NAME IS ARIELLA
ALBUQUERQUE. I'M A RISING SENIOR AT THE
URBAN SCHOOL OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I'VE LIVED ACROSS THE
STREET FROM THE HERITAGE MY ENTIRE LIFE.
I'M INTERESTED IN PUBLIC POLICY AND LAW AND I VOLUNTEER WITH
TWO LEGAL NONPROFITS INCLUDING THE SAN FRANCISCO HOUSING
RIGHTS COALITION. >> I UNDERSTAND THE URGENT NEED
FOR MORE HOUSING IN OUR CITY. I ALSO BELIEVE STRONGLY IN THE
IMPORTANCE OF THE RULE OF LAW, ESPECIALLY WHEN IT COMES TO
PRESERVING AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND PROTECTING OUR CITY'S
HISTORIC LANDMARKS. THIS BRINGS ME TO MY CONCERNS
AND QUESTIONS ABOUT THE EXPANSION OF THE HERITAGE WHY
WAS THE HERITAGE ALLOWED TO ACQUIRE AND INCORPORATE
NEIGHBORING BUILDINGS INTO ITS BUSINESS OPERATIONS WITHOUT
COMPLETING THE LEGALLY REQUIRED STEPS TO DO SUCH A CHANGE
IN USE? >> WHY IS IT CONSIDERED SOUND
PUBLIC POLICY TO PERMIT THE CONVERSION OF RENT CONTROLLED
AFFORDABLE HOUSING INTO LUXURY SENIOR UNITS THAT ARE
UNAFFORDABLE TO MOST SAN FRANCISCANS?
WHY WOULD SAN FRANCISCO ALLOW ONE OF ITS NEWEST HISTORIC
LANDMARKS TO BE BOXED IN BY LARGER MODERN BUILDINGS ON
THREE SIDES? WE WOULDN'T LET THIS HAPPEN TO
OTHER HISTORIC LANDMARKS LIKE PALACE OF FINE ARTS ARE QUITE
TOWER. >> FINALLY, WHY IS 60,000
SQUARE FEET OF NEW CONSTRUCTION NECESSARY TO ADD JUST 23 UNITS?
THAT SCALE RAISES QUESTIONS ABOUT HOW MUCH OF THIS PROJECT
ACTUALLY SERVES HOUSING NEEDS VERSUS COMMERCIAL EXPANSION.
I APPRECIATE YOUR TIME AND CONSIDERATION AND I
RESPECTFULLY ASK THAT YOU UPHOLDS FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT
TO EQUITABLE HOUSING, LEGAL INTEGRITY AND HISTORIC
PRESERVATION. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. IT'S FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> PLEASE. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS TODD PAULA. I'M A RESIDENT OF FRANCISCO
STREET AND A VOICE FOR THE NUMEROUS OTHER SIDE OF EMAILED
INTO YOUR OFFICES. I WANT TO URGE YOU TO DENY THE
HERITAGE ON THE MARINA'S APPEAL TO REMOVE THE CONDITION OR
CRYING REQUIRING COLLABORATION WITHIN THE HISTORIC
PRESERVATION COMMISSION'S ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE
ON DESIGNING AND MASSING REVISIONS.
THIS CONDITION WAS ESSENTIAL TO THE SPEAKER'S APPROVAL OF THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS AND CANNOT BE REMOVED WITHOUT
UNDERMINING THE APPROVAL ITSELF .
HPC MEMBERS VOICED CONCERNS AS THE PROJECT'S IMPACT OF THE
LANDMARK JULIA MORGAN MANSION. THEIR APPROVAL OF THE CEO WAS
BASED ON ASSURANCES FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE THAT
THEY HAD THE AUTHORITY TO MAKE A SEAL CONDITIONAL WITHOUT THE
ARK'S CONDITION THE CEO WOULD NOT HAVE PASSED.
OVERTURNING THIS NOW WOULD UNDERCUT THE AUTHORITY OF THE
HPC AND THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE.
THERE IS NO LEGAL BASIS TO REMOVE THIS CONDITION.
IF YOU DISAGREE WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AS
INTERPRETED SECTION, THE CORRECT ACTION IS TO INVALIDATE
THE COA NOT REMOVE THE CONDITION AND REQUIRE THE
PROJECT TO GO THROUGH THE FULL HPC REVIEW PROCESS.
ADDITIONALLY, I URGE YOU TO OVERTURN THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S APPROVAL OF THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZED
OPTION AND THE ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT.
THE HERITAGE VIOLATED CITY LAW BY CONVERTING TEN RENT
CONTROLLED RESIDENTIAL UNITS INTO INSTITUTIONAL USE
MIRRORING THE EXACT SAME CONDUCT THAT LED TO A $60
MILLION SETTLEMENT WITH THE ACADEMY OF ART.
THIS UNLAWFUL REMOVAL OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING SHOULD BE
PENALIZED NOT REWARDED WITH NEW ENTITLEMENTS.
PLEASE PROTECT THE HISTORIC CHARACTER OF OUR NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI, MY NAME IS MORRIS FITZGERALD AND I LIVE IN THE
MIDDLE OF THE 1400 BLOCK ON BASS STREET.
AND ONE THING I'M NOT CERTAIN IF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IS
AWARE THAT THIS PLAN CONTEMPLATES MOVING THE
ENTRANCE OF THE HERITAGE HOUSE FROM WHERE IT HAS BEEN FOR A
HUNDRED YEARS OVER TO BAY STREET AND TO INCLUDE A
CIRCULAR DRIVEWAY, UNDERGROUND PARKING AND A NEW ENTRANCE WAY
THERE AND I'M HERE TO TELL YOU ABOUT THAT BLOCK VERY BRIEFLY.
I'VE LIVED THERE 25 YEARS. I LIVE THERE WITH MY WIFE
AND MY TWO CHILDREN. WE HAVE THE PLEASURE OF TRYING
TO GET IN AND OUT OF OUR DRIVEWAY IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
BLOCK EVERY MORNING TO TAKE THE KIDS TO SCHOOL AND FOR OTHER
USES AND I CAN TELL YOU THAT IT'S AN EXTREMELY DANGEROUS
PATCH OF ROAD. THIS IS SO BECAUSE THE CARS
COMING FROM MARIN IN THE MORNING GO UP LAGUNA MAKE A
LEFT TURN ONTO BAY STREET. THESE ARE TWO LANES THAT TURN
LEFT AND THE CARS BECAUSE OF THE CONFIGURE ATION OF OF
LAGUNA BAY STREET IT GOES FROM 80FT AT LAGUNA DOWN TO 50FT
IN THE MIDDLE OF THE BLOCK WITH THIS CREATES IS A WIDE SWOOP OF
TRAFFIC THAT COMES AROUND THAT CORNER.
>> SO THE CHANCES OF AUTOMOBILE COLLISIONS HAVE TENFOLD
INCREASE WITH THE NEW INTRODUCTION OF A PARKING
GARAGE AND A NEW CIRCULAR DRIVEWAY ALSO THAT PATCH OF BAY
STREET IS AN EXTREMELY BUSY PEDESTRIAN WALKWAY.
THAT IS SO BECAUSE PEOPLE COMING FROM THE EAST MARINA TO
GO TO SAFEWAY OR CHILDREN GOING TO MOSCONI PLAYGROUND OR THE
VAST NUMBERS OF PEOPLE WHO USE THAT TO ACCESS THE GREAT MEADOW
AT FORT MASON. AGAIN GETTING IN AND OUT OF MY
GARAGE ALWAYS SOMEBODY WALKING PAST ALWAYS SOME KID ON A
SCOOTER, ALWAYS A WOMAN PUSHING HER BABY OR A DOG OR CELL PHONE
OR ALL THREE. AND I'M VERY CONCERNED THAT THE
MASSIVE INCREASE OF INGRESS AND EGRESS ON BAY STREET AT
THAT ONE LOCATION, THAT VERY DANGEROUS LOCATION WILL LEAD TO
SOME DISASTROUS CONSEQUENCES. >> I THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO. CAN SOMEONE HELP ME WITH THE
PHOTOS? >> THE OVERHEAD PROJECTOR.
I HAD LARGE POSTERS BUT THEY WOULDN'T ALLOW ME TO BRING THEM
IN AND I JUST HAVE A LOBBY, RIGHT?
>> SO VISUALLY AND BEFORE YOU BEGIN, CAN YOU JUST WHEN YOU'RE
READY PULL THE MICROPHONE CLOSE AS CLOSE AS YOU CAN THERE.
>> IS THAT OKAY? YEAH.
MY NAME IS GLORIA FONTANELLA. I HAVE BEEN LIVING ON BAY
STREET FOR THE PAST 50 ALMOST 50 YEARS.
I'M HERE. >> I'D LIKE TO SHOW THIS ONE IF
YOU COULD. >> THE ONE ON THAT ONE SHOWS
THE FORD TRUCKS. CISCO.
ONE, TWO, THREE, FOUR. >> I'M SO SORRY.
I HAD ALL THINGS PREPARED. >> I WANT TO SHOW ACCIDENTS
REAL FAST AUTOMOBILE ON ITS SIDE AND AUTOMOBILE ON ITS SIDE
IN FRONT OF THE 1400 BLOCK OF BAY STREET.
MOTORCYCLE CRASH ALL OVER BAY STREET.
I'M A FORMER COMMISSIONER FOR THE FIRST SAN FRANCISCO
COMMISSION ON THE ENVIRONMENT. >> I'VE WORKED ON TO DOYLE
DRIVE TASK FORCE. THANK GOODNESS WE USED PEOPLE
WON'T EVEN REMEMBER WHAT DOYLE DRIVE WAS TODAY'S PRESIDIO
PARKWAY WE USED TO CALL IT A BLOODBATH.
>> WE WOULD WATCH PEOPLE MAKE U TURNS OUT THERE BUT THANK GOD
TODAY THERE'S STILL SPEEDING LIKE CRAZY.
THERE'S SPEEDING ON BAY AND DOING THE SAME THING MAKING
ILLEGAL TURNS BECAUSE THEY REALIZE THEY'RE ON THEIR WAY TO
THE WHARF INSTEAD OF THE BRIDGE.
>> I I SENT A LETTER TO COMMISSIONER MOORE AFTER THE
FIRST MEETING BECAUSE SHE WAS RIGHT ON.
I SAID YOUR OBSERVATION AT THE PLANNING COMMISSION ON
SEPTEMBER 26TH WHEN SHE MENTIONED HOW DANGEROUS
AND THAT INTERSECTION IS SHE SAID WHY ARE WE DISCUSSING BAY
AND LAGUNA ARE THE AUTOMOBILES AND ILLEGAL TRUCKS IS WHAT I
WAS TRYING TO SHOW YOU. WE HAVE FOUR SETS OF LAWS.
>> THERE ARE NO TRUCKS ALLOWED. WE'RE UNDER THE NATIONAL
STANDARD ARE LANES SO FROM FRANKLIN DOWN TO LAGUNA IT'S NO
TRUCKS. >> I BROUGHT THIS PHOTO WHICH
THEY WOULDN'T LET ME BRING IN. LET'S SAY I'VE AT LEAST A
HUNDRED OF AT LEAST 100 SIDE VIEW MIRRORS WE HAVE WE HAVE SO
MUCH INFORMATION I'VE BEEN GIVING.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS TODAY.
>> THANK YOU. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER. >> HI, I'M CHERYL.
I'M HERE TO TALK ABOUT THE IMPORTANCE OF PRESERVING
HISTORIC BUILDINGS. >> WHEN WE DO THAT WE ENSURE
THAT THERE IS A GREATER INVESTMENT IN OUR COMMUNITY
AND IT ALSO ENSURES THAT PEOPLE AFTER US ARE ABLE TO ENJOY
THOSE HISTORIC LANDMARKS. >> SO PRESERVING THEM IS QUITE
IMPORTANT. >> WHEN WE WANT TO EXTEND OR WE
WANT TO BUILD ADDITIONAL HOUSING OR HOUSING UNITS, WE
NEED TO LOOK FOR OTHER PLACES OR SPACES FOR THOSE.
IF YOU NEED IT TO BE MORE LUXURY BECAUSE I DO UNDERSTAND
THAT THERE ARE DIFFERENT PEOPLE OF DIFFERENT DEMOGRAPHICS THAT
WOULD LIKE A CERTAIN TYPE OF LIFESTYLE.
>> SO YOU'LL NEED TO SHIFT AND YOU'LL NEED TO FIGURE OUT
DIFFERENT WAYS IN ORDER TO PROVIDE THAT TYPE OF HOUSING
UNITS FOR THOSE WHO ARE LOWER LOWER CLASS OF INDIVIDUALS WHO
THEIR DEMOGRAPHIC CANNOT AFFORD THE TYPES OF HOUSING THAT THEY
NEED SO THEY CAN HAVE SUSTAINABLE HOUSING.
YOU NEED TO CREATE CONDITIONS THAT ARE HEALTHY, LIVABLE
IN THAT THEY ARE MAINTAINED IN AN EFFICIENT WAY NOT TO THE
DETRIMENT OF THEIR LIVELIHOOD AND THE FUTURE OF THEIR
LIVELIHOOD. THEY SHOULDN'T JUST BECAUSE
THEY ARE OLDER HAVE TO LIVE IN CONDITIONS THAT ARE LESS
THAN OTHERS. SO HOPEFULLY THAT YOU
UNDERSTAND THAT PLEASE MAKE SURE THAT YOU MAKE THE CORRECT
DECISION ON THIS. I THINK IT'S QUITE CLEAR ON
MAKING SURE WE CAN PRESERVE HISTORY BUT THE FACT THAT WE
HAVE TO HAVE THIS CONVERSATION IN THE FIRST PLACE IS WHY I'M
HERE. SO PLEASE MAKE SURE THAT YOU'RE
DOING THE CORRECT THINGS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER.
HI. SO I'M SORRY I'M NOT TOO
FAMILIAR WITH THIS SPECIFIC LOCATION BUT NO MATTER WHAT
SINCE THE FUTURE IS THAT IS THE OPPOSITE OF GLOBAL GO LOCAL.
SO FIRST YOU GUYS KNOW BETTER THAN ANYONE HOW IT'S GOING TO
AFFECT THE NEIGHBORHOOD BECAUSE YOU'VE BEEN LIVING THERE FOR
LONG ENOUGH. >> SO FIRST THING WHICH WE HAVE
TO TRUST YOU YOU HAVE TO TRUST THEM OBVIOUSLY ENOUGH.
>> I MEAN IF IT WERE THAT OBVIOUS I WOULDN'T HAVE TO SAY
THAT IT'S OBVIOUS. WE DON'T TOUCH HISTORIC
BUILDINGS EXCEPT IF WE BUILD SOMETHING EVEN MORE BEAUTIFUL.
LAST BECAUSE I DON'T HAVE MUCH TO COMMENT ON THAT YOU NEVER
FIRST OF ALL EVER ARE DEFINED. AFFORDABLE YOU NEED TO PUT A
PRICE WHAT'S AFFORDABLE. >> SO THIS IS A JOKE.
WE DON'T NEED MORE HOUSING. YEAH, FOR NOW IN SAN FRANCISCO
WE DON'T TO PUT YOU IN THERE. OKAY.
SORRY. I DO MY PUBLIC COMMENTS WHEN
THE TIME HAS COME. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC
WHO WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF
THE FIRST APPELLANT TANYA ALBUQUERQUE OR STEVEN WILLIAMS
? >> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. >> WE WILL NOW ASK THE SECOND
APPELLANT ALSO THE PROJECT SPONSOR TO COME FORWARD
AND PRESENT THEIR CASE ON THE SIU AND THE CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS. >> AND YOU HAVE TEN MINUTES.
>> THANK YOU AND GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS ALAN MURPHY. I'M WITH THE LAW FIRM OF
PERKINS TUOHY. >> WE REPRESENT THE PROJECT
SPONSOR HERITAGE ON THE MARINA DURING THE HISTORIC
PRESERVATION COMMISSION HEARING ON THE PROJECT AND MISTAKE WAS
MADE THAT FORCED THE SPONSOR TO APPEAL ITS APPROVALS THE
HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION INCLUDED AS A
CONDITION OF PROJECT APPROVAL AN OPEN ENDED REQUIREMENT FOR
FURTHER REVIEW OF PROJECT MASSING AND ARCHITECTURAL
DETAILS BY AN AD HOC COMMITTEE WITHOUT ANY APPARENT APPEAL
PROCESS AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S RESPONSE TO OUR
APPEAL STAFF AGREES WITH US. THIS CONDITION OF APPROVAL
SHOULD BE MODIFIED OR REMOVED FIRST.
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AGREES THE CONDITION OF APPROVAL ONE
IS UNNECESSARY BECAUSE THE PROJECT AS DESIGNED COMPLIES
WITH ALL REQUIREMENTS FOR APPROVAL OF A CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS. SECOND, THE DEPARTMENT AGREES
THAT THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION'S ARCHITECTURAL
REVIEW COMMITTEE CANNOT CONDUCT ITS REVIEW OF A PROJECT AFTER
THE COMMISSION ITSELF HAS DONE SO.
>> THE PROJECT SPONSOR AGREES WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S
RECOMMENDATION TO MODIFY CONDITION OF APPROVAL ONE
CONSISTENT WITH THE REQUEST IN OUR APPEAL WITH FURTHER
MODIFICATIONS AS PROPOSED BY PLANNING STAFF AND ITS RESPONSE
. WE ALSO AGREE WITH THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S RECOMMENDATION TO MODIFY THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S FINDINGS SIX L CONSISTENT WITH THE LANGUAGE
IN OUR APPEAL LETTER. THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR
CONSIDERATION. I'M AVAILABLE SHOULD THERE BE
ANY QUESTIONS AND ALSO OTHERS ON THE PROJECT SPONSOR TEAM
WILL SPEAK WITH YOU DURING THE REBUTTAL PERIOD ON THE OTHER
APPEALS BEFORE YOU TODAY. >> THANK YOU.
I APOLOGIZE SO THAT THAT IS IT. ALL RIGHT.
SO WE WILL NOW TAKE PUBLIC COMMENTS FROM FOLKS IN SUPPORT
OF THE SECOND APPELLANT. >> GOOD EVENING.
THIS EVENING ALREADY SUPERVISORS MY NAME IS CAROLYN
KERNOT AND I'M A PRESERVATION ARCHITECT AND PRINCIPAL AT PAGE
AND TURNBULL IN SAN FRANCISCO. MY COLLEAGUES AND I HAVE BEEN
WORKING ALONGSIDE HERITAGE ON THE MARINA OWNERSHIP AND DESIGN
TEAM FOR THE PAST COUPLE OF YEARS TO ENSURE THE SENSITIVE
TREATMENT OF THE HISTORIC JULIE MORGAN BUILDING, THE PROPOSED
ADDITION AND THE ASSOCIATED LANDSCAPE FEATURES.
IT HAS BEEN VERY CLEAR IN MY INTERACTION WITH BOTH
LEADERSHIP AND RESIDENTS THAT HERITAGE ON THE MARINA TAKES
THEIR STEWARDSHIP RESPONSIBILITY OF THE HISTORIC
JULIA MORGAN BUILDING SERIOUSLY.
THEY AND THEIR RESIDENTS CELEBRATE AND CHERISH THE
BUILDING'S HISTORY AND ITS CONNECTION TO JULIA MORGAN.
>> A LITTLE BACKGROUND AND ABOUT OUR WORK TO DATE.
PAIGE AND TURNBULL BEGAN THE PROJECT BY PREPARING A THOROUGH
HISTORIC RESOURCE EVALUATION WITH FINDINGS ABOUT THE
HISTORY, SIGNIFICANCE AND CHARACTER DEFINING FEATURES
OF THE PROPERTY. WE ALSO COMPLETED A PRELIMINARY
CONDITIONS ASSESSMENT OF THE JULIA MORGAN BUILDING AND WE
HAVE PROVIDED TREATMENT RECOMMENDATIONS FOR THE REPAIR
OF BRICK TERRACOTTA MORTAR SLATE WOOD WINDOWS AND THE
SURROUNDING IRON FENCE. THE BUILDING IS IN VERY GOOD
CONDITION AND IT HAS BEEN WELL-MAINTAINED OVER ITS 100
YEAR HISTORY REFLECTING THE GREAT STEWARDSHIP OF HERITAGE
ON THE MARINA REGARDING THE PROPOSED ADDITION IT SHOULD BE
NOTED THAT THE PROPERTY HAS VERY DIFFERENT URBAN CONDITIONS
THAT RESPOND THAT IT RESPONDS TO ON ITS NORTH WEST AND SOUTH
SIDES ON THE SOUTH SIDE OF THE PROPERTY FACING FRANCISCO.
THE PROPOSED ADDITION HAS A MORE RESIDENTIAL RHYTHM
AND CHARACTER RESPONDING TO THE EXISTING HEIGHT AND CHARACTER
OF THE RESIDENTIAL BUILDINGS ON THAT STREET ON THE WEST SIDE OF
THE PROPERTY THE FULL EXPANSE OF THE JULIAN MORGAN BUILDING'S
PRIMARY FACADE AS WELL AS THE LAWN AND FENCING THE FRAME OUR
VIEW OF THIS IMPORTANT BUILDING WILL BE RETAINED, REPAIRED
AND RESTORED FOR THE ENJOYMENT OF FUTURE GENERATIONS.
>> OUR INTENTION AND OUR HOPE IS TO MOVE FORWARD WITH THE
APPROVED CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS COORDINATE
ADDITIONAL DESIGN REFINEMENTS THROUGH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
THANK SPEAKER MY NAME IS PATRICK ALEXANDER AND I'M A
RESIDENT OF THE HERITAGE AT THE MARINA.
>> ALL THE RESIDENTS ARE AWARE OF WHY THERE IS A NEED FOR THE
HERITAGE TO START CONSTRUCTION TO INCREASE THE NUMBER OF UNITS
AVAILABLE. CURRENTLY THE HERITAGE HAS A
SURPLUS OF VERY SMALL STUDIO UNITS WHICH WHEN IT WAS FOUNDED
100 YEARS AGO WERE WHAT RETIREES WANTED.
THIS IS NOT THE CASE TODAY. THE DEMAND IS FOR ONE AND TWO
BEDROOM UNITS AND THAT IS WHY THE HERITAGE NEEDS TO BE ABLE
TO EXPAND TO FULFILL THIS DEMAND.
>> WHEN I CAME TO THE HERITAGE I CAME THERE WITH THE INTENTION
OF SPENDING THE REST OF MY LIFE AT THE HERITAGE THEREBY
RELIEVING MY FAMILY OF THE BURDEN OF TAKING CARE OF ME
IN MY OLD AGE. THE SAME APPLIES TO THE REST OF
THE RESIDENTS. WE GAVE UP HOUSES.
WE GAVE UP CONDOS. WE GAVE UP APARTMENTS TO BE
ABLE TO LIVE IN THIS LOVELY OLD BUILDING WITH ITS AMAZING
LOCATION. WE WANT TO BE ABLE TO LIVE
AND CONTINUE TO LIVE DOING THAT FOR THE REST OF OUR LIVES.
WE ALL KNOW CONSTRUCTION IS MESSY BUT THE EVENTUAL OUTCOME
WILL BE A BENEFIT. IT WILL BE A BENEFIT TO THE
COMMUNITY AND THE CITY AS WELL AS THE CITY AND PROVIDE
ADDITIONAL HOUSING FOR RETIRED SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SO PLEASE VOTE IN FAVOR OF THE HERITAGE SO WE CAN ALL
CONTINUE TO LIVES THERE FOR THE REST OF YOUR LIFE.
WORST OF OUR LIVES. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WE'LL HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
OKAY. >> WE DID THE OVERHEAD AS A
BACKUP TV PLEASE. >> SO MY NAME IS GREETING
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS TEO ARMOR.
I'VE BEEN A RESIDENT AT HERITAGE ON THE MARINA SINCE
2020. >> I'M A ONE HANDED PARAPLEGIC.
>> I MOVED THERE AT THE HEIGHT OF THE VIRUS IN ORDER TO FIND
SOME SAFETY A SAFE HAVEN. >> IT TURNS OUT FIVE YEARS
LATER I'M LIVING IN AS CLOSE TO PARADISE AS I'LL EVER GET.
I'M REALLY ENJOYING LIVING THERE.
WHY? WELL, FOR A BUNCH OF REASONS.
BUT I THINK THE MAIN THING IS THAT WHAT I WANT OF THIS PLACE
AND WHY I LIKE LIVING IN THIS JULIA MORGAN BUILDING IS THAT
IT'S AN ATTRACTIVE OFFER FOR ME FOR MY KIND OF PERSON AN
AFFORDABLE SENIOR COMMUNITY. AND THIS IS ESSENTIAL IN MANY
WAYS FOR SAN FRANCISCO'S AGING POPULATION.
THE IDEA OF AGING IN YOUR IN YOUR HOUSE 1 OR 2 PEOPLE
LIVING IN A LARGE PROPERTY WASTE HOUSING STOCK.
SO SENIOR HOUSING LIKE THE ONE WE LIVE IN LIKE HERITAGE ON THE
MARINA FREES UP LARGER PROPERTIES FOR YOUNGER FAMILIES
WHO DESPERATELY NEED IT. I'M A PAST LIFE.
I'M AN ARCHITECT. >> I'VE LOOKED AT THE DRAWINGS.
I'VE LOOKED AT THE PLANS. YES, THERE ARE ISSUES BUT THIS
FIGHT IS WORTH IT. >> AND BELIEVE ME I HAVE ONE OF
THE BEST VIEWS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I LOOK OUT OVER FORT MASON IN THE BAY.
BUT I'M WILLING TO GIVE UP THAT VIEW TO SEE THIS PROJECT
SUCCEED. YES, THERE WILL BE NOISE
AND JUST YES IT'LL BE NOISE DURING THE CONSTRUCTION BUT WE
AND WE LIVE RESIDENTS LIVE AT GROUND ZERO.
>> WE WILL BE GOING THROUGH THIS AND WE ARE CONCERNED MORE
THAN ANYBODY AND I KNOW MY BOARD AND OUT OF THE
CONTRACTORS AND EVERYBODY WILL BE BEHIND US AND MAKING SURE
THAT THE CONSTRUCTION IS AS SAFE AND AS AS AS GOOD AS IT
POSSIBLY CAN BE. I PLEASE WE'RE NOT ASKING YOU
TO SOLVE THE HOUSING CRISIS WHEN YOUR CONSTITUENTS WANT A
SOLUTION LIKE THIS. >> PLEASE SAY YES.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. I HAVE NO OVERHEADS.
SORRY. >> MY NAME IS TONY HANLEY.
MY WIFE LINDA AND I HAVE LIVED AT THE HERITAGE ON THE MARINA
FOR EIGHT YEARS. >> THE HERITAGE OF THE MARINA
IS A FAMILY AND THAT'S WHAT MAKES IT SO GREAT THE CARING
STAFF THAT TAKES CARE OF US. WHEN I SAY FAMILY YOU KNOW
EVERYBODY'S NAME ALL THE STAFF, ALL THE RESIDENTS TWO COMMENTS
SOME GENTLE I MEAN ONE OF THE GENTLEMAN UP HERE WAS LOOKING
AT OUR TAX RETURN AND WE HAVE ALL THIS VALUE.
>> THE VALUE IS IS AT WE HAVE NO DEBT.
OUR PROBLEM IS OUR COSTS RUN 5 TO $7000 MORE A MONTH THAN OUR
INCOME. >> NOW WE DO HAVE AND IT'S BEEN
REPORTED WE DO HAVE A PORTFOLIO .
AND THANK GOODNESS FOR THAT PORTFOLIO THAT HAS ALLOWED THE
ABSORPTION THE MONEY OFF THAT PORTFOLIO HAS ALLOWED AN
ABSORPTION OF THE COST. THE LAST THING THAT BUGGED ME
WAS THE GREAT DRIVEWAY DISPUTE. >> IF YOU EVER BEEN TO THE
HERITAGE AND LOOKED AT A CISCO TRUCK OR THE SAN FRANCISCO NOW
IT'S RECOLOGY I CALLED THE GARBAGE THEY HAVE TO TURN OUT
ON BAY STREET BACK IN THE PROJECT CALLS FOR DRIVE THRU.
>> SO THEY DRIVE IN TURN RIGHT DRIVE INTO THE PROPERTY, DO
THEIR STUFF AND THERE'S A DRIVE OUT.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> EARLY EVENING SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS PATRICK MURPHY.
I'M A NATIVE SAN FRANCISCAN WHO HAS LIVED ON FRANCISCO STREET
SINCE 1989, PURCHASED MY PROPERTY ABUTTING THE HERITAGE
IN 1999. >> FOR THE PAST 20 7 TO 37
YEARS THE MANAGEMENT AND OCCUPANTS AT THE HERITAGE
HAVE BEEN NOTHING BUT WONDERFUL NEIGHBORS.
I DO FEEL LIKE SOME OF THEM HAVE BECOME PART OF MY FAMILY
AND MY BUILDING. I AM AGE 65 CONSIDERING WHERE
TO LIVE OR RETIREMENT AND THE HERITAGE PROVIDES A DISTINCT
AND DIFFERENT RELATIVELY AFFORDABLE CCR ALTERNATIVE FOR
SENIORS SUCH AS MYSELF LOOKING TO REMAIN IN SAN FRANCISCO
WHERE WE HAVE LIVED ALL OUR LIVES.
I HAVE LIVED IN AN APARTMENT ALL MY LIFE AND NOT LOOKING FOR
LUXURY BUT WHAT THEY HAVE NOW IS STUDIO APARTMENTS.
I DON'T WANT TO MOVE DOWN TO A STUDIO.
THEY NEED TO BE ABLE TO BUILD SOMETHING THAT FIT WHAT PEOPLE
ARE LOOKING FOR TODAY WHICH IS A LARGER SIZE APARTMENT.
THE EXTRA SQUARE FOOTAGE WILL HELP FOR A COMMON LIVING SPACE
FOR ALL THE PEOPLE THAT DO LIVE THERE.
I URGE YOU TO SUPPORT THE HERITAGE AND APPROVE I APPROVED
THIS PROCESS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> ALL RIGHT.
NEXT SPEAKER IF THERE ARE ANY IN LINE DOWN THERE.
CAN YOU TURN THAT OFF? ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
SEEING NO OTHER SPEAKERS, PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
AND NOW WE WILL HEAR FOR TEN MINUTES FROM REPRESENTATIVES OF
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT
RANDLEMAN AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS MEGAN GALPIN. I'M A SENIOR ENVIRONMENTAL
PLANNER AT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
JOINING ME TODAY ARE JUSTIN GRABBING ALISON VANDERSLICE,
JOI NAVARETTE AND LISA GIBSON. >> CAN WE PLEASE GO TO MY
SLIDES? >> I'LL BE PRESENTING THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S RESPONSE TO THE APPEAL OF THE
CERTIFICATION OF THE FINAL AIR FOR THE 3400 LAGUNA STREET
PROJECT. AFTER I COMPLETE MY
PRESENTATION, I'LL HAND THINGS OVER TO MY COLLEAGUE RICHARD
SUE CRAY WHO WILL PRESENT ON THE TWO OTHER APPEALS.
>> BEFORE I BEGIN, I DO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE TESTIMONY THAT
WE HEARD TODAY FROM MEMBERS OF THE COMMUNITY WHO ARE CONCERNED
ABOUT THE POTENTIAL IMPACTS OF THE PROJECT.
>> THESE ISSUES HAVE BEEN ADDRESSED IN THE DEPARTMENT'S
APPEAL RESPONSE AND AS WELL IN THE AIR ITSELF.
>> NEXT SLIDE PLEASE. 3400 LAGUNA STREET IS AN
APPROXIMATELY 1.6 ACRE PROJECT SITE WITH FRONTAGES ALONG
LAGUNA BAY AND FRANCISCO STREET AND THE MARINA DISTRICT
HERITAGE ON THE MARINA HAS CONTINUOUSLY OPERATED A
RESIDENTIAL CARE FACILITY FOR THE ELDERLY AT THE SITE SINCE
1925. >> NEXT SLIDE THE PROPOSED
PROJECT WOULD MAINTAIN THE CURRENT OPERATION AT THE SITE
AS A RESIDENTIAL CARE FACILITY WHILE RESTORING THE HISTORIC
JULIA MORGAN BUILDING AND CONSTRUCTING TWO NEW 40
FOOT TALL BUILDINGS IN THE LOCATION OF TWO NON HISTORIC
BUILDINGS TO BE DEMOLISHED. >> THE PROJECT WOULD ALSO ADD A
BELOW GRADE PARKING GARAGE AND A NEW VEHICLE DRIVEWAY.
THE PROJECT WOULD RESULT IN THE ADDITION OF 23 CARE UNITS NEW
CARE UNITS. NEXT SLIDE SECURE THE SCHOOL
GUIDELINES AND CHAPTER 31 OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
ESTABLISH THE LEGAL STANDARDS FOR AN E.R. AT A HIGH LEVEL THE
AIR MUST BE ADEQUATE, ACCURATE AND OBJECTIVE AND THE
CONCLUSIONS OF THE AIR MUST BE SUPPORTED BY SUBSTANTIAL
EVIDENCE. ON APRIL 17TH, 2025, THE
PLANNING COMMISSION FOUND THAT AIR TO MEET THE STANDARDS OF
ADEQUACY. >> THE LETTERS OF APPEAL CLAIM
THE AIR IS INADEQUATE BUT UPON CLOSE REVIEW THEIR ARGUMENTS DO
NOT MEET THE LEGAL BURDEN OF SHOWING THAT THE AIR ANALYSIS
IS NOT SUPPORTED BY SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE.
ALL CONCERNS RAISED BY THE APPELLANT ARE SHOWN HERE ON THE
SLIDE AND THEY ARE ADDRESSED IN THE DEPARTMENT'S APPEAL
RESPONSE AND IN THE AIR. I'LL PROVIDE A SUMMARY OF THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S RESPONSE TO SOME OF THESE CONCERNS NOW.
>> NEXT SLIDE PLEASE. PLANNING CODE SECTION 306.3
NOTICE OF HEARINGS PERTAINS TO APPROVAL ACTIONS BY THE
PLANNING COMMISSION AND IS NOT RELEVANT TO THE ENVIRONMENTAL
REVIEW WHICH IS NOT AN APPROVAL PURSUANT TO SECTION THE SCHOOL
GUIDELINES AND CHAPTER 31 OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE.
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT ACTED PROPERLY IN OUR NOTIFICATIONS.
>> NEXT SLIDE. >> WE DID HEAR FROM A NUMBER OF
SPEAKERS TODAY ABOUT CONCERNS ABOUT TRAFFIC DATA REGARDING
TRANSPORTATION AND THE PROPOSED PROJECT WAS REVIEWED BY THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT STREET DESIGN ADVISORY TEAM AS
DESCRIBED IN THE DRAFT R APPENDIX E.
>> THAT TEAM CONCLUDED THAT THE PROPOSED PROJECT'S NEW VEHICLE
DRIVEWAY AND FREIGHT LOADING EGRESS LOCATION LOCATED FURTHER
AWAY FROM THE BAY AND LAGUNA STREET INTERSECTION AND THE
RESTRICTED RIGHT ONLY TURN WOULD NOT INCREASE HAZARDS FOR
DRIVERS OR ROADWAY USERS. THE DRAFT R ALSO CONTAINS A
QUANTITATIVE ANALYSIS OF FREIGHT AND PASSENGER LOADING
DEMAND WHICH CONCLUDED THAT THE PROPOSED PROJECT WOULD PROVIDE
ADEQUATE OFF STREET FREIGHT AND PASSENGER LOADING INCLUDING
DURING PEAK HOURS. >> AS FOR OTHER TOPICS RAISED
THE DEPARTMENT'S APPEAL RESPONSE NOTED THAT THE PROJECT
SITE AND THE PROJECT DESCRIPTION INCLUDING THE PLANS
WERE ADEQUATE AND ACCURATE UNDER SECTION.
THE PROJECT WAS EXEMPT FROM ESTHETICS AND PARKING ANALYSIS
UNDER SECTION. THE DEPARTMENT ANALYZED A
REASONABLE RANGE OF ALTERNATIVES PURSUANT TO THE
SCORE GUIDELINES AND THE DRAFT AIR CORRECTLY ANALYZED THE
PROPOSED PROJECT SHADOW IMPACTS UTILIZING THE HEIGHT
MEASUREMENT UNDER THE PLANNING CODE.
>> NEXT SLIDE PLEASE. THE GROUNDS FOR AN AIR
CERTIFICATE AN APPEAL UNDER CHAPTER 31 IS WHETHER THE AIR
ADEQUATELY COMPLIES WITH THE REQUIREMENTS OF SECTION.
THE APPELLANT HAS NOT MET THE BURDEN OF CONCLUSIONS OF THE
CONCLUSIONS OF THE AIR THAT THEY'RE NOT SUPPORTED BY
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE AND IS NOT IN COMPLIANCE WITH CEQA.
FOR THESE REASONS THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT RESPECTFULLY
REQUESTS THAT THE BOARD REJECT THE SECURE APPEAL AND UPHOLD
THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S CERTIFICATION OF THE FINAL AIR.
THIS CONCLUDES MY PRESENTATION .
MY COLLEAGUES AND I ARE AVAILABLE FOR QUESTIONS.
NEXT, I'D LIKE TO INTRODUCE RICH ZACHRY DEPUTY DIRECTOR OF
CURRENT PLANNING. >> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS
RICH CRAY. I'M JOINED HERE WITH SYLVIA
GIMENEZ AND CHARLES ANGEL FROM PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF.
>> THIS IS THE DECISION BEFORE YOU IS WHETHER TO UPHOLD OR
OVERTURN THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION'S
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS AND THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION TO AMEND AN EXISTING PLANNED
UNIT DEVELOPMENT FOR THE EXPANSION OF AN EXISTING
RESIDENTIAL CARE FACILITY CALLED HERITAGE ON THE MARINA.
THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS RECEIVED ONE
APPEAL FROM THE PROJECT SPONSOR THE SAN FRANCISCO LADIES
PROTECTION AND RELIEF SOCIETY AND THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION RECEIVED TWO APPEALS FROM SAVE THE MARINA'S
HERITAGE NEIGHBORHOOD ORGANIZATION OR APPLICANT ONE
AND THE PROJECT SPONSOR WHICH WERE REFERRED TO AS APOLLON
TWO. >> THE PROJECT SPONSOR RAISES
TWO ISSUES WITH THE CITY A CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
IN THEIR WRITTEN APPEAL OF THE PROJECT ONE THAT THERE IS
SUFFICIENT EVIDENCE IN THE RECORD TO SUPPORT THE HPC
CONDITION OF APPROVAL IS UNNECESSARY AND TWO THAT HPC
CONDITION OF APPROVAL ONE IS VAGUE IS AN UNLAWFUL DELEGATION
OF AUTHORITY BY THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION TO ITS
ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE AND RISKS VIOLATING THE CITY
VIOLATED AND RISKS THE CITY VIOLATING THE PERMIT
STREAMLINING ACT. IN ADDITION, THE PROJECT
SPONSOR RAISES ONE ISSUE IN THEIR WRITTEN APPEAL OF THE
PROJECT'S OF THE PROJECT'S CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
AND THAT'S FINDING SIX L SHOULD BE MODIFIED TO BE CONSISTENT
WITH THE REQUESTED MODIFICATION TO THE CONDITION OF APPROVAL
NUMBER ONE IN THE HPC MOTION THE HPC CONDUCTED A JOINT
HEARING IN CONJUNCTION WITH THE PLANNING COMMISSION DUE TO TIME
AND FACILITATION CONSTRAINTS OF THAT JOINT HEARING, THE
REGULATORY FRAMEWORK AND PROCEDURES WERE NOT READILY
APPARENT AT THE TIME OF THE ABC'S APPROVAL MOTION GIVEN
THAT UNDER THOSE PROCEDURES THE IAC CANNOT CONDUCT ITS REVIEW
AFTER HPC. THE DEPARTMENT RECOMMENDS
MODIFYING CONDITION OVER APPROVAL ONE CONSISTENT WITH
THE APPEAL LETTER REQUEST AND LANGUAGE BUT MODIFYING THAT
LANGUAGE TO BE MORE SPECIFIC TO MORE SPECIFICALLY REFER TO THE
ISSUES DISCUSSED BY THE HPC DURING THE JOINT PUBLIC
HEARING. THE DEPARTMENT FURTHER
RECOMMENDS THAT THE MODIFIED CONDITION AS THE PERMIT
STREAMLINING ACT APPLY TO THE PROJECT AND REQUIRE A 90 DAY
REVIEW TIMELINE FOLLOWING CERTIFICATION OF THE
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT. ALTERNATIVELY, THE DEPARTMENT
RECOMMENDS REMOVING CONDITION OF APPROVAL ONE FROM THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS AFTER THE HPC HEARING
AND RESPONSE THE ADDED CONDITION OF APPROVAL NUMBER
ONE THE PLANNING COMMISSION ADDED FINDING SIX L TO THEIR
APPROVAL MOTION IN WHICH THE COMMISSION FOUND THAT THE
OVERALL SIZE AND INTENSITY OF THE PROJECT ARE AS PROPOSED ARE
CRITICAL TO THE PROGRAMMATIC VIABILITY OF THE PROJECT
AND DIRECTED PLANNING STAFF TO BRING THE PROJECT BACK TO THE
COMMISSION AS AN INFORMATIONAL ITEM.
FOLLOWING THE AGENCY'S REVIEW, THE DEPARTMENT RECOMMENDS
MODIFYING FINDINGS SIX L OF THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
MOTION PER THE SPONSORS LETTER FOR CONSISTENCY WITH THE
STRATEGIC VIDEO APPROPRIATENESS RECOMMENDATION AND FOR
COMPLIANCE WITH THE PERMIT STREAMLINING ACT.
FOR THESE REASONS THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT REQUESTS THE BOARD
MODIFY BOTH THE C OF A AND THE Q APPELLANT NUMBER ONE OF THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION RAISES SIX MAIN ISSUES IN THEIR
WRITTEN APPEAL OF THE PROJECT WHICH INCLUDE ONE ADEQUACY OF
THE PLANS APPROVED BY THE COMMISSION TO ADEQUACY OF THE
NOTICE OF PUBLIC HEARING. THREE THE Q FINDINGS FAILURE TO
ADEQUATELY ADDRESS DETRIMENTAL IMPACTS FOUR THAT THE PROJECT
DESCRIPTION IS INACCURATE FIVE THAT THE COMMISSION THE
COMMISSION'S ATTEMPT TO RESTRICT AND CONTROL THE
ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE IS INVALID AND SIX THAT THE
COMMISSION'S APPROVAL WAS MOTIVATED BY ECONOMIC ECONOMIC
NEEDS OF THE PROJECT OVERALL THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FINDS
THAT THE ISSUES RAISED BY APPLICANT NUMBER ONE ARE
WITHOUT MERIT AND THAT THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S APPROVAL
OF THE PROJECT WAS PROPER. THE PLAN SUBMITTED COMPLY WITH
THE DEPARTMENT'S PLAN SUBMITTAL GUIDELINES AND WERE
PROFESSIONAL AND WERE PROFESSIONALLY PREPARED.
PUBLIC NOTICE WAS ISSUED IN ACCORDANCE WITH PLANNING
CODE SECTIONS 306.3 AND 333. THE COMMISSION MADE REQUIRED
CONDITIONAL USE FINDINGS INCLUDING A DETERMINATION THAT
THE PROJECT WOULD NOT BE DETRIMENTAL TO THE SURROUNDING
AREA AND THAT IT SUPPORTS AN IDENTIFIED POLICY GOAL OF
EXPANDING RESIDENTIAL CARE FACILITIES FOR SENIORS.
THE PROJECT UNDERWENT APPROPRIATE INTERAGENCY REVIEW
TO ADDRESS TRAFFIC AND LOADING AND NO VIOLATIONS OF THE
EXISTING CONDITIONAL USE OR PLANNING CODE WERE IDENTIFIED.
THE COMMISSION'S FINDINGS ACCURATELY REFLECT THE ACTIONS
TAKEN AND DO NOT INFRINGE UPON THE ROLE OF THE HPC.
>> FINALLY, THE COMMISSION'S DECISION WAS GROUNDED IN A
BALANCE OF APPLICABLE POLICY OBJECTIVES AND FINDINGS
REQUIRED UNDER PLANNING CODE SECTIONS 303 AND 304.
FOR THESE REASONS THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT REQUEST THE BOARD
REJECT THIS APPEAL OF THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
AND TO CLOSE THE BOARD HAS A NUMBER OF ACTIONS BEFORE THEM.
IF THE BOARD CHOOSES TO UPHOLD THE ER APPEAL THEN NO FURTHER
ACTION ON THE C OF A AND Q IS NEEDED IF THE BOARD DENIES THE
APPEAL. THE BOARD MAY TAKE SEPARATE
ACTION ON THE APPEALS OF THE C OF A AND Q AS A REMINDER THE
DEPARTMENT DOES RECOMMEND THAT THE BOARD UPHOLD THE C OF
APPEAL AND STRIKE OR MODIFY CONDITION NUMBER ONE.
IN ADDITION, THE DEPARTMENT RECOMMENDS THAT THE BOARD DENY
THE SAVE THE MARINA CUE APPEAL AND UPHOLD THE PROJECT SPONSOR
A C YOU APPEAL AND MODIFY FINDINGS SIX L TO BE CONSISTENT
WITH ITS ACTIONS ON THE C OF A AND PERMIT STREAMLINING ACT.
AND THIS CONCLUDES OUR PRESENTATION.
>> THANK YOU. >> ALL RIGHT.
>> AND WE HAVE QUESTION SUPERVISOR JIM.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT BENJAMIN AND I JUST I JUST NEED TO
UNDERSTAND A LITTLE BIT ABOUT WHAT WE'RE LOOKING AT TODAY.
>> HOW PLEASE HELP ME UNDERSTAND THAT IT SEEMS TO ME
THOUGH THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION IS
REQUIRED ASKING FOR A CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATION
AND THAT IS ACTUALLY WHAT WAS RESULTED PART OF THE SEQUEL OR
IS IT NOT OR SUPERVISORS THROUGH THE CHAIR ROBERTS
SHOUKRY DEPARTMENT STAFF THE AIR AND THE ENVIRONMENTAL
REVIEW OF THE PROJECT WAS COMPLETED FIRST AND IN THIS
CASE OUR ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW STAFF COMPLETED AN
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT. SUBSEQUENTLY BECAUSE THE
PROJECT IS BOTH A CITY LANDMARK AND INVOLVED, THE EXPANSION OF
A RESIDENTIAL CARE FACILITY A CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
FOR THE EXTERIOR WORK THAT HAPPENED ON THE PROPERTY OR ANY
NEW CONSTRUCTION THAT WAS HAPPENING ON THE PROPERTY WAS
REQUIRED BECAUSE IT'S A CITY LANDMARK AND THEN A CONDITIONAL
USE FROM THE PLANNING COMMISSION WAS ALSO REQUIRED TO
EXPAND THE RESIDENTIAL CARE FACILITY.
AND SO IF I MAY CONTINUE, JUST HELP ME UNDERSTAND AND SO TODAY
WHAT WE'RE LOOKING AT BECAUSE THIS IS PARTICULARLY NOT NOT
REALLY ABOUT THE SECURE IN ITSELF OR LIKE WHETHER IT'S
WISHES CERTIFY OR NOT OR YOU KNOW, AFFIRM THE CERTIFICATION
OF THE SEQUEL. IT'S MORE I HAVE A QUESTION
ABOUT THE REVERSING AND WITH THE CONDITIONAL AND RIGHT NOW
AS IS CURRENTLY STANDS THE CONDITIONAL IS INCLUDING A
CONDITIONAL USE AND CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATION OR
APPROPRIATENESS. IS THAT CORRECT?
>> CORRECT. AND SO WHAT WE'RE LOOKING AT IS
THAT IF WE WERE TO FOR ITEM 26 TO SAY THAT IF WE WERE TO
REVERSE THAT THEN THAT MEANS WE'RE ALSO REVERSED THE
REQUIREMENTS FOR CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
AND APPROPRIATION AND CONDITIONAL USE THE
REQUIREMENT WOULD STILL APPLY. SO WHAT THE BOARD CAN DO IS
ACCEPT THE APPEAL AND THEN MODIFY THE MOTION OR THE
CERTIFICATE OR APPROPRIATENESS AND THE CONDITIONAL USE AS THEY
SEE FIT. >> BUT IF WE WERE TO
CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE FINAL AIR OR CAN LAY OUT LIKE IS THE
CONDITIONAL ARE WE I MEAN I THINK THAT I MY ASSUMPTION IS
SO I SHOULD SHARE WITH ME MAY HELP US UNDERSTAND WHERE WE'RE
HEADING ON THIS BUT I'M TRYING TO UNDERSTAND.
SO CURRENTLY AS IT STANDS FOR THE AIR IT DOES INCLUDE THE
REQUIREMENT FOR CCU AND REQUIREMENT.
>> OKAY. BUT IT'S TWO SEPARATE ACTIONS
IN THIS CASE. SO FOR A PROJECT TO BE APPROVED
BY OUR COMMISSIONS AND OUR BOARD ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW
UNDER THE CALIFORNIA ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY ACT IS
REQUIRED. SO THAT IS ONE ACTION IN THIS
CASE THE AIR IS THE APPROPRIATE ACTION AND THE SUBSEQUENT
ACTIONS BY OUR COMMISSIONS RELY ON THAT ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW TO
MEET OUR COMPLIANCE WITH STATE LAW AND THESE INSTANCES.
SO FOR EXAMPLE IF THE BOARD CHOSE TO UPHOLD THE AIR APPEAL
THEN ACTION ON THE C OF A AND C YOU WOULD NOT BE REQUIRED
BECAUSE THOSE TWO DOCUMENTS WOULD NO LONGER BE VALID
AND BUT OKAY MY LAST QUESTION IS THAT HOW WE UNDERSTAND AS IT
CURRENTLY STANDS IN THE IN THE EXISTING BUILDING THAT IS TO BE
DEMOLISHED THAT IS IN QUESTION RIGHT NOW ARE THERE ANY ONE
PARTICULAR ARE THERE ARE IS A TENANT OCCUPIED THE THERE ARE
ROOMS IN THERE BUT AS I UNDERSTAND THE HERITAGE ON THE
MARINA WILL BE SHIFTING THE LOCATION OF THOSE TENANTS TO
MOVE THEM INTO OTHER PARTS OF THE FACILITY TO ACCOMMODATE FOR
THE CONSTRUCTION IN THOSE TWO ADDITIONS.
>> SO THEY WILL BE ME TECHNICALLY MOVED TO THE SO
CALLED MAIN BUILDING. CORRECT.
AND THEN IT'S SO THE THE BUILDING NOW CLEARLY IS NOT THE
LANDMARK BUILDING THE LANDMARK IS ONLY THE ORIGINAL JULIA
MORGAN PROPERTY. >> THE LATTER SIX ADDITIONS ARE
NOT PART OF THE LANDMARK AND SO THE TENANTS WILL ACTUALLY BE
MOVED FROM THE NON HISTORIC BUILDING INTO THE HISTORIC
BUILDING AND THEN THE GOAL WHILE THE PROJECT IS TO
PROPOSED DEMOLISH THE NON HISTORIC BUILDING AND THEN IT
WILL BECOME ADDITIONAL 23 UNITS CORRECT AND CURRENTLY HOW MANY
UNITS IN THAT NON HISTORIC BUILDING I WOULD ASK THE
PROJECT SPONSOR TO ADDRESS THE QUESTION.
>> I DON'T HAVE THE NUMBER OF TYPOLOGIES.
OKAY. MAY I?
OH SURE. OKAY I GUESS SPONSOR LOOK AT
THE PROJECT SPONSOR THE QUESTION IS FOR THE BUILDING
THAT IS CURRENTLY ON YOU KNOW IN QUESTION THAT TO BE DEMOLISH
THERE THEN YOU CAN ACTUALLY REBUILD IN FOR A ADDITIONAL 23
UNITS ON SITE. HOW MANY UNITS WITHIN THIS NON
HISTORIC BUILDING AND HOW MANY TENANTS ARE CURRENTLY OCCUPYING
THAT BUILDING FOR THE TO THE BAY STREET BUILDING IS A TWO
STORY BUILDING THAT CURRENTLY OCCUPIES OUR DINING ROOM ON THE
FIRST FLOOR AND ON THE SECOND FLOOR SIX RESIDENTIAL UNITS.
>> I GUESS MY QUESTION IS THE FRANCISCO SIDE THE FRANCISCO
SIDE IS CURRENTLY OUR VACANT SKILLED NURSING FACILITY.
WE CLOSED THAT IN 2023. WE WERE LOSING $2.5 MILLION A
YEAR ON THAT AND SO IT'S COMPLETELY EMPTY.
>> IT IS VACANT. VACANT, UNDERSTOOD.
AND HOW MANY UNITS RIGHT NOW IN THAT VACANT BUILDING FOR THE
RESIDENTIAL CARE UNITS THEY'RE NOT UNITS IN THE SKILLED
NURSING FACILITY. THERE ARE ROOMS THERE WERE 32
BEDS IN THAT BUT THEIR ROOMS AND THEN SO THE 32 BEDS ARE
GOING TO BE DEMOLISHED AND THEN YOU'RE REPLACING IT WITH 23
UNITS. >> THAT'S CORRECT.
BUT PEOPLE ARE ARE INFLATING THE SIZE OF THOSE UNITS.
YOU HAVE TO CONSIDER THAT THERE'S ALSO AMENITY SPACE.
THERE'S ALSO, YOU KNOW, OFFICE SPACE AND LOBBY SPACE
AND KITCHEN THOSE KINDS OF THINGS.
>> THERE IS 30 TWO BEDS, 32 ROOMS VERSUS 23 UNITS OF 800FT2
PER ROOM PER UNITS. >> CORRECT.
I SHOULD CLARIFY THAT THE 32 BEDS ARE NOT PART OF THE 86
UNITS THAT ARE BEFORE YOU AS EXISTING ON THE PROJECTS.
RIGHT. THERE ARE 86 UNITS THAT ARE
EXISTING IN THE APPLICATION. 109 UNITS WILL BE PROVIDED
AFTER THE PROJECT IS COMPLETE SO IT IS AN INCREASE OF 23
UNITS. THE BEDS THAT ARE REFERRED TO
WERE ESSENTIALLY FOLKS AS I UNDERSTAND IT WHO WHO HAD
PREVIOUSLY OTHER ACCOMMODATIONS WITHIN HERITAGE ON THE MARINA
AND THEN WENT TO THE SKILLED NURSING FACILITY WHEN THEY
NEEDED THAT LEVEL OF CARE. AND TODAY THE MODEL IS TO
ACTUALLY PROVIDE THAT CARE WITHIN THE UNITS THAT THE
INDIVIDUALS OCCUPY. SO IT'S A DIFFERENT MODEL SO IT
WOULD NOT BE IT WOULD NOT BE RIGHT TO THINK OF IT AS
REMOVING BEDS BECAUSE ACTUALLY OVERALL THE PROJECT IS
INCREASING THE NUMBER OF CARE SUITES AND SO FORTH.
THE NEW DESIGN IS TECHNICALLY 23 UNITS WITH 800FT2 EACH UNIT.
>> IT IS A 23 UNIT INCREASE AND YOU KNOW THE AVERAGE SO ON
AVERAGE THE UNITS IF YOU TAKE ALL OF THEM IN ACCOUNT WILL BE
BETWEEN 7 AND 800FT2. BUT OUR AVERAGE UNIT RIGHT NOW
IS 250FT2. >> THANK YOU.
THAT JUST TRYING TO HELP ME UNDERSTAND THE SCALE I MEAN IT
MAKES SENSE. I THINK SOME OF THE PUBLIC
COMMENTS I MADE TALKED ABOUT YOU KNOW, THEN IT WOULD TURN
INTO A TWO 2 OR 3 BEDROOMS UNITS INSTEAD OF SORT THIS ONE
PERSON ALONE UNITS OR BEDS ROOMS AS SITUATION.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
I JUST WANTED TO UNDERSTAND WHAT WE'RE LOOKING AT.
MUCH APPRECIATE IT. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
SPONSOR. THANK YOU SO MUCH PLANNING
STAFF I HAVE NO MORE QUESTION AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN
AND NOW I THINK WE'RE INVITING PROJECT SPONSORS UP THERE SO I
THINK WE'RE INVITING YOU BACK TO TALK TO US FOR UP TO TEN
MINUTES. >> WELL HI, I'M MARY LINDY
AND I'M THE CEO OF THE SAN FRANCISCO LADIES PROTECTION
AND RELIEF SOCIETY. WE DO BUSINESS AS HERITAGE ON
THE MARINA. I'M ALSO A NURSE WITH A
BACHELOR'S AND A MASTER'S DEGREE IN NURSING AND I HAVE 40
YEARS OF NURSING EXPERIENCE AS WELL AS 27 YEARS AS A
PROGRESSIVE ADMINISTRATOR IN SENIOR CARE.
THIS IS INDEED MY PASSION. I APPRECIATE YOU TAKING THE
TIME TO HEAR OUR VISION AND TO HELP US HELP YOU UNDERSTAND WHY
WE NEED TO SUSTAIN SENIOR LIVING IN THE SAN FRANCISCO
MARINA. I WANT YOU TO KNOW WHO WE
REALLY ARE AND WHY WE'RE REALLY HERE.
FOR 172 YEARS THE SOCIETY AND NOW THE HERITAGE ON THE
MARINA HAS BEEN A PILLAR OF SUPPORT FOR SAN FRANCISCO
AND WE OFFERED BOTH COMMUNITY AND COMPASSIONATE CARE.
TODAY THAT SUPPORT LOOKS LIKE INDEPENDENT AND ASSISTED LIVING
RESIDENTS SENIORS APPROXIMATELY 80 OF THEM AND WE ENSURE THAT
THEY HAVE CARE, DIGNITY, COMFORT OF THE HIGHEST QUALITY
. >> HOWEVER, WE ARE FACING A
FINANCIAL CRISIS THAT CHALLENGES US AND THREATENS OUR
VISION. >> LIKE MANY ORGANIZATIONS,
WE'RE STRUGGLING WITH RISING COSTS WAGES, BENEFITS, CARE
NEEDS AND OVERHEAD EXPENSES HAVE INCREASED BEYOND OUR
RESOURCES OVER THE PAST DECADE. >> OUR ANNUAL DEFICIT HAS GROWN
FROM $3 MILLION TO $8 MILLION WHILE OUR INVESTMENTS HAVE
HELPED SUSTAIN US SO FAR THEY ARE NO LONGER ENOUGH WITHOUT
ACTION, OUR ABILITY TO SERVE SENIORS IS TRULY AT RISK.
ONE OF THE MAIN CHALLENGES WE FACE IS THAT WE WERE ORIGINALLY
BUILT AS A BOARDING HOME AND MOST OF OUR CARE UNITS ARE
ONLY ABOUT 250FT2. THAT'S THE SIZE OF MOST OF YOUR
CLOSETS. THEY SIMPLY DO NOT MEET THE
EVOLVING NEEDS OF TODAY'S SENIORS AND AS A RESULT MANY OF
THOSE REMAIN VACANT. RATHER THAN RAISING FEES ON OUR
CURRENT RESIDENTS TO MORE THAN THEY CAN MANAGE, WE BELIEVE THE
MOST RESPONSIBLE THING TO DO IS TO EXPAND IN THAT WAY WE CAN
CARE FOR MORE SENIORS AND ALSO PRESERVE THE INTEGRITY OF THE
JULIA MORGAN BUILDING. >> THIS PATH ALLOWS US ONGOING
FINANCIAL STABILITY AND SUSTAINABILITY AND ALSO
KEEPS US TRUE TO OUR NONPROFIT MISSION ABOVE ALL HERITAGE ON
THE MARINA ALWAYS HAS BEEN AND WILL CONTINUE TO BE A
NONPROFIT. >> THIS PROJECT IS NOT ABOUT
PROFIT. IT'S ABOUT SURVIVAL.
>> IT'S ABOUT HONORING AND SUSTAINING OUR 172 YEAR
LEGACY OF CARE RIGHT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND WITH YOUR SUPPORT WE CAN PROTECT THE FUTURE OF SENIOR
LIVING IN THE MARINA. ALLOWING GENERATIONS TO COME TO
RECEIVE THE CARE THAT THEY DESERVE RIGHT IN THE VERY PLACE
OUR 80 RESIDENTS CURRENTLY AND PROUDLY CALL HOME ON BEHALF
OF THOSE RESIDENTS AND OUR STAFF AND OUR BOARD OF
DIRECTORS, THANK YOU FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION.
THANK YOU. >> HI, MY NAME IS FRANK
ROCKWOOD. I'M WITH ROCKWOOD PACIFIC WHERE
THE DEVELOPMENT MANAGER HAS JUST WANTED TO JUMP IN AND JUST
CLARIFY JUST A FEW FIGURES FOR THE RECORDS.
AS MARY STATED, MOST OF THE UNITS ARE VERY SMALL.
THE MODE IF YOU WILL, IS LESS THAN 250FT2 BUT ON AVERAGE THE
CURRENT UNIT MIX IS SLIGHTLY LESS THAN 400FT2.
>> AND WITH THE PROPOSED PROJECT THAT AVERAGE WOULD
INCREASE TO A LITTLE OVER SEVEN HUNDRED SQUARE FEET.
>> SO I JUST WANTED TO MAKE SURE THAT WAS CRYSTAL CLEAR.
AND THEN I ALSO WANTED TO CLARIFY THE SIX UNITS THAT ARE
IN THE EXISTING BAY CONNECTOR BUILDING.
THOSE RESIDENTS COULD MOVE TO THE MORGAN BUILDING OR THEY MAY
END UP MOVING TO THE PERRY BUILDING.
IN FACT I SUSPECT MOST OF THEM WOULD END UP MOVING TO THE
PERRY BUILDING WHICH IS NOT A HISTORIC BUILDING.
>> AGAIN, JUST WANT TO CLARIFY THAT ALLEN MURPHY AGAIN WITH
THE FIRM OF PERKINS CHUI. JUST TO CONCLUDE WE AGREE WITH
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S RECOMMENDATIONS ACROSS THE
BOARD AND THAT WAS FOR THE FIRST APPEAL OUR APPEAL THAT I
DISCUSSED EARLIER. WE ALSO AGREE WITH THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S RECOMMENDATION TO DENY THE APPEAL FILED BY SAVE
THE MARINA'S HERITAGE FOR THE REASONS THAT THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT ADDRESSED. AND THAT WOULD BE DENYING BOTH
THE APPEAL OF THE CERTIFICATION BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION OF
THE FINAL YEAR ALSO ITS ISSUANCE OF THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION AND CERTAINLY AVAILABLE IF THERE ARE ANY
QUESTIONS. BUT WE AGREE WITH THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S ANALYSIS OF THOSE APPEALS AND SO I'LL STAND ON
THAT. >> AND WE THANK YOU VERY MUCH
FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION. >> THANK YOU.
AND SO WE WILL NOW GO TO OUR BACK TO OUR FIRST APPELLANTS TO
PRESENT A REBUTTAL ARGUMENT ON THE FINALLY ARE AND SEE YOU FOR
UP TO THREE MINUTES. >> I THINK WE'RE GOING TO SPLIT
OUR TIME AGAIN. >> I'M TANYA ALBUQUERQUE.
AGAIN, HERE'S WHAT I JUST HEARD.
I HEARD THE HERITAGE IS A GREAT PLACE TO LIVE.
I HEARD THE MARINA IS A GREAT NEIGHBORHOOD TO LIVE IN.
I AGREE WITH THAT. BUT WHAT I DIDN'T HEAR IS I
DIDN'T HEAR ANYONE ON THE OTHER SIDE EVEN THOUGH THEY HAD THREE
TIMES AS MUCH TIME AS WE JUST HAD TALK ABOUT THE ILLEGAL
CONVERSION OF THE THREE PROPERTIES THAT ARE ADJACENT TO
THEIR ADAGE FROM RESIDENTIAL TO INSTITUTIONAL USE THAT THE
TAKING AWAY OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING FROM OUR NEIGHBORHOOD.
AND I ALSO DIDN'T HEAR ANY ACKNOWLEDGMENT OF THE REALITY
THAT AT THE HPC HEARING THEY WERE NOT GOING TO ISSUE THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS UNTIL THEY WERE COUNSELED BY
THE CITY ATTORNEY THAT THEY COULD MAKE IT CONDITIONAL.
IT IS CLEAR AS DAY THAT THAT WAS NOT GOING TO HAPPEN UNTIL
THE CITY ATTORNEY ASSURED THEM AGAIN AND AGAIN AND AGAIN THAT
THIS WAS A PATH FORWARD AND THEY WANTED TO FIND A PATH
FORWARD BECAUSE THEY WANTED TO FIND A WAY TO SUPPORT THAT
MISSION OF SENIOR LIVING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND WE ARE SUPPORTIVE OF SENIOR HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
OUR MESSAGE IS JUST THAT THIS PROJECT RIGHT NOW IS ILL
CONCEIVED, IT'S TOO BIG AND IT'S DETRIMENTAL TO THIS
LANDMARK AND IT IS IT IS OUR REQUEST THAT YOU EITHER SUPPORT
THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS AND KEEP
CONDITION ONE AS IT IS OR OVERTURN THE CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS AND SEND IT BACK TO THE HPC AND TO THE
I.R.S. TO FOLLOW NORMAL PROTOCOL.
>> I'M GOING TO STOP THERE. HELLO, STEVE WILLIAMS AGAIN.
YOU KNOW, AS TANYA SAID, WHAT WE HEARD WAS FINANCIAL
NECESSITY. WE'RE IN A FINANCIAL CRISIS.
SAVE US. THIS GIANT PROJECT IS THE ONLY
WAY WE CAN SAVE OURSELVES. THAT HAS NOTHING TO DO WITH
FOLLOWING THE PLANNING CODE OR FOLLOWING THE LAW OR FOLLOWING
THE RULES. AND HERITAGE HAS NOT DONE THAT.
AND WHAT PLANNING IS SUGGESTING IS SO INCREDIBLY CYNICAL.
THE HPC CLEARLY DID NOT THINK THIS PROJECT FIT WITHIN THE
SECRETARY OF INTERIOR STANDARDS .
THEY CLEARLY THOUGHT THAT THIS NEW BUILDING WOULD OVERWHELM
AND OVERPOWER THE LANDMARK THE LANDMARK THAT THIS BOARD
APPROVED ABOUT TWO MONTHS AGO. >> AND NOW THEY'RE SAYING OH,
IT'S UNNECESSARY TO HAVE THE CONDITION OF OF APPROVAL.
DON'T SEND IT BACK. JUST WIPE OUT THE CONDITION YOU
SAW WITH YOUR OWN EYES. THE HPC ASKING SHOULD WE MAKE
IT VAGUE? >> AND BEING TOLD OVER AND OVER
AGAIN YES. THE MORE VAGUE IT IS THE BETTER
THE FLEXIBILITY. >> ALSO CAN WE CAN WE MAKE IT
CONDITIONAL YOU HEARD OVER AND OVER AGAIN YES, ABSOLUTELY.
YOU CAN MAKE IT CONDITIONAL. >> NOW IN A KAFKAESQUE TURN OF
EVENTS, THOSE ARE THE VERY ARGUMENTS THAT ARE MADE AGAINST
THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS.
THE VERY ADVICE THAT THEY RECEIVED FROM PLANNING AND THE
CITY ATTORNEY IS NOW THE BASIS OF THE APPEAL.
>> DON'T DON'T FALL FOR IT. >> GRANT THE APPEAL.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
AND WE WILL NOW HEAR FROM OUR SECOND APPELLANT, THE PROJECT
SPONSOR ON THE SIU AND CERTIFICATE OF
APPROPRIATENESS. REBUTTAL OR NO PUBLIC COMMENT
OR DOWNLOAD PUBLIC COMMENT? NOPE NOPE.
>> BUT IT'S THE RULES. ALL RIGHT.
>> OKAY. >> OH, MR. WHITE WE TOOK PUBLIC
COMMENT ON BOTH APPELLANTS. >> WE TOOK PUBLIC COMMENT BUT
YOU DIDN'T TAKE IT ALL IN REBUTTAL.
WHAT YOU DO EACH OF PUBLIC COMMENTS ON OPENING STATEMENT
NOW THEY DO IN REBUTTAL AND I WANT TO GIVE A MORE PUBLIC
COMMENT. >> YOU'RE NOT GOING TO WIN THIS
ARGUMENT ON NOT BECAUSE BECAUSE THE CLERK IS GOING TO EXPLAIN
OUR RULES. >> ALL RIGHT, SIR.
YOU PUT THEY PUT THEM OUT WHEN THEY SAID THAT THE PLACE IS
GOING TO BE 800FT2. AIN'T NO SENIOR CITIZEN WILL BE
ABLE TO TRANSFER OVER AND MOVE HERE TO A PLACE THAT'S 800FT2.
>> WE WE GOT TO GO. WE GOT TO KEEP MOVING.
>> WELL, WHY DO WE SAY THAT WHEN ALL THE PEOPLE IN HERE
PROTESTING DADDY BULL, YOU DIDN'T DO A THING WHEN
HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE IN HERE DISTURBED EVERYBODY FOR THREE.
>> BUT I WANT TO HEAR A COMPANY THAT WAS BUILT IN DUNBAR.
>> WE GOT ONE COMING UP HERE. >> YOU KNOW WHAT YOU GOT?
>> PLAY A LITTLE CLIP. OKAY.
YEAH. >> BACK TO LATER.
TALK TO ME LIKE I TELL YOU. INSULT MY INTELLIGENCE MAN.
WHAT YOU RACISM. >> ALL RIGHT.
BACK TO OUR PROJECT SPONSOR. THANK YOU.
ALAN MURPHY ON BEHALF OF THE PROJECT SPONSOR.
>> I THINK THE ONLY ADDITIONAL POINT I'LL MAKE IS THAT THE
FINDINGS MADE BY THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION DO
AMPLY SUPPORT ISSUANCE OF THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
AND THAT WAS ONE OF THE POINTS WE MADE AND OUR APPEAL IS THAT
IT WAS UNNECESSARY TO HAVE CONDITION OF APPROVAL ONE
BECAUSE IN FACT THE RECORD AND THE FINDINGS MADE BY THE
STORK PRESERVATION COMMISSION DID SUPPORT ISSUANCE OF THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS WITHOUT THAT CONDITION OR
ALTERNATIVELY AS THAT CONDITION WOULD BE MODIFIED BY AS
RECOMMENDED BY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
SO JUST TO CONCLUDE WE DO SUPPORT THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S RECOMMENDATIONS ACROSS THE BOARD AND WE AGREE
WITH THE ANALYSIS AS WELL. AND SO RATHER THAN REPEATING
THAT ANALYSIS ON THE POINTS RAISED BY THE OTHER APPELLANT,
WE WILL YOU KNOW AGAIN WE AGREE WITH THE DEPARTMENT'S ANALYSIS
THERE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
DON'T SEE ANY OH, SHALL I CALL ON YOU OR SHALL I CLOSE THE
HEARINGS FIRST? >> OKAY.
SEEING NO ONE ON THE ROSTER THESE PUBLIC HEARINGS ITEMS 25
,29 AND 33 HAVE BEEN HELD AND ARE NOW FILED AND I THINK
SUPERVISOR CHERYL YOU MIGHT HAVE WANTED TO SAY SOMETHING.
>> WELL, I DID I MAKE A MISTAKE THERE.
I WANTED TO ASK A COUPLE OF QUESTIONS.
OH, DID I MAKE IT WAS OH, BY BY ALL MEANS.
>> IS IT A GOOD HEARING? IT'S A MATTER NO.
OKAY. JUST GO AHEAD.
OKAY, GREAT. >> SORRY.
OKAY, SO FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU ALL FOR BEING HERE FROM
FROM ALL SIDES. THIS IS OBVIOUSLY COMPLICATED
AND NOT SIMPLE. SO I WANT TO ASK QUICKLY ABOUT
TRAFFIC CONDITIONS ON BAY AND LAGUNA, SOMETHING I'M
PERSONALLY FAMILIAR WITH. I'VE STUDIED THE EYE INJURY
NETWORK. >> CAN WE TALK A LITTLE BIT
ABOUT WHAT HERITAGE IS PLANNING TO DO TO ENSURE TRAFFIC SAFETY
FOR THIS PRETTY HIGHLY TRAFFICKED INTERSECTION THERE
AND SPECIFICALLY TO DRIVE DRIVEWAY LOADING AND OPERATIONS
PLAN? >> SURE.
ALAN MURPHY ON BEHALF OF THE PROJECT SPONSOR THERE IS A
ROBUST DRIVEWAY LOADING IS AN OPERATION PLAN THAT IS REQUIRED
AS A CONDITION OF APPROVAL ON THE PROJECT TO ENSURE THAT
LOADING CONDITIONS ARE ACTUALLY BETTER THAN THEY ARE
IN EXISTING CONDITIONS. EVEN WITH THE PROPOSED PROJECT
. >> SO THAT IS ONE OF THE KEY
FEATURES OF THE PROJECT APPROVAL.
IN ADDITION, THE PROJECT INCORPORATES OTHER ELEMENTS TO
IMPROVE SAFETY AND BAY STREET THAT INCLUDES IMPROVING THE
DRIVEWAY ENTRANCE FURTHER DOWN ALONG BAY AWAY FROM THE
INTERSECTION WITH LAGUNA AND ALSO MAKING A ONE DIRECTION
DRIVEWAY. BOTH THOSE IMPROVEMENTS
ACTUALLY WILL FURTHER IMPROVE TRAFFIC SAFETY ON BAY.
AND THEN FINALLY THERE'S A PLANNING CODE REQUIREMENT FOR
NEW PROJECTS WHICH THIS PROJECT IS SUBJECT TO TO INSTALL BULB
OR TO HAVE BOTH BOATS INSTALLED ON.
I BELIEVE IT'S TWO CORNERS OF THE PROJECT AND THAT WILL
FURTHER INCREASE PEDESTRIAN SAFETY IN THAT VICINITY AS
WELL. SO OVERALL THE PROJECT NOT ONLY
WILL NOT EXACERBATE ANY EXISTING CONDITIONS ALONG BAY
BUT ACTUALLY WILL IMPROVE TRAFFIC SAFETY AND THAT'S AN
MTA APPROVAL. DO I HAVE THAT RIGHT THERE?
BOTH BOATS ARE REQUIRED FIRST FOR THE DRIVEWAY LOADING
AND OPERATIONS PLAN THE FOR THE FULL DRIVEWAY LOADING
AND OPERATIONS PLAN ULTIMATELY WILL BE APPROVED BY THE CITY.
>> I DON'T KNOW WHICH DEPARTMENT WHO WHO APPROVES
THAT? WHICH OPERATOR THE CHAIR YES.
>> THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT APPROVES THE DRIVEWAY LOADING
QUESTIONS PLEASE. OKAY, GREAT.
AND THAT IS NECESSARY FOR THE THE PROJECT TO GO FORWARD?
YES, THAT IS CORRECT. >> OKAY.
THANK YOU. CAN WE TALK ABOUT CAN WE TALK
ABOUT THE NOTIFICATION PROCESS HERE?
IT SOUNDS LIKE THERE'S IT GOT NOTICED CORRECTLY.
IT DIDN'T GET NOTICED CORRECTLY.
>> WHY DID THIS PROJECT HAVE TO GET NOTICED?
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FOR THE QUESTION THROUGH THE CHAIR.
MEGAN CALVIN PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF WE REISSUED
THE NOTICE OF PREPARATION OF THE DRAFT IIR BECAUSE WHEN WE
INITIALLY ISSUED THE NOTICE OF PREPARATION WE MADE TWO
PROCEDURAL ERRORS. WE DID NOT FILE IT WITH THE
STATE CLEARING HOUSE WHICH IS REQUIRED UNDER SEQUA AND WE
DIDN'T POST A NEWSPAPER AD WHICH IS REQUIRED PER CHAPTER
31 OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE. SO UPON RECOGNIZING THOSE
ERRORS WE WENT AHEAD AND REISSUED THE NOTICE OF
PREPARATION SO THAT MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC COULD HAVE FULL
OPPORTUNITY TO COMMENT AND WE HONORED COMMENTS FROM THE FIRST
NOTICING PERIOD AS WELL AS THE SECOND NOTICING PERIOD.
>> THANK YOU. >> CAN YOU JUST ADDRESS THE
DISCREPANCY BETWEEN THE APPELLANT'S VIEW OF THE
NOTICING AND THE DEPARTMENT'S VIEW THE NOTICING?
>> OH SURE. >> SO IN THE APPELLANT'S LETTER
THEY WERE THEY WERE DISCUSSING THAT THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION WAS NOT PROPERLY NOTICED FOR THE HEARING THAT
OCCURRED ON APRIL 17TH. FOR THE SEQUEL PURPOSES WE ONLY
NOTIFY INTERESTED PARTIES WHICH IS ANYONE THAT COMMENTED ON THE
NOTICE OF PREPARATION OR THE DRAFT R AND WE NOTICED ALL OF
THOSE INDIVIDUALS OF THE R CERTIFICATION HEARING AND AS
WELL AS THE PUBLICATION OF THE RESPONSE TO COMMENTS DOCUMENT
THE APPELLANT BROUGHT UP PLANNING CODE SECTION 306.3
WHICH ONLY REFERS TO PLANNING APPROVALS WHICH RELATES TO THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATIONS OR PERHAPS TO RICH SORRY.
>> SO AND IN PREPARATION FOR THE HPC AND PLANNING COMMISSION
JOINT HEARING WE FOLLOW THE PROCEDURES OF PLANNING CODE
SECTION 333 IN GENERAL. WE'RE ONLY REQUIRED TO NOTIFY
MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC OWNERS AND OCCUPANTS WITHIN 150FT BUT
WE TEND TO OVER NOTICE TOO ABOUT 300FT AND SO ALL OF THAT
NOTIFICATION OCCURRED APPROPRIATELY AND WHAT IS
REQUIRED IN THE PLANNING CODE. >> OKAY.
THANK YOU. TO DO DO THE APPELLANTS WANT TO
ADDRESS THAT ONE IF YOU'D LIKE TO.
>> SURE. OUR CONCERN WAS WITH THE
NOTICING HAD TO DO WITH AS THE CITY SAID THEY GENERALLY DO
300FT. AND WHEN YOU DO A RADIUS OF
300FT ALL THE BUILDINGS IN OUR APPEAL THE RESIDENTS DIDN'T
RECEIVE THAT NOTICE. AND SO I UNDERSTAND THAT THE
REGULATION MIGHT SAY 150FT BUT IF THEY SAY THEIR GENERAL
PATTERN AND PRACTICE IS 300FT THEN I DON'T UNDERSTAND WHY
THESE RESIDENTS OF THESE BUILDINGS THAT ARE CLEARLY
WITHIN 300FT WOULD BE RANDOMLY EXCLUDED.
AND THAT WAS WHY WE RAISED IT. OKAY.
>> THANK YOU. SO I WANT TO TALK QUICKLY ABOUT
THE PLANS THE PROJECT SPONSORS PLANS.
DO THEY SATISFY SECTION SIX SECTION 15 124 WITH WITH SEVEN
SUFFICIENT INFORMATION FOR ANALYSIS AND CERTIFICATION FOR
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REVIEW. >> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION.
MEGAN KAPLAN DEPARTMENT STAFF. SO SECURE UNDER THE SQUARE
GUIDELINES ARTICLE NINE WE ARE REQUESTED TO PROVIDE THE
RELEVANCE OR IT DICTATES THE RELEVANCE SCOPE OF THE IIR
PROJECT DESCRIPTION. AND THAT INCLUDES THE LOCATION
AND PROJECT BOUNDARIES OF THE PROPOSED PROJECT SHOWN ON
DETAILED AND REGIONAL MAPS WHICH WERE INCLUDED IN THE
DRAFT E-R. AND ALSO A GENERAL DESCRIPTION
OF THE PROJECT'S TECHNICAL, ECONOMIC AND ENVIRONMENTAL
CHARACTERISTICS. CONSIDERING THE PRINCIPAL
ENGINEERING PROPOSALS OF THE FACILITIES.
>> AND SO WE LOOKED AT THE WHAT WOULD THE ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS
BE OF THE PROPOSED DEMOLITION OF THE TWO STRUCTURES AS WELL
AS THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE BELOW GRADE PARKING GARAGE, THE
EXCAVATION. ALL OF THOSE THINGS WERE
INCLUDED IN A ROBUST PROJECT DESCRIPTION CHAPTER IN THE
DRAFT IRR. AND SO THE DEPARTMENT STANDS BY
OUR KIND OF FOLLOWING SEQUA IN ORDER TO PROVIDE AN ADEQUATE
PROJECT DESCRIPTION THAT WAS ROBUST.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
SO IT SOUNDS LIKE INTERIM PLANS ARE OKAY FOR THE SITE REVIEW.
>> IS THAT MORE OR LESS AN ACCURATE STATEMENT OR.
>> THAT'S RIGHT. SO THE THE BUILDING DEPARTMENT
WILL REVIEW THE FINAL DESIGN LEVEL PROJECT PLANS WHICH THEN
WILL COME BACK TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT WHICH OUR CURRENT
PLANNER WILL LOOK AT AND MAKE SURE THAT THEY THE PLANS MATCH
WHAT WAS APPROVED AT THE PLANNING COMMISSION ON APRIL
17TH. IF THERE'S ANY CHANGES WE WOULD
FLAG THAT AND THEN NEED TO EITHER DO ADDITIONAL ANALYSIS
OR HAVE THE PROJECT SPONSOR YOU KNOW MAKE SURE THAT THE PLANS
LINE UP TO FINAL PLANS COULD GET DISAPPROVED OR BE WE THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT WILL REVIEW THE PLANS BEFORE THE BUILDING
PERMIT IS APPROVED. >> THANK YOU.
AND JUST GENERALLY WHY WASN'T THE ER NEEDED FOR THE PROJECT?
AND I GUESS AS YEAH WHY WAS IT NEEDED FOR THE PROJECT?
SO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT MAKES A DETERMINATION OF FIRST
WHETHER A PROJECT IS A PROJECT UNDER SEQUA.
WE DETERMINED THAT IT WOULD HAVE ENVIRONMENTAL EFFECTS SO
WE NEEDED TO PREPARE AN ENVIRONMENTAL DOCUMENT AND THEN
WE LOOKED AT WHETHER THERE WOULD BE ANY POTENTIAL
SIGNIFICANT EFFECTS BECAUSE THE JULIA MORGAN BUILDING WAS
ALREADY BEING TREATED AS A HISTORIC RESOURCE.
IT WAS IDENTIFIED AS A HISTORIC RESOURCE.
THIS IS EVEN PRIOR TO IT BEING LANDMARKED OUT OF AN ABUNDANCE
OF CAUTION WE PREPARED AN ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT
WHICH IS OUR HIGHEST LEVEL OF ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW TO FOCUS
ON TWO AREAS CULTURAL RESOURCES SPECIFICALLY HISTORIC
ARCHITECTURAL RESOURCES AT THE JULIA MORGAN BUILDING MAKING
SURE THAT THAT THERE WOULD NOT BE ANY SIGNIFICANT OR.
TO EVALUATE WHETHER THERE WOULD BE SIGNIFICANT EFFECTS.
AND WE LOOKED AT AIR QUALITY BECAUSE THE PROJECT IS LOCATED
IN THE AIR POLLUTANT EXPOSURE ZONE AND THE AND THERE'S
EXCAVATION INVOLVED WITH THE PROJECT AND THROUGH THAT
ANALYSIS WE FOUND THAT THERE WOULD NOT BE ANY SIGNIFICANT
UNAVOIDABLE EFFECTS BUT WE WERE ALREADY IN THE PROCESS OF
PREPARING THE EIA. SO WE IDENTIFIED SIX MITIGATION
MEASURES THAT WOULD REDUCE ANY SIGNIFICANT EFFECTS TO LESSEN
SIGNIFICANT WITH MITIGATION. >> OKAY.
THANK YOU. COULD TURN TO THE CERTIFICATE
OF APPROPRIATENESS. SO THIS ISSUE WITH HPC AND THE
ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE IS IS OBVIOUSLY QUITE UNUSUAL.
>> SO WHEN DOES WHEN DOES A PROJECT TYPICALLY GO TO THE
ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE IN A PROCESS LIKE THIS?
>> HI RICHARD. THROUGH THE CHAIR TYPICALLY WE
SCHEDULE PROJECTS FOR THE ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE
THAT ARE INVOLVING INFILL NEW CONSTRUCTION WITHIN A HISTORIC
DISTRICT. IS OUR CURRENT STANDARD OR WHEN
THE DEPARTMENT FEELS THAT WE NEED ADDITIONAL DESIGN ADVICE?
SO IN MOST CASES IF WE FEEL COMFORTABLE WITH EITHER THE
DESIGN OR THE PROJECT AND WHETHER OR NOT IT MEETS THE
STANDARDS OF ARTICLE TEN AND MEETS THE SECRETARY OF
INTERIOR STANDARDS, WE WILL NOT SCHEDULE IT FOR ARCHITECTURAL
REVIEW COMMITTEE. >> THE ONLY TIME THAT WE DO
SCHEDULE ARCHITECTURE OR REVIEW COMMITTEE AS A MATTER OF POLICY
IS WHEN THE PROJECT IS NEW INFILL, NEW CONSTRUCTION WITHIN
A HISTORIC DISTRICT. GREAT.
BUT DOES DOES THE ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE USUALLY HAPPEN
BEFORE THE HPC? >> YES.
HERE IT'S CORRECT OR AFTER. BEFORE BEFORE.
OKAY SO IS IS THERE PRECEDENT FOR A PROJECT TO HAVE IT'S
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS I GUESS APPROVED AND THEN THEN
GO TO THE ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE FOR I GUESS RE
APPROVAL OR ADJUSTMENTS NOT TYPICAL IN MY EXPERIENCE
AND I'VE BEEN WITH THE CITY FOR 15 YEARS WE'VE NEVER HAD
ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE AFTER A PROJECT APPROVAL.
>> NEVER IN 15 YEARS. >> OH OKAY.
SO I MEAN I GUESS I GUESS I'M I DON'T UNDERSTAND WHAT WHAT
HAPPENED THERE AND THEN I ALSO IN ONE OF THE DOCUMENTS YOU YOU
YOU PREPARED YOU WROTE ARCC CANNOT CONDUCT ITS REVIEW AFTER
EACH PC IF THAT'S AN ACCURATE STATEMENT WHY DID THIS RULING
GET MADE WHAT HAPPENED? >> I THINK AND I MIGHT DEFER TO
THE CITY ATTORNEY FOR A LITTLE ASSISTANCE ON THIS ONE AS I
UNDERSTAND THAT IT WAS A BIT OF AN UNUSUAL REQUEST
AND TYPICALLY WHEN WE ARE RESPONDING TO COMMISSIONER
COMMENTS WE'RE TRYING BEST TO TRY AND FIGURE OUT HOW ALL OF
THIS FITS. AND ALSO A FACTOR IN THAT THERE
IS A LEGAL FRAMEWORK THAT MIGHT BE THERE OR IT MIGHT NOT BE
THERE AND SO WE WILL OFTEN TRY AND WORK WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY
TO FIGURE OUT A COMPROMISE OR CRAFT CONDITIONS OF APPROVAL
THAT MIGHT MEET THE INTENT OF WHAT THE COMMISSIONER WOULD
WANT IN THIS INSTANCE. SO I THINK IN THIS PARTICULAR
INSTANCE WE NEEDED ADDITIONAL INFORMATION TO GIVE A FIRM
FINDING AND ESPECIALLY IN HINDSIGHT WE RECOGNIZED WE
NEEDED KIND OF A LITTLE BIT MORE TIME TO SEE HOW THIS
PROJECT FITS WITHIN THE LARGER FRAMEWORK OF OTHER LAWS THAT
ARE APPLICABLE. >> SO IN THIS CASE PARTICULARLY
THE PERMIT STREAMLINING ACT. >> OKAY.
HONESTLY I DON'T UNDERSTAND WHAT THAT MEANS AND I DON'T
UNDERSTAND WHAT THAT MEANS AND WHY IT HAPPENED THIS WAY.
I MEAN IF THE ANSWER IS IT WAS A MISTAKE AND IT SHOULDN'T HAVE
HAPPENED THIS WAY, IT WAS A MISTAKE.
I THINK THAT'S A FAIR ANSWER. PEOPLE MAKE MISTAKES.
I JUST WANT TO CLARIFY I HONESTLY I DON'T THINK WE NEED
TO HOLD PEOPLE TO TASK FOR MAKING MISTAKES IS A VERY FAIR
THING IN A VERY COMPLICATED SITUATION.
FOR THIS I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE I ACTUALLY UNDERSTAND I'LL
DEFER TO THE DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY FOR SOME ASSISTANCE.
>> GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD
ROSSI. I WAS NOT AT THAT HEARING
OBVIOUSLY AND MY UNDERSTANDING AFTER REVIEWING THE CHARTER
PROVISION AND THE PLANNING CODE PROVISIONS AT ISSUE HERE IS
THAT THE HPC CAN'T DELEGATE AUTHORITY TO THE ARCHITECTURE
REVIEW COMMITTEE TO APPROVE THE PROJECT.
AND THIS DELEGATION WAS VERY BROAD AND IT I THINK CAN BE
READ TO REQUIRE OR AUTHORIZE THE COMMITTEE TO APPROVE THE
FINAL PROJECT. WHAT YOU HAVE BEFORE YOU OF
COURSE WHAT THIS APPEAL IS ABOUT THE BOARD HAS THE
AUTHORITY. IT'S A DE NOVO REVIEW.
YOU HAVE THE AUTHORITY TO REVIEW THE ENTIRE RECORD
AND MAKE YOUR DECISION AND ON THAT PARTICULAR CONDITION I
WOULD AGREE WITH THE PLANNING'S RECOMMENDATION.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SO THEN I GUESS FOR PROJECTS
INVOLVING LANDMARKS, THIS THIS OBVIOUSLY IS AN ATYPICAL OR
UNIMPRESSIVE ANTED SITUATION. CAN YOU TELL ME THE STANDARD
PROCESS FOR PLANNING TO REVIEW AND APPROVE FINAL ARCHITECTURAL
DESIGNS? >> SO IN A TYPICAL PROCESS THE
COMMISSION WILL APPROVE A PROJECT IF THE COMMISSION HAS
ADDITIONAL CONDITIONS OR CONCERNS THEY TYPICALLY
IDENTIFY WHAT THEY ARE. AND THEN WE WORK WITH THE
SPONSOR. IT'S GOING TO ENSURE THAT THE
COMMISSION'S INTENT IS ULTIMATELY FOLLOW THROUGH
WITHIN WHATEVER FINAL DESIGNS THAT OCCUR AND HAPPEN OVER TIME
. SO SMALL TWEAKS FOR EXAMPLE
TOWARDS INTERIOR FEATURES MAY OCCUR OVER TIME OR SMALL
REFINEMENTS IN THE EXTERIOR OR KIND OF MATERIALS BUT
ULTIMATELY WE HAVE TO FOLLOW THROUGH WITH WHAT THE DESIGN
WAS THAT WAS APPROVED BY OUR COMMISSIONS AND FOLLOW THROUGH
ACCORDINGLY. SO AS A PROJECT TRANSITIONS
FROM ENTITLEMENT OR THE PUBLIC HEARING PHASE ON TO THE
BUILDING PERMIT PHASE, THERE IS ADDITIONALLY MORE WORK THAT THE
ARCHITECTURAL TEAMS WILL DO TO ENSURE THAT THE PROJECT CAN
ACTUALLY BE BUILT ACCORDING TO BUILDING CODE AND OTHER CITY
CODES. >> SO IT WOULD BE STANDARD FOR
HPC TO APPROVE A CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS AND ASK THE
PROJECT SPONSOR TO WORK WITH THE DEPARTMENT AFTERWARDS.
>> YEAH THAT'S FAIRLY TYPICAL ESPECIALLY IF THEY'VE
IDENTIFIED SPECIFIC ISSUES THAT THEY WOULD LIKE US TO WORK WITH
THE SPONSOR ON. >> OKAY.
OKAY. OKAY.
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION THERE THERE WAS SOME TALK OF
VIOLATIONS OF THE EXISTING CONDITIONAL USE FOSSILIZATION
RELATED TO I THINK IT'S PROPERTIES ADJACENT TO THE
PROJECT SITE ON THE PROJECT SITE ADJACENT TO THE PROJECT
SITE ARE THESE TWO ARE THESE TWO ARE THE PROPERTIES ON THE
PROJECT SITE OR NOT ON THE PROJECT SITE?
>> THE ONES THAT THE THE ONES WHICH ARE GREAT RIGHT NOW THOSE
PROPERTIES IDENTIFIED IN THE LATTER APPEAL ARE NOT PROJECT
ARE NOT PART OF THE PROJECT SITE THEY'RE NOT PART OF THE
PROJECT SITE CAN YOU WOULD CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
FOR THE PROJECT CAN YOU USE ADJACENT PROPERTIES WHEN
DISCUSSING CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION OF IF THEY'RE NOT
PART OF THE PROJECT SITE WE DON'T ANALYZE THEM TYPICALLY SO
IN THIS INSTANCE THE ONE OF THE APPELLANT'S BROUGHT UP ADJACENT
PROPERTIES THAT ARE RELATED IT SOUNDS LIKE TO THE APPROVAL BUT
IF IT'S NOT PART OF WHAT THE SPONSOR IS SUBMITTING THEIR
DISCUSSION IS IS A BIT IRRELEVANT IN THE DISCUSSION OF
THE ACTUAL LAND USE ENTITLEMENT AND WHAT WE'RE ALLOWING ON A
SPECIFIC SITE. >> OKAY.
DO WE KNOW HAVE HAS THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT LOOKED INTO
THESE OTHER BUILDINGS? ARE WE ARE THERE ACTIVE
VIOLATIONS? >> WE WE HAVE NOT AND SO
AND WE'RE HAPPY TO. USUALLY WHEN THE CLAIMS ABOUT
VIOLATIONS OCCUR OUR STAFF WILL FOLLOW UP ACCORDINGLY
AND FOLLOW THROUGH WITH THEM. AS WE UNDERSTAND JUST BY A
SEARCH OF THE BUILDING PERMIT RECORD THEY'RE STILL
IN RESIDENTIAL USE SO THEY WOULD COMPLY WITH THE
UNDERLYING ZONING THAT'S ALLOWED THERE.
>> SO SO YOU HAVE LOOK THEY DO COMPLY, IS THAT CORRECT?
SO THERE ARE STILL RESIDENTIAL USE.
SO YOU LOOKED AT THEM AND SO THERE ARE NO VIOLATIONS.
IS THAT AN ACCURATE STATEMENT? I THOUGHT I READ THAT
SOMEWHERE. I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE I'M
READING IT AS I UNDERSTAND THAT WE HAVE I DON'T MEAN YOU
PERSONALLY THAT WOULD MAKE YOU SUPERMAN.
>> OKAY. OKAY.
>> I HAVE NO FURTHER QUESTIONS. I DON'T KNOW IF ANY OF MY
COLLEAGUES WOULD LIKE TO THANK YOU.
ARE IT IN THE QUEUE FOR QUESTIONS?
>> SUPERVISOR OKAY. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO OBVIOUSLY THIS IS AN INCREDIBLY COMPLICATED
AND MAYBE UNPRECEDENTED USE YOUR WORDS RICH SITUATION FIRST
OF ALL TO THE PLANNING STAFF AND THE CITY ATTORNEY'S TEAM.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR DILIGENCE ON THIS MATTER IS INCREDIBLY
COMPLICATED AND I REALLY APPRECIATE YOU ALL BEING HERE
TO ANSWER ALL THESE QUESTIONS AGAIN TO TO BOTH THE APPELLANTS
,THE PROJECT SPONSORS, TO THE NEIGHBORS.
>> THANK YOU ALL FOR BEING HERE.
YOU KNOW, HERITAGE ON THE MARINA IS OBVIOUSLY A VERY LONG
STANDING INSTITUTION. YOU KNOW, WE HEARD HOW THEY'RE
PROPOSING TO BUILD TWO NEW FACILITIES AND ADD SENIOR
UNITS. >> WE HEARD A LOT OF THINGS
SINCE THIS APPEAL WAS FILED. YOU KNOW, I MET WITH THE
PROJECT SPONSORS, APPELLANTS PLANNING DEPARTMENT WALKED THE
BLOCKS MANY TIMES INCLUDING THIS WEEKEND.
YOU KNOW, I ALSO HAVE EXAMINED THE CITY'S HIGH INJURY NETWORK
MAPS ABOUT TRAFFIC QUITE FRANKLY, THAT CONCERNS ME
DEEPLY. YOU KNOW, SO HEARING ABOUT
MOVING THE ENTRANCE FURTHER AWAY FROM FROM WHAT IS A I
BELIEVE I WROTE DOWN FIVE INJURIES OR FIVE CRASHES AT BAY
AND LAGUNA INTERSECTION NOT IN THE MID-BLOCK ACTUALLY
IN THE LAST FIVE YEARS SO I LIKE THE IDEA THAT THAT THE
ENTRANCE BEING MOVED AWAY BUT YOU KNOW DESPITE THAT I SUPPORT
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S CONCLUSION THAT THE PROJECT
DOESN'T CREATE SIGNIFICANT AND UNAVOIDABLE IMPACTS UNDER
CEQA AND THAT SEEMS PRETTY CLEAR TO ME BASED ON OUR
PLANNING CODE AND FRANKLY IT'S A VERY YOU KNOW, IT'S A IT'S A
DECENTLY HIGH LEGAL THRESHOLD AND THE ISSUES ON THE AIR
APPEAL TO ME DON'T REACH THAT LEGAL THRESHOLD NECESSARY TO
OVERTURN THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S UNANIMOUS APPROVAL
OF THE AIR. THAT SAID, I WILL CONTINUE
AND I WANT TO MENTION OF THE PROJECT SPONSORS I WILL
CONTINUE TO MONITOR THE PROJECT TO ENSURE FULL COMPLIANCE WITH
WITH THE MITIGATION MEASURES THAT WERE MENTIONED AND TO
ENSURE THAT ADVERSE ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS DON'T
OCCUR DURING CONSTRUCTION. I THINK FOR FOR THE RESIDENTS
NOT ONLY OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD BUT THE CITY.
>> SO THE CONDITIONAL YOUTH AUTHORIZATION AND CERTIFICATE
OF APPROPRIATENESS, YOU KNOW, I THINK SAVED THE MARINA'S
HERITAGE, RAISED SOME SOME CONCERNS AND YOU KNOW, THOSE
ARE ONES WE NEED TO LOOK AT SERIOUSLY.
YOU KNOW SOME ABOUT OWNERSHIP OF DIFFERENT BUILDINGS MERGING
OF UNITS. >> YOU KNOW, BASED ON WHAT I
JUST HEARD, THERE ARE NOT VIOLATIONS AND BECAUSE THEY'RE
TECHNICALLY NOT PART OF THE PROJECT SITE, THEY'RE THERE.
IT'S NOT APPROPRIATE TO CONSIDER THEM IN EITHER OF
THESE TWO. AND YOU KNOW, THE PLANNING CODE
SEEMS TO BE PRETTY CLEAR HERE ABOUT WHAT IT'S REVIEWABLE FOR
THESE APPROVALS NOW. NOW THAT SAID, HERITAGE ON THE
MARINA HAS A RESPONSIBILITY TO BE A GOOD NEIGHBOR.
SO I, I REALLY DO EXPECT THEM TO MAINTAIN OPEN COMMUNICATION
,YOU KNOW, WITH THEIR NEIGHBORS AND TAKE THAT
SERIOUSLY DESPITE ALL THIS AND YOU KNOW, I DON'T I DON'T
THINK WE QUITE MEET THE HIGH LEGAL THRESHOLD TO REJECT THIS
PROJECT THAT WILL ADD, YOU KNOW, 23 NEW NEW UNITS FOR
SENIORS. >> SO SO FINALLY CONDITION ONE
THIS IS, YOU KNOW, A REALLY CHALLENGING ONE.
>> YOU KNOW, PROJECT MASSING WAS OBVIOUSLY A CONCERN BUT
FROM WHAT I HEARD THE WAY THAT THAT WAS PUT DOWN WAS
ESSENTIALLY INAPPROPRIATE. >> SO YOU KNOW, I THINK I PLAN
TO SUPPORT MODIFIED LANGUAGE THAT THAT CORRESPONDS WITH THE
EXISTING DEPARTMENTAL PRACTICES THAT THAT ENSURES WE WILL MEET
THE PERMIT STREAMLINING ACT AND WE DON'T KIND OF VIOLATE
STATE LAW HERE. SO WITH ALL THAT SAID AND SORRY
FOR THE RAMBLING I'D LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION ON THE SEX
APPEAL. I MOVE TO APPROVE ITEM 26
AND TABLE ITEMS 27 AND 28. >> ALL RIGHT COLLEAGUE
SUPERVISOR CHERYL HAS MADE A MOTION AGAIN TO AFFIRM THE
SECRET DETERMINATION BY APPROVING ITEM 26 TABLING ITEMS
2728 I BELIEVE. IS THAT A SECOND?
THAT'S NOT A SECOND AT FIRST. IS THERE A SECOND FOR THAT
SECOND BY DORSEY NOW SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMANDA
AMENDMENT WITH ALL DUE RESPECT TO SUPERVISOR CHERYL I AGREE
THAT I YOU KNOW I CONCUR WITH AFFIRMING THE AIR FORCE DOES
PROJECT HOWEVER I DO NOT CONCUR WITH TO CONDITIONALLY REVERSE
THE AIR PARTICULARLY ABOUT REMOVING THE CONDITION OF
APPROVAL THAT WAS ACTUALLY PUT IN PLACE BY HISTORIC
PRESERVATION COMMISSION CLEARLY THAT THEY HAVE SOME QUESTIONS
AND THEREFORE WHILE IT MAY BE QUESTIONABLE THAT THEY PUT INTO
THESE WHILE THEY APPROVE THE CERTIFICATE APPROPRIATENESS IS
ON THE CONDITION THAT IT WOULD LIKE TO HAVE FURTHER REVIEW.
>> I THINK THAT I WANT TO AFFIRM AND SUPPORT FOR THE
HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION ACTION TO IMPOSE THE
ACTION OF THE CONDITION FOR APPROVAL.
SO IF I MAY YOU KNOW TO IS TO SEVER THAT MOTION ONE BY ONE
YOU OF THAT'S OKAY AND THAT I CAN ACTUALLY VOTE IN SUPPORT OF
ITEM 26 TO AFFIRM THE AIR. HOWEVER I WILL NOT BE
IN SUPPORT OF ITEM 27 TO REMOVE THE CONDITION APPROVAL UH.
ALL RIGHT. LET ME LET ME LET ME TRY TO LET
ME AT LEAST SITUATE MYSELF. I'M GOING TO ASK STAFF TO
CORRECT AND CITY ATTORNEY TO CORRECT ME IF I'M GETTING THIS
WRONG. >> I THINK WE'RE VOTING BASED.
WE GOT THREE VOTES COMING AT US OR POSSIBLY TWO DEPENDING ON
HOW THE THE NEXT SET OF THINGS IS DESCRIBED.
>> BUT THE FIRST VOTE I BELIEVE IS JUST ON THE CERTIFICATION OF
THE FINAL ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT AND DOESN'T IMPACT
WHETHER WE THINK THAT THE CONDITION IMPOSED BY THE
HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION SHOULD STAY OR GO.
SO IF WE THINK THAT THE ENVIRONMENTAL THAT THE AIR
ADEQUATELY ANALYZED ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS AM I
GETTING THIS RIGHT OR WRONG? THEY ARE NODDING.
SO MR. CITY ATTORNEY DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD RUSSELL YES.
>> THE SUPERVISOR CHERYL HAS MADE A MOTION ONLY WITH RESPECT
TO THE SEX APPEAL AND I THINK THE OTHER TWO APPEALS WILL BE
ADDRESSED LATER IN HIS FURTHER MOTION TWO MORE MOTIONS
AND THERE'S 1 OR 2 MORE MOTIONS.
RIGHT. SO THE THE HISTORIC
PRESERVATION APPEAL WILL BE ON A MOTION RELATED ONLY TO THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS IF THAT'S THE CONDITION THAT
YOU'RE CONCERNED ABOUT. >> SUPERVISOR SO FOR THIS IF WE
WANT TO AFFIRM THE SEQUEL REGARDLESS OF OUR VIEWS ON THE
SEE YOU AND THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS WE WOULD VOTE
YES IF WE THINK THAT THE AIR IS INADEQUATE OR THERE'S SOMETHING
THEY DIDN'T THEY GOT WRONG IN THE ENVIRONMENTAL ANALYSIS
WE WOULD VOTE NO ON THE MOTION TO PROVIDE JAN THANK YOU.
>> AND SO THAT MEANS THAT WE'RE ADDRESSING THE AIR CURRENTLY
WITH 20 THROUGH 26 TO 38 AND THEN THAT WE WILL BE
ADDRESSING THE YOU FROM THE ITEMS OF 30 TO 32.
>> THANK YOU. IT'S 26 TO 28 ARE JUST SECURE.
>> 30 TO 32 ARE JUST CONDITIONAL USE AND 30 FOUR
THROUGH 3634 THROUGH 36 OUR CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS
THANK YOU. >> THIS IS A LITTLE CONFUSING
TO ME BECAUSE I THINK THE ISSUE IF THERE ARE ISSUES WITH THE
SEE YOU THEY STEM FROM THE SIGNIFICANT IMPROVEMENTS.
>> WE'LL TALK ABOUT THAT IN A MINUTE.
ALL RIGHT. SO IS EVERYBODY CLEAR EVERYBODY
CLEAR ON HOW THEY'RE VOTING ON THE MOTION MADE BY SUPERVISOR
CHERYL SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR DORSEY TO AFFIRM THE SECRET
DETERMINATION BY APPROVING ITEM 26 AND TABLING ITEMS 27 AND 28
. >> LAST CALL, MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL. YES.
ON THE MOTION TO APPROVE ITEM 26 AND TABLE 27 AND 28
SUPERVISOR SARTOR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN I CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR
I THERE ARE ALL RIGHT THANK YOU MADAM CLERK WITHOUT OBJECTION
ITEM 26 IS APPROVED ITEMS 27 AND 28 ARE TABLED.
>> ALL RIGHT, WE GOT SIX MORE ITEMS TO GO.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL LOOKS LIKE YOU HAVE SLOTS.
>> ALL RIGHT, SO ON THE CONDITIONAL USE APPEAL I WANT
TO MOVE TO AND TO BE CLEAR HERE, YOU KNOW SUPERVISOR CHAN,
I THINK YOU RAISE FAIR POINTS BUT AT THE END OF THE DAY
UPHOLDING A MISTAKES SEEMS LIKE A MISTAKE ON THE CONDITIONAL
USE APPEAL SO I WANT TO MOVE TO AMEND ITEM 31 DISAPPROVING THE
PLANNING COMMISSION'S DECISION AND REVISE IT TO APPROVE THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION WITH A MINOR MODIFICATION
SPECIFICALLY THE FINDING AND SIX L ON PAGE EIGHT OF THE
COMMISSION'S DECISION TO BE SHOULD BE REVISED TO REMOVE THE
REFERENCE TO FURTHER REVIEW BY THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION
COMMISSION'S ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE WHICH IS
UNNECESSARY FOR THIS PROJECT TO MEET THE REQUIREMENTS FOR
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION UNDER PLANNING CODE SECTION 303
I'LL ALSO MAKE A MOTION TO REVISE WBC'S DECISION ON THIS
ISSUE AND WE GET TO THAT ITEM BUT INSTEAD A FINAL REVIEW FOR
THE PROJECT MAY BE COMPLETED BY PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF SO
THAT FINDING AND SIX L WILL STATE QUOTE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
PRESERVATION STAFF REVIEW THE COMMISSION FINDS THAT THE
OVERALL SIZE AND INTENSITY OF THE PROJECT AS PROPOSED ARE
CRITICAL TO THE PROGRAMMATIC VIABILITY OF THE PROJECT
AND DIRECTED PLANNING STAFF TO BRING THE PROJECT BACK TO THE
COMMISSION AS AN INFORMATIONAL ITEM AFTER PLANNING
PRESERVATION STAFF'S FINAL REVIEW UNQUOTE.
ALL ASPECTS ALL OTHER ASPECTS OF THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S
DECISION WOULD REMAIN THE SAME. SO THAT'S A MOTION ON ITEM 31.
>> OKAY. >> BEFORE I ASK FOR A SECOND ON
THAT I WANT TO GET CLEAR ON WHAT IS HAPPENING BECAUSE I
BELIEVE WHAT I HEAR SUPERVISOR CHERYL SAYING IS DESCRIBING AN
AMENDMENT TO THE CONDITIONAL USE APPROVAL THAT CAME OUT OF
THE PLANNING COMMISSION AND THAT IS AN AMENDMENT TO 30
OR TO 31 DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD ROSSI WHEN THE BOARD IS
GOING TO AMEND AN APPROVAL. >> YEAH, YOU ACTUALLY HAVE TO
ADOPT THE MOTION THAT DISAPPROVES THE APPROVAL
AND THEN APPROVE IT WITH DIFFERENT CONDITIONS SO IT'S
CORRECTLY AN AMENDMENT TO ITEM 31 AS SUPERVISOR CHERYL STATED
. OKAY.
AND SO THEN YOU ALL WILL VOTE ON THE AMENDMENTS AND THEN I'M
ASSUMING HE'LL MAKE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE THAT MOTION WITH AS
AMENDED AND THEN TO DISPOSE OF THE OTHER ITEMS AS WELL.
>> SO HE HAS HIS MOTION HAS PROPOSED AN AMENDMENT TO 31 IS
THAT CORRECT IS THAT CORRECT? YES.
AND AND CAN I GET A SECOND FOR THAT AND THEN WE'LL TALK ABOUT
IT SECOND BY MELGAR THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR CHAN
SORRY, I'M TRYING TO UNDERSTAND MY APOLOGIES COLLEAGUES.
>> I'M SO LET ME UNDERSTAND THOUGH MY ASSUMPTION IS THAT
YOU ACTUALLY ARE SHOULD GO AHEAD IF IF I WERE SUPERVISOR
CHERYL THAT TRYING TO JUST MOVE THIS FORWARD BUT WITH ONLY BUT
AMENDING THE CONDITIONS FOR REMOVING THE CONDITION APPROVAL
ONE BUT SUSTAINED WITH THE FINDINGS SIX L AND THEN I WOULD
ACTUALLY MOVE THE MOTION FORWARD WITH ITEM NUMBER 31
AND THEN A MEN ITEM 30 BECAUSE YOU'RE STILL APPROVING THE
CONDITIONAL USE OR WE'RE REJECTING THE CONDITIONAL USE
ALTOGETHER HERE HERE THE BOARD BY CHANGING THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S DECISION YOU'RE DISAPPROVING IT BECAUSE THE
SUPERVISOR CHERYL REQUIRE IS DESIRES TO CHANGE ONE OF THE
CONDITIONS SO THAT'S THE CORRECT MOTION TO ADOPT
AND THEN 30 WOULD BE TABLED BECAUSE WE'RE NOT THE BOARD
WOULD NOT BE AFFIRMING AT THIS YOU YOU'RE REVISING IT
BASICALLY AND THEN THE BOARD WOULD NEED TO ADOPT THAT MOTION
BY A VOTE THRESHOLD BECAUSE YOU'RE DISAPPROVING THIS TO YOU
AND DIRECT THE CLERK TO PREPARE FINDINGS TO SUPPORT THAT
DECISION AND WE'RE DOING ALL OF THAT IN ONE VOTE IS THAT THE
MOTION THAT SUPERVISOR CHERYL MADE THAT WAS SECOND BY
SURPRISE? MOTHER YES.
OKAY. >> WE'RE CLEAR JUST JUST TO BE
CLEAR THEN ARE THE MOTION TO THE OTHER TWO MOTIONS AS WELL
VOTE ON THE AMENDMENTS APPROVE THE MOTION AS AMENDED DIRECT
THE CLERK TO ADOPT THE FINDINGS AND TABLE ITEM 30 I BELIEVE
THAT THAT IS WHAT SUPERVISOR CHERYL MOVED AND WAS SECOND BY
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. GOOD.
I'M NOT SCURRYING AROUND MAKING THINGS TOO HARD FOR CLERKS OR
ATTORNEYS. MAYBE I AM ALL RIGHT ANYWAY,
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THAT MOTION.
>> MR. PRESIDENT WILL TAKE THE MOTION FIRST ON ITEM 31 TO
AMEND ITEM THREE CHERYL MENTIONED RATES.
>> YES ON THE MOTION TO AMEND ITEM 31 AS STATED BY
SUPERVISORS CHERYL SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUPERVISOR
SAUDER CHARTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN NO CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR
AND GAUDIO AND GAUDIO EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
RANDLEMAN I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I THERE ARE TEN
EYES AND ONE NO ALL RIGHT SO WE HAVE AMENDED WE HAVE AMENDED 30
AND APPROVES WE'VE AMENDED 31 IS WHAT WE HAVE DONE.
>> ALL RIGHT I WILL GAVEL THAT I GUESS.
OKAY. AND AND THEN SUPERVISOR CHERYL
WANTS TO MOVE SO I'D LIKE YEAH I'D LIKE TO MOVE TO A TO
APPROVE 31 AS AMENDED AND I ALSO MOVE TO APPROVE ITEM 32
DIRECTING THE CLERK TO PREPARE FINDINGS SUPPORTING THIS
DECISION AND THEN TO TABLE ITEM THIRD ITEM 30 IS THERE A SECOND
FOR THAT SECONDED BY MELGAR? >> NO DISCUSSION MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THAT MOTION.
THE MOTION TO TABLE ITEM 30 APPROVE ITEM 31 AS AMENDED
AND ITEM 32 SUPERVISOR SARTOR SARTOR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN NO
CHAN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
EITHER ATTORNEYS IN ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN VOTING NO ALL
RIGHT THE MOTION PASSES ALL RIGHT AND THAT LEAVES US THREE
THREE ITEMS LEFT SUPERVISOR CHERYL ALL RIGHT.
>> I'D LIKE ON THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATE THIS I'D LIKE TO
MAKE A MOTION TO AMEND ITEM 35 DISAPPROVING THE HISTORIC
PRESERVATION COMMISSION'S DECISION AND REVISE IT TO
APPROVE THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS WITH SOME
DIFFERENT CONDITIONS SPECIFICALLY CONDITION ONE ON
PAGE 15 OF CPSC'S DECISION SHOULD BE REVISED TO REMOVE
REFERENCE TO THE ARCHITECTURAL REVIEW COMMITTEE'S FURTHER
REVIEW. THIS PROJECT WHICH IS
UNNECESSARY FOR THE CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS TO MEET ALL
THE REQUIREMENTS NECESSARY FOR APPROVAL INCLUDING UNDER
ARTICLE TEN OF THE PLANNING CODE AND FRANKLY THE SECRETARY
OF INTERIOR STANDARDS FOR REHABILITATION.
SO INSTEAD THAT CONDITIONS OF STATE AND I QUOTE FINAL
ARCHITECTURAL DETAILS PRIOR TO SUBMITTAL OF ANY BUILDING
PERMIT APPLICATION DEPARTMENT PRESERVATION STAFF SHALL REVIEW
AND APPROVE FINAL PROJECT ARCHITECTURAL DETAILS OF
FENESTRATION SIZES ORIENTATION MATERIALS AND EXTERIOR FINISHES
PROVIDED THAT NO REDUCTION IN PROJECT SQUARE FOOTAGE SHALL
RESULT FROM SUCH REVIEW AND QUOTE ALL OTHER ASPECTS OF
THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION'S DECISION REMAIN
THE SAME. ALL RIGHT.
IS THERE A SECOND FOR THAT SECOND BY MELGAR AND THERE'S NO
DISCUSSION MADAM CLERK CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THAT MOTION ON
ITEM 35 AS AMENDED BY SUPERVISOR CHERYL SECONDED BY
SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUPERVISORS SARTOR SARTOR I SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHIN
NO CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EYES SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO IN GAUDIO EYES SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I'M SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR CHAN VOTING NO
OKAY THE MOTION PASSES AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL I THINK
WE GOT ONE MORE. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO I'D LIKE TO MOVE TO APPROVE ITEM 35 AS AMENDED AND MOVE TO
APPROVE ITEM 36 DIRECTING THE CLERK TO PREPARE FINDINGS
SUPPORTING THIS DECISION AND TO TABLE ITEM 34 AND COLLEAGUES
THANK YOU FOR HEARING THIS DISTRICT TWO ITEM TODAY IS
THEIR SECOND SECONDED BY MELGAR.
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THAT MOTION ON THE
MOTION TO A TABLE ITEM 34 APPROVE ITEM 35 AS AMENDED
AND APPROVE ITEM 36 SUPERVISOR SARTOR SARTOR EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR
CHAN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR OR DORSEY
DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO AND ENGARDIO EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT GENTLEMEN I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR I MELGAR I THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR
CHAN VOTING NO AND THE MOTION PASSES AND WITH THAT GRATITUDE
TO COLLEAGUES FOR YOUR PATIENCE WITH ME WE WILL GO ON WE WILL
GO BACK TO THE BEGINNING OF OUR AGENDA.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL OUR CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS
WENT THROUGH FIVE ITEMS ONE THROUGH FIVE ARE ON CONSENT.
THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OF
JACKSON ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY.
>> I DON'T SEE ANYBODY MOVING TO SEVER.
THAT'S GREAT MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEMS ONE THROUGH FIVE SUPERVISORS SADR SADR EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN I CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHENNAI
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
RANDLEMAN I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR EITHER ARE
ELEVENSES WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON
FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS ITEM
NUMBER SIX ITEM SIX THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE THE
CLERK OF THE BOARD TO SELL LICENSES TO THIRD PARTIES TO
USE THE LEGISLATIVE MANAGEMENT SYSTEM SOFTWARE AND TO AMEND
THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO ESTABLISH A FUND TO RECEIVE
REVENUE FOR LICENSING TO THIRD PARTIES AND FROM
INTERDEPARTMENTAL FUND TRANSFERS.
>> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
PLEASE CALL ITEM SEVEN. >> ITEM SEVEN THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO FIX COMPENSATION FOR PERSONS EMPLOYED BY THE
CITY WHOSE COMPENSATION IS SUBJECT TO CHARTER PROVISION
SECTION 8.409 AND JOB CODES NOT REPRESENTED BY AN EMPLOYEE
ORGANIZATION AND TO FIX THE WORKING SCHEDULES AND OTHER
TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF EMPLOYMENT AND METHODS OF
PAYMENT EFFECTIVE JULY FIRST 2025 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM EIGHT ITEM EIGHT THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO ADOPT AND IMPLEMENT THE SECOND
AMENDMENT TO THE 2024 THROUGH 2027 MEMORANDUM OF
UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND THE SERVICE
EMPLOYEES INTERNATIONAL UNION LOCAL 1021 STAFF AND PER DIEM
NURSES TO ADDRESS THE ORDER OF SELECTION FOR FILLING VACANT
NURSING POSITIONS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NINE ITEM NINE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO ELIMINATE RETAIL USE
SIZE LIMITS ON HEALTH SERVICE USES AND REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH
CLINICS IN THE IMU. OH THE MIXED USE OFFICE
DISTRICT EAST OF SEVENTH STREET TO ELIMINATE THE RETAIL RATIO
LIMITS IN THE MUO DISTRICT EAST OF SEVENTH STREET AND TO AFFIRM
THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM TEN. ITEM TEN THIS IS AN ORDINANCE
TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO INCREASE THE STIPENDS
THE CITY PROVIDES TO THE ASSESSMENT APPEALS BOARDS DUE
TO THE UNPRECEDENTED DEMAND IN ASSESSMENT APPEALS HEARINGS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEMS AND 11 THROUGH 13 TOGETHER ITEMS 11 THROUGH 13
COMPRISE THE PROPOSED INTERIM BUDGETS FOR THE BUDGET
AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE AND THE INTERIM SALARY
ORDINANCE AND THE INTERIM BUDGET RESOLUTION FOR THE
OFFICE OF COMMUNITY INVESTMENT AND INFRASTRUCTURE FOR THE CITY
AND COUNTY. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST
READING AND THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 14.
>> ITEM 13 MR. PRESIDENT. YOU SEE A 14 I BELIEVE 14.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
ITEM 14 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE SETTLEMENT OF THE
LAWSUIT FILED BY THE ORIGINATED APARTMENTS INC AGAINST THE CITY
AND COUNTY CONCERNING THE REAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 524 HOWARD
STREET FOR A STIPULATED ASSESSED VALUE OF THE SUBJECT
PROPERTY FOR PROPERTY TAX PURPOSES OF APPROXIMATELY 65
MILLION AS OF JANUARY 1ST 2021 FOR THE FISCAL YEAR 2021
THROUGH 2022 OR IF THE ASSESSMENT APPEALS BOARD DOES
NOT ACCEPT THAT STIPULATED ASSESSED VALUE AGREEMENT THAT
THE ASSESSMENT APPEALS BOARD HOLDING NEW ASSESSMENT APPEAL
HEARING TO DETERMINE THE ASSESSED VALUE OF THE SUBJECT
PROPERTY AS OF JANUARY 1ST 2021 FOR THE FISCAL YEAR 2021
THROUGH 2022 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 15 ITEM 15 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
RETROACTIVE TIVELY AUTHORIZE THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
DEPARTMENT TO ENTER INTO A MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDING
AGREEMENT WITH THE UNITED STATES CAPITOL POLICE TO
PROVIDE SUPPLEMENTAL LAW ENFORCEMENT SERVICES JANUARY
FIRST, 2025 THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2025 SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 16 ITEM 16 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE A PERMIT BETWEEN THE RECREATION AND PARK
DEPARTMENT AND PHIL PARTNERS LLC FOR THE GOLDEN CITY
FOOTBALL CLUB TO USE KEZAR STADIUM FOR THEIR HOME GAMES
PLUS USE OF OTHER FIELDS FOR PRACTICES FOR 15 YEARS WITH
THREE FIVE YEAR EXTENSION OPTIONS FOR A PERMIT FEE EQUAL
TO APPROXIMATELY 1500 PER GAME PLUS 750 PER HOUR REIMBURSEMENT
OF OUR PD EXPENSES AS A SHARE OF REVENUES AND A SPECIFIED
NUMBER OF TICKETS AND THE COMPLETION OF CERTAIN STADIUM
IMPROVEMENTS TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM 17 ITEM 17 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE PLANNING CODE TO ALLOW TO PROJECTING SIGNS FOR ALL CORNER
BUSINESSES IN ALL NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL AND RESIDENTIAL
COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS CITYWIDE AND TO ABOLISH THE 20 301
CHESTNUT STREET SPECIAL SIGN DISTRICT.
TO AMEND THE ZONING MAP TO REFLECT THAT DISTRICT'S
ABOLITION TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 18.
>> ITEM 18 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE LIST OF PROJECTS
TO BE FUNDED BY FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 26 ROAD
MAINTENANCE AND REHABILITATION ACCOUNT FUNDS FOR THE LOCAL
STREETS AND ROAD PROGRAM AS ESTABLISHED BY CALIFORNIA
SENATE BILL ONE THE ROAD REPAIR AND ACCOUNTABILITY ACT OF 22
2017. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 19.
>> ITEM 19 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROVE THE AMENDED AIRPORT
SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY POLICY GOVERNING THE USE OF SECURITY
CAMERAS AND TO MAKE THE REQUIRED FINDINGS IN SUPPORT OF
SAID APPROVALS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 20 .
>> ITEM 20 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE TO CREATE THE VALENCIA STREET ENTERTAINMENT ZONE THE
PIER 39 ENTERTAINMENT ZONE THE FOLSOM STREET ENTERTAINMENT
ZONE. THE YOSEMITE AVENUE
ENTERTAINMENT ZONE. THE HAYES VALLEY ENTERTAINMENT
ZONE AND THE YERBA BUENA LANE DOWNTOWN ACTIVATION LOCATION.
AND TO CONFIRM THE SEQUENT DETERMINATION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM 21. >> ITEM 20 ONE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO REVISE
ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO HOMICIDE REWARD
FUND TO INCLUDE ALLOWING THE CHIEF OF POLICE IN THE CHIEF'S
DISCRETION TO APPROVE PAYMENT OF A REWARD WHEN INFORMATION
LEADS TO THE FILING OF CRIMINAL CHARGES TO PROHIBIT DENIAL OF A
REWARD BASED ON ANONYMITY, CRIMINAL HISTORY AND TO REQUIRE
THAT A PERSON SEEKING A REWARD THAT PROVIDES INFORMATION THAT
THEY PROVIDED VOLUNTARILY AND NOT A PART OF A PLEA
BARGAIN AND TO ENSURE THAT A REWARD IS NOT PAID TO A PERSON
FOR THE PROVISION OF FALSE INFORMATION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
22. >> ITEM 22 ORDINANCE TO APPROVE
AMENDMENTS TO THE RULES AND REGULATIONS FOR THE
NEIGHBORHOOD BEAUTIFICATION AND GRAFFITI CLEANUP FUND.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 23
ITEM 20 THREE THIS IS A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MAYOR'S
NOMINATION OF GAIL STERN STRING A FOR APPOINTMENT TO THE
HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMISSION TERM ENDING DECEMBER
31ST, 2028. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 24.
>> ITEM 24 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPOINT LUANA MCALPINE TO THE
IN-HOME SUPPORTIVE SERVICES PUBLIC AUTHORITY TERM ENDING
MARCH 1ST, 2028. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> AND MADAM CLERK, I THINK THAT WE HAVE A COMMITTEE REPORT
THAT TAKES US TO ITEM. I'M JUST SCROLLING TO THAT.
YES, I DON'T 37 YES. THIS ITEM WAS CONSIDERED BY THE
LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING
ON MONDAY JUNE 16TH AND WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED BEARING
THE SAME TITLE ITEM 37 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING
CODE TO ALLOW CERTAIN TOURIST HOTELS AND MOTELS TO BE USED
FOR INTERIM HOUSING WITHOUT THEREBY ABANDONING OR
DISCONTINUING THE HOTEL USE CLASS UNDER THAT CODE AND TO
AUTHORIZE THE REESTABLISHMENT OF HOTEL USE FOR CERTAIN
SHELTER IN PLACE HOTELS TO AMEND THE BUILDING CODE TO
ALLOW INTERIM HOUSING WITHOUT THEREBY CHANGING THE UNDERLYING
OCCUPANCY CLASSIFICATION OF THE PROPERTY AND TO ALLOW
REESTABLISHMENT OF HOTEL USE FOR SHELTER IN PLACE HOTELS TO
AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO A ROLL CALL.
>> YES. THE FIRST MEMBER TO INTRODUCE
NEW BUSINESS IS SUPERVISOR SAUDER.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM EXCITED
TO INTRODUCE LEGISLATION THAT WILL MAKE IT EASIER FOR NEW
SMALL BUSINESSES TO OPEN AND TO GROW IN DISTRICT THREE.
THIS LEGISLATION IS A DIRECT ANSWER TO THE URGENT CALLS OF
RESIDENTS AND SMALL BUSINESSES FOR MORE FLEXIBILITY, MORE
SUPPORT AND A PLANNING CODE THAT MEETS THE MODERN DAY
REALITIES OF RETAIL SERVICES AND RESTAURANTS.
FOR TOO LONG SAN FRANCISCO HAS MADE IT TOO HARD TO OPEN
AND RUN A SMALL BUSINESS AND DISTRICT THREE HAS BEEN THE
MOST EGREGIOUS LAYING RULE AFTER ALL AND PUTTING ROADBLOCK
AFTER ROADBLOCK IN THE WAY THIS RESULTS IN ONLY THE
WELL-CONNECTED KNOWING HOW TO NAVIGATE A COMPLEX SYSTEM
AND OTHERS BEING LEFT BEHIND WITH ONLY EMPTY STOREFRONTS TO
SHOW FOR IT. SO WHILE THE RECENT PERMIT S.F.
PACKAGE IS AN APPROACH TO A CITYWIDE PERMIT AND CONCERN,
OUR LEGISLATION IS MORE FOCUSED ON NEIGHBORHOOD BY NEIGHBORHOOD
CHANGES SPECIFIC TO DISTRICT THREE OUR CHANGES ARE SURGICAL
THEY DO NOT TOUCH PROGRAMS THAT ARE WORKING AND THEY MAKE
THOUGHTFUL CHANGES THAT RESPECT THE UNIQUE CHARACTER OF EACH OF
OUR DISTRICT THREE NEIGHBORHOODS OUR CHANGES ARE
NEEDED. THEY RESPOND TO HIGH RATES OF
EMPTY STOREFRONTS ON CORRIDORS LIKE PARK STREET AND CORRECT
PLANNING QUIRKS AND BARRIERS THAT HAVE PREVENTED BUSINESSES
FROM OPENING IN OUR DISTRICT AND OUR CHANGES ARE INFORMED.
THIS PACKAGE WAS PUT TOGETHER IN PARTNERSHIP WITH
NEIGHBORHOOD ORGANIZATIONS, MERCHANTS AND INFORMED BY MY
OWN DECADE AS A DISTRICT THREE RESIDENT AND SMALL BUSINESS
ADVOCATE AND OWNER. IN ONE EXAMPLE OF THE IMPACT OF
THIS LEGISLATION WILL EXPAND THE SUCCESSFUL COMMUNITY
BENEFIT PRIORITY PROCESSING PROGRAM TO ALL OF DISTRICT
THREE BECAUSE WHY WOULD WE INTENTIONALLY CHOOSE TO MAKE
THE PERMIT PROCESS SLOWER AS TODAY'S CODE DOES NEXT WILL
FINALLY ALLOW FLEXIBLE RETAIL ACROSS DISTRICT THREE JUST AS
THE REST OF THE CITY ALLOWS THIS PLANNING CODE CATEGORY
ALLOWS FOR A MIX OF BUSINESSES BUSINESS TYPES IN THE SAME
SPACE. IF YOU WANT TO OPEN A COFFEE
SHOP AND BOOKSTORE UNDER ONE ROOF WE SHOULD ALLOW YOU TO
WELL REMOVE AN OUTDATED PROHIBITION ON ARTS ACTIVITIES
WHICH RESULT IN NOT BEING ALLOWED TO OPEN A DANCE SCHOOL,
A CERAMICS STUDIO OR A PHOTOGRAPHY STUDIO ON HILL
AND WE'LL LEGALIZE WALK UP FACILITIES MEANING THAT JUST AS
YOU CAN GET A SLICE OF PIZZA THROUGH A WINDOW AT GOLDEN BOY
ON GREEN STREET, YOU WILL NOW BE ABLE TO DO THE SAME
THROUGHOUT THE ENTIRE NEIGHBORHOOD.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN THE BIRTHPLACE OF COMPANIES KNOWN
AROUND THE WORLD GAP BANK OF AMERICA TEHRANI SIRUPS
GHIRARDELLI AND THOSE LOVED LOCALLY ANCHOR STEAM FILLS IT'S
IT TO NAME JUST A FEW. BUT OVER THE PAST DECADE IT
SEEMS THAT WE'VE TAKEN OUR CREATIVES, OUR ENTREPRENEURS,
CHEFS AND ARTISTS FOR GRANTED. TODAY'S LEGISLATION IS A STEP
TOWARDS CHANGING THAT IN DISTRICT THREE.
A SPECIAL THANKS TO MICHELLE ANDREWS.
MICHELLE HAPPY BIRTHDAY AND TO TO BELLE FROM MY OFFICE
AND BRIAN CROSSMAN FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR
THEIR HEAVY LIFTING ON GETTING THIS LEGISLATION READY.
I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH MY COLLEAGUES AND WITH OUR
DIVERSE SET OF COMMUNITIES IN DISTRICT THREE TO SHAPE
AND PASS LEGISLATION TO SUPPORT SMALL BUSINESSES AND HELP OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS CONTINUE TO THRIVE.
>> AND THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SARTOR SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
WALTON. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION WITH
CO-SPONSORSHIP FROM SUPERVISORS CHEN FIELDER AND ENGARDIO
MAYOR GAR CHEN. PRESIDENT MALAMAN MAHMOOD
AND CHERYL ON CELEBRATING JUNETEENTH IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AS IT IS AN OFFICIAL HOLIDAY
AND URGING ALL SAN FRANCISCANS TO JOIN IN HONORING THIS
IMPORTANT DAY. JUNETEENTH IS A DAY OF
REFLECTION RESILIENCE AND EMPOWERMENT.
DEEPLY ROOTED IN THE HISTORY, HERITAGE AND ONGOING STRUGGLE
FOR JUSTICE WITHIN BLACK COMMUNITIES ACROSS THIS
COUNTRY. JUNETEENTH, ALSO KNOWN AS
EMANCIPATION DAY JUBILEE DAY, FREEDOM DAY AND BLACK
INDEPENDENCE DAY COMMEMORATES JUNE 19TH, 1865, THE DAY WHEN
UNION SOLDIERS ARRIVED IN GALVESTON, TEXAS
AND ANNOUNCED THE END OF THE CIVIL WAR AND ABOLITION OF
SLAVERY. THIS ANNOUNCEMENT CAME MORE
THAN TWO YEARS AFTER THE EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION HAD
BEEN ISSUED BY PRESIDENT ABRAHAM LINCOLN ON JANUARY
FIRST, 1863. THE ARRIVAL OF UNION TROOPS
MARKED THE LONG OVERDUE ENFORCEMENT OF THEIR PROMISE OF
FREEDOM. FOR THE LAST ENSLAVED BLACK
AMERICANS SINCE 1865, JUNETEENTH HAS BEEN CELEBRATED
ANNUALLY AS A TIME FOR COMMUNITIES TO COME TOGETHER TO
REFLECT, REJOICE AND RECOMMIT THE WORK OF RACIAL JUSTICE.
IT IS A DAY THAT HONORS STRENGTH AND RESILIENCE OF
BLACK AMERICANS AND RECOGNIZES THE TREMENDOUS CONTRIBUTIONS OF
BLACK COMMUNITIES TO OUR NATION'S HISTORY.
AND FUTURE IN SAN FRANCISCO JUNETEENTH CELEBRATES WINS HAVE
BEEN A PART OF OUR CITY'S CULTURAL FABRIC FOR DECADES
SINCE THE 1950S. OUR CITY HAS PROBABLY HOSTED
JUNETEENTH FESTIVALS AND PARADES, PARTICULARLY ALONG
FILLMORE STREET, A HISTORIC HUB OF BLACK CULTURE AND COMMUNITY
IN SAN FRANCISCO. TODAY'S JUNETEENTH CELEBRATION
SPANNED MANY NEIGHBORHOODS REFLECTING OUR CITY'S DIVERSE
AND SHARED COMMITMENT TO JUSTICE.
ON JUNE 17TH, 2021, FORMER PRESIDENT JOE BIDEN SIGNED THE
JUNETEENTH NATIONAL INDEPENDENCE DAY ACT INTO LAW
MAKING JUNETEENTH AN OFFICIAL FEDERAL HOLIDAY
AND ACKNOWLEDGING ITS PROFOUND SIGNIFICANCE IN AMERICAN
HISTORY. HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WE HAVE A
RESPONSIBILITY NOT ONLY TO RECOGNIZE THIS DAY BUT TO
CONTINUE THE HARD WORK OF ADDRESSING SYSTEMIC RACISM
UPLIFTING BLACK COMMUNITIES AND BUILDING A CITY WHERE
FREEDOM, JUSTICE AND OPPORTUNITY CAN BE A
REALITY FOR EVERYONE. THE SECOND ITEM I'M INTRODUCING
IS A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF THE 2025 ROAD TO REPAIR
PRIORITY BILL PACKAGE INTRODUCED BY MEMBERS OF THE
CALIFORNIA LEGISLATIVE BLACK CAUCUS IN THE STATE
LEGISLATURE. THIS PACKAGE INCLUDES 16 STATE
BILLS THAT ARE PART OF A MULTIYEAR EFFORT TO REPAIR THE
GENERATIONAL HARMS OF SLAVERY AND SYSTEMIC RACISM
IN CALIFORNIA. THESE BILLS ARE MODELED AFTER
RECOMMENDATIONS FROM THE CALIFORNIA REPARATIONS TASK
FORCE AND INCLUDE AND I'M NOT GOING TO READ ALL THE BILLS FOR
THE SAKE OF TIME BUT IT INCLUDES BILLS LIKE ASSEMBLY
BILL SIX WOULD PROHIBIT SLAVERY IN ALL FORMS.
HB SEVEN WOULD AUTHORIZE PRIORITY EMISSIONS FOR
DESCENDANTS OF AMERICAN CHATTEL SLAVERY TO HIGHER EDUCATION
INSTITUTIONS. HB 742 SEEKS TO DESIGNATE
DESCENDANTS OF AMERICAN CHATTEL SLAVERY FOR PRIORITY WHEN
ISSUING PROFESSIONAL LICENSES. SB 510 SEEKS TO REQUIRE
COMPLETE AND ACCURATE K-12 CURRICULUM REGARDING RACIAL
DISPARITIES INCLUDING IMPACTS OF SEGREGATION, SLAVERY
AND SYSTEMIC DISCRIMINATION. ALL OF THESE BILLS IN THIS
PACKAGE ADDRESS THE DISPARITIES AND OF COURSE THE NEGATIVE
IMPACTS ON THE BLACK COMMUNITY IN THIS STATE.
IN SAN FRANCISCO WE HAVE LONG LED EFFORTS TO ADDRESS
HISTORICAL INJUSTICES. WE RECENTLY UNANIMOUSLY PASSED
AN OFFICIAL APOLOGY TO AFRICAN-AMERICANS AND THEIR
DESCENDANTS AND WE CONTINUE WORKING ON IMPLEMENTING THE
RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO REPARATIONS PLAN.
REPARATIONS ARE A CRUCIAL STEP TOWARD REPAIRING ECONOMIC,
SOCIAL AND PSYCHOLOGICAL DAMAGE CAUSED BY CENTURIES OF SLAVERY,
SEGREGATION AND DISCRIMINATION .
I HOPE THAT ALL OF MY COLLEAGUES WILL JOIN ME
AND UNANIMOUSLY COSPONSORING THIS RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF
CALIFORNIA'S ROAD TO REPAIR BILLS ESPECIALLY IN OUR CURRENT
CLIMATE WHERE OUR FREEDOMS AND CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS ARE
AT RISK OF BEING TAKEN AWAY AND OUR COMMUNITIES ARE UNDER
THREATS DAILY. I WANT TO THANK EARLY
CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD AND SUPERVISOR CHAN IN THE.
>> I SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON SUPERVISOR
SIR CHAN. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> HI. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUE TODAY I WANT TO INTRODUCE A RESOLUTION URGING
OUR STATE LEGISLATORS SENATOR WINNER AND ASSEMBLY MEMBER
HANEY AND STEPHANIE TO CHAMPION LEGISLATION THAT WOULD ALLOW
COUNTIES TO IMPLEMENT LOCAL WEALTH AND PROGRESSIVE INCOME
TAX IF THEY CHOOSE TO. >> WE ARE FACING A MASSIVE
LOCAL DEFICIT THAT WILL BE MADE WORSE BY STATE AND FEDERAL
CUTS. >> THIS WILL IMPACT OUR MOST
VULNERABLE AND WILL LEAD TO REDUCED ACCESS TO DIRECT
AND ESSENTIAL SERVICES THAT KEEPS OUR CITY OUR PEOPLE SAFE.
HOUSE IT FAT AND CARE. >> DISTRICT 11 IT'S HOME TO ONE
OF THE LARGEST POPULATION OF WALKING IMMIGRANTS AND LABOR
HOUSEHOLD IN A CITY. >> THIS FAMILIES WORK HARD
AND PAY THEIR FAIR SHARE TO THE CITY.
THEY DESERVE TO LIVE IN A CITY THAT IS SAFE, CLEAN
AND AFFORDABLE. >> BUT WHAT WE ARE SEEING RIGHT
NOW IS THAT LOW AND MIDDLE INCOME SAN FRANCISCAN ARE BEING
DISPROPORTIONATELY IMPACTED BY THE BUDGET DECISIONS,
ESPECIALLY AT THE FEDERAL LEVEL AND BILLIONAIRES AREN'T PAYING
THEIR FAIR SHARE. IN FACT THE WEALTHIEST THE
WELFARE AMERICANS STAND TO GAIN FROM EVEN BIGGER TAX BREAK.
UNDER THE CURRENT PROPOSAL BEING NEGOTIATED BY THE
CONGRESS, I BELIEVE THAT THE CITY SHOULD HAVE AND SHOULD
ABLE TO EXPLORE WHETHER OR NOT ADDITIONAL TAX SHOULD BE LEVIED
ON THE WEALTHIEST MEMBER OF OUR COMMUNITIES GIVEN WHAT IS GIVEN
WHAT WE ARE FACING NATIONWIDE WITH THIS EXTREMELY HOSTILE
BUDGET CONDITIONS. IT'S MORE IMPORTANT NOW MORE
THAN EVER IMPORTANT NOW THAT WE NEED EVERY TOOL AT OUR DISPOSAL
TO ENSURE THAT OUR CITY IS PROVIDING HIGH QUALITY
COMPREHEND AND SAFE AND COMPASSIONATE CARE IN THE
AREAS THAT WE HAVE AT FOR THE DECADES.
>> AND I APPRECIATE THE TWO EARLY CO-SPONSORS.
BY SUPERVISOR CHAN SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR MELGAR
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUES I AM TODAY SUBMITTING A LETTER OF INQUIRY
THAT SEEKS FROM OUR DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT
AND DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING A
COMPREHENSIVE ANALYSIS OF 911 CALLS FOR SERVICE AT ALL SITE
BASED PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING ADDRESSES IN SAN
FRANCISCO. I AM ASKING THAT THIS ANALYSIS
EVALUATE DATA FROM JANUARY 1ST, 2020 TO THE PRESENT TO GET A
LONGITUDINAL PERSPECTIVE ON THE PUBLIC SAFETY AND MEDICAL
EMERGENCY DEMANDS OF PERMANENT SUPPORTIVE HOUSING OR PCH
AND HOW THEY MAY BE CHANGING OVER TIME.
I ALSO ASK THAT EACH PCH SITE THAT'S LISTED INCLUDE
INFORMATION IDENTIFYING ITS NONPROFIT CONTRACTOR
AND PROPERTY MANAGER. NOW THE TOPIC OF PUBLIC SAFETY
ISSUES IN AND AROUND PCH FACILITIES ISN'T NEW.
IT IS A SUBJECT WE TOOK UP AT A HEARING LAST YEAR IN FACT.
AND WHILE WE HAVE SEEN IMPROVEMENTS AT SOME LOCATIONS
IN DISTRICT SIX, WE HAVE ALSO SEEN NEW PROBLEMS EMERGE AT
SOME NEW PCH LOCATIONS. THIS NEED FOR BETTER DATA COMES
IN THE CONTEXT OF A LETTER I SENT THIS MORNING TO THE
TENDERLOIN NEIGHBORHOOD DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION WHICH
DISAPPOINTINGLY OPTED TO OPPOSE ASSEMBLY BILL 255 LEGISLATION
BY ASSEMBLY MEMBER MATT HANEY TO FUND DRUG FREE SUPPORTIVE
RECOVERY HOUSING WHICH THIS BOARD UNANIMOUSLY ENDORSED
ENDORSED TWICE AND WHICH ENJOYS SIMILARLY STRONG SUPPORT FROM
MAYOR LURIE AND OUR ENTIRE LEGISLATIVE DELEGATION
IN SACRAMENTO. RIGHT NOW WE THANKFULLY HAVE
COMPREHENDS LIVE DATA ON DRUG OVERDOSE DEATHS AND PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING AND THOSE NUMBERS ARE INCREASINGLY
ALARMING. IN A YEAR'S TIME THE PROPORTION
OF DRUG O.D. FATALITIES IN PCH HAS GROWN FROM ABOUT 21% LAST
YEAR, ACCOUNTING FOR ABOUT ONE IN EVERY FIVE DRUG DEATHS
CITYWIDE TO 30% SO FAR THIS YEAR REPRESENTING REPRESENTING
NEARLY 1 IN 3 DRUG OVERDOSE DEATHS CITYWIDE.
THIS IS A DISTURBING TREND THAT I BELIEVE DRUG FREE
AND RECOVERY ORIENTED PCH OPTIONS WOULD HELP REVERSE.
AS IT HAPPENS, D.C. RANKS THIRD WORST AMONG PCH PROVIDERS THIS
YEAR WITH TEN DRUG O.D. FATALITIES IN JUST FOUR MONTHS.
>> WE ALSO KNOW THAT TI AND DC MANAGE PROPERTIES ACCOUNT FOR
ABOUT FIVE OF THE TOP 100 MOST RESPONDED TO ADDRESSES FOR
POLICE CALLS FOR SERVICE THIS YEAR.
THIS THESE FIVE FACILITIES GENERATED ACTUALLY LAST YEAR
MORE THAN 600 911 CALLS JUST FOR POLICE EMERGENCIES ALONE
NOT COUNTING 911 CALLS FOR MEDICAL EMERGENCIES OR FIRE.
THAT MEANS THAT EACH OF THESE BUILDINGS IS AVERAGING AROUND
911911 CALL PER DAY FOR JUST POLICE EMERGENCIES.
>> NOW I BELIEVE ANYONE NOBODY SHOULD BLAME TEN DC FOR THE
LOSS OF LIFE OR PREDICTABLE PUBLIC SAFETY CHALLENGES WE SEE
AT THESE DRUG TOLERANCE SITES. STILL TO MY MIND THESE PROBLEMS
MAKE ALL THE MORE TROUBLING THIS ORGANIZATION'S DECISION TO
OPPOSE NEEDED PROGRESS AND TO DEFEND THE ADEQUACY OF A STATUS
QUO THAT NO ONE SHOULD FIND ACCEPTABLE.
WE NEED BETTER DATA TO ASSESS PUBLIC NUISANCES AND PUBLIC
SAFETY CHALLENGES TO MORE FULLY INFORM OUR POLICY DECISIONS
AND TO MATCH THE HIGH QUALITY DATA WE NOW HAVE ON DRUG
OVERDOSE DOSE FATALITIES. SO I THANK THE CLERK FOR
FACILITATING THIS REQUEST AND I LOOK FORWARD TO SEEING THE
ANALYSIS AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR AND GAUDIO SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU SO
MUCH MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF CALIFORNIA SENATE
BILL 48 WHICH PROHIBITS SCHOOLS TO THE EXTENT POSSIBLE FROM
GRANTING ACCESS TO IMMIGRATION AUTHORITIES BECAUSE EVERY
STUDENT REGARDLESS OF IMMIGRATION STATUS DESERVES TO
FEEL SAFE IN OUR SCHOOLS. >> THERE HAVE BEEN DEEPLY
ALARMING INCIDENTS OF ICE ENFORCEMENT ACROSS OUR STATE
THAT HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH PROTECTING PUBLIC SAFETY
INCLUDING ICE AGENTS ATTEMPTING TO ENTER TO ELEMENTARY SCHOOLS
IN LOS ANGELES COUNTY. >> HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WE
HAVE ALREADY SEEN FIRSTHAND THE IMPACT THAT ICE AGENTS CAN HAVE
ON FAMILIES WITH THE DECEPTIVE DETENTIONS AT ICE CHECK INS.
>> ON JUNE 4TH OF AT LEAST 15 PEOPLE INCLUDING SEVERAL
CHILDREN ONE OF WHOM WAS ONLY THREE YEARS OLD.
>> ADDITIONALLY, I'VE HEARD COUNTLESS STORIES OF FAMILIES
BEING AFRAID TO SEND THEIR KIDS TO SCHOOL WORRIED THAT ICE WILL
SHOW UP AND TAKE THEM AWAY. THIS IS AN ENVIRONMENT THAT IS
NOT SAFE FOR STUDENTS THAT MAKES OUR CITIES MUCH LESS SAFE
AND IS AN INFRINGEMENT ON DUE PROCESS AND THE RULE OF LAW.
>> ADDITIONALLY EARLIER THIS YEAR THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION
RESCINDED THE LONGSTANDING POLICY TO PROTECT SENSITIVE
LOCATIONS FROM ICE ENFORCEMENT INCLUDING SCHOOLS, CHURCHES
AND HOSPITALS. >> TRUMP'S ONLY INTENT
IN DEPLOYING ICE TO SCHOOL SITES IS TO INSTILL FEAR IN OUR
COMMUNITIES. >> NO CHILD NOR FAMILIES SHOULD
EVER FEAR GOING TO SCHOOL. >> ALL CHILDREN HAVE A
FUNDAMENTAL RIGHT TO PUBLIC EDUCATION.
>> SCHOOL SITES ARE SACRED INSTITUTIONS FOR LEARNING
AND THE FOSTERING OF A STUDENT'S WELL-BEING.
>> AS IF USD HAS ALREADY STRENGTHENED THEIR POLICIES
AND PROTOCOLS AS OF THIS YEAR, HOWEVER, THIS BILL SEEKS TO
CODIFY THESE SCHOOL SITE PROTECTIONS ACROSS CALIFORNIA.
>> THIS RESOLUTION COMES ON THE HEELS OF THE MOTION PASSED AT
THE YOUTH COMMISSION YESTERDAY URGING THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
TO SUPPORT THIS BILL. >> I WANT TO THANK THE YOUTH
COMMISSION AND ESPECIALLY TO THE DISTRICT NINE COMMISSIONERS
SKYLER DENG, WHO AUTHORED THIS MOTION.
>> THIS IS ABOUT REINFORCING OUR STATUS AS A SANCTUARY CITY
HONORING THE TRUST OUR FAMILIES PLACE IN OUR SCHOOLS
AND PROTECTING OUR CHILDREN AND FAMILIES IN THE FACE OF
INCREASED ICE ACTIVITY IN OUR COMMUNITIES.
>> I HOPE YOU ALL WILL STAND WITH OUR STUDENTS
AND COMMUNITIES TO TELL ICE TO KEEP OUT OF OUR SCHOOLS.
>> THANK YOU. THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER. SUPERVISOR MAHMUD SUBMIT.
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> I HAVE AN ORDINANCE AND A RESOLUTION.
THE ORDINANCE RELATES TO CHAPTER 16 ARTICLE FIVE OF THE
ADMINISTRATE OF CODE WHICH GIVES EMPLOYEES THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO THE OPTION TO DONATE A PORTION OF
OUR PAYCHECKS TO SPECIFIED ORGANIZATIONS.
THESE INCLUDE CREDIT UNIONS, EMPLOYEE ASSOCIATIONS AND LOCAL
CHARITABLE FUNDS THAT SERVE SAN FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTERS, POLICE
OFFICERS AND CITY WORKERS GENERALLY.
THROUGH THIS PROGRAM MEMBERS CAN CHOOSE TO CONTRIBUTE MONEY,
PAY DUES OR BUY SHARES TO SUPPORT FINANCIAL SERVICES
BENEFITS OR COMMUNITY PROGRAMS. TODAY I'M INTRODUCING AN
ORDINANCE TO EXPAND THAT LIST BY ADDING THE SAN FRANCISCO
FIREFIGHTER AND EMS BEHAVIORAL HEALTH HEALTH FOUNDATION.
THIS FOUNDATION PARTNERS WITH SAN FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTERS
LOCAL 798 AND OTHER BAY OR BAY AREA ORGANIZATIONS TO PROVIDE
FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE TO ACTIVE AND RETIRED MEMBERS
EXPERIENCING A BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CRISIS, ACCORDING TO
FORMER SAN FRANCISCO FIRE CHIEF SANDY TONG WHO RAISED THE ISSUE
WITH ME EARLIER THIS YEAR. >> MORE AND MORE FIRE
DEPARTMENT MEMBERS ARE FACING BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CHALLENGES
AND MORE ARE SEEKING TREATMENT AND SUPPORT.
THE FOUNDATION WAS CREATED TO HELP MEET THE FINANCIAL NEEDS
OF THESE MEMBERS IN MOMENTS OF CRISIS.
ITS GRANTS HELP BRIDGE THE GAP BETWEEN THE IMMEDIATE EMERGENCY
AND THE LONG TERM SUPPORT OFFERED BY CITY RESOURCES LIKE
THE SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH SERVICE SYSTEMS EMPLOYEE
ASSISTANCE PROGRAM, EMPLOYEE HEALTH BENEFITS AND S.F.
BEHAVIORAL HEALTH UNIT. THESE GRANTS CREATED BY SFD
MEMBERS FOR FIRST RESPONDERS CAN COVER COSTS LIKE TRAVEL,
FUEL, FOOD, LODGING, TIME OFF WORK, CHILD CARE, ELDER CARE,
PET CARE, CLOTHING AND SHORT TERM COUNSELING SUPPORT AMONG
OTHER EMERGENCY NEEDS. >> THIS ADDITION IS A SIMPLE
WAY TO SUPPORT THE HEALTH OF PEOPLE WHO PUT THEIR LIVES ON
THE LINE FOR SAN FRANCISCO EVERY DAY.
AGAIN, I WANT TO THANK FORMER CHIEF TONG FOR HER CONTINUED
ADVOCACY ON BEHALF OF SAN FRANCISCO'S FIREFIGHTERS AS
WELL AS MELANIE MATHESON IN MY OFFICE AND BRAD RUSSI IN THE
CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR THEIR WORK ON THE LEGISLATION.
I'M GOING TO SPEAK MORE ABOUT THIS NEXT WEEK BUT I ALSO AM
INTRODUCING TODAY A RESOLUTION CONDEMNING ANTI-SEMITIC ISM
AND ALL FORMS OF RACE AND RELIGION RELIGION BASED
VIOLENCE IN SAN FRANCISCO IN THE WAKE OF NATIONAL
INCIDENTS INVOLVING SHOOTINGS AND OTHER VIOLENCE AND THEN
LOCAL INCIDENTS OF OF PROPERTY DAMAGE, VIOLENCE AGAINST
INDIVIDUALS, HARASSMENT OF PROMINENT JEWISH INDIVIDUALS.
IT SEEMS LIKE TIME THAT FOR THIS BOARD TO WEIGH IN.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR HELPING ME THINK
THIS THROUGH THIS RESOLUTION AND FOR YOUR FEEDBACK AND EDITS
AND PARTNERSHIP AND CO-SPONSOR SHIP AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR MILLER SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER,
THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> WELL THEN LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT.
PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MAY 13TH BOARD MEETING MINUTES AS
PRESENTED. ITEMS 40 THROUGH 44 THE ITEMS
ADOPTED WITHOUT REFERENCE TO COMMITTEE AND OTHER GENERAL
MATTERS NOT ON TODAY'S AGENDA. I WILL JUST STATE FOR THE 3
P.M. SPECIAL ORDERS THE FTA FOR THE SIU AND THE CIA THE
CERTIFICATE OF APPROPRIATENESS .
>> THOSE ITEMS HAD THEIR PUBLIC COMMENT PROCESS CONCLUDED
AND WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
MR. WRIGHT WELCOME. ANY WAY TO HANDLE THIS?
HOW'S THE DISCRIMINATION AND YOUR PRICE FIXING AND YOUR
PRICE GOUGING IS TO TAKE YOU IN FRONT OF THE EVER SO
HONORABLE UNITED STATES FEDERAL DISTRICT COURT JUDGE.
I'M JUST LAYING THE FOUNDATION OF FACTS.
SO UNDER WHAT YOU IN COURT YOU CAN'T SAY THAT YOU DON'T KNOW
NOTHING ABOUT THE ISSUE AND ABOUT YOUR BUDGET WHERE YOU
EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IS BEING PAID
$1,500 A MONTH MORE THAN YOU SHOULD BE BEING PAID WHICH TOOK
PLACE EIGHT YEARS AGO WHEN SUPERVISOR COHEN GAVE EACH
AND EVERY ONE OF YOU THAT SAY AT $1,500 A MONTH SALARY
INCREASE BECAUSE OF THE PRICE CUTS THAT DONALD TRUMP AND YOUR
HIGH TAXES OF GAVIN NEWSOM YOU ENDED UP AT THE PRESENT TIME
WHEN I MADE MY LAST DEMONSTRATION YOU HAD A
1,584,000,000 OVERPAYMENT OF FUNDS AND NONE OF YOU SIT UP
THERE AND CARE ABOUT IT JUST LONG AS MONEY IS BEING KEPT
IN YOUR POCKET. HOW ABOUT YOU, CHEN?
YOU WANT TO STRAIGHTEN OUT THE BUDGET?
YOU WANT TO CUT THE BUDGET OF THE POLICE FUNDS AND YOU BEING
OVERPAID YOU SELF THAT'S DISGUSTING.
>> YOU ADDRESS THE WHOLE BOARD NOT JUST ALL OF YOU.
>> DON'T JUST TELL ME YOU DRESS ON ICE MY TIME.
YOU SHUT UP. NOW AT THE PRESENT TIME THAT
WAS TWO MONTHS AGO. SO THE AMOUNT OF OVERPAID MEANT
THAT EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS BEEN
GETTING IS STANDS RIGHT NOW $1,000,000,717 MILLION OF
OVERPAYMENT BUT YET YOU WANT TO CUT FUNDS FROM THE MOST
VULNERABLE PEOPLE THAT'S GETTING SERVICES IN THE CITY
BECAUSE OF YOUR POOR SUPERVISION AND MANAGEMENT OF
THE TAXPAYERS MONEY. MAYOR YOU SHOULD DONATE YOUR
MONEY THAT YOU CLAIM THAT YOU'RE NOT BEING PAID FOR BEING
THE MAYOR TO PAY FOR THE FINES THAT THAT LEGAL AID THAT HELPS
THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE THAT'S HOMELESS OUT ON THE
STREET AND EVICTION DEFENSE AND HELP PEOPLE THAT ARE ON THE
VERGE OF LOSING THEIR HOUSING AND ABOUT YOU DIFFERENTIAL
TREATMENT HOW COME YOU'RE NOT GETTING BACK PAY CLAWING BACK
THAT OVERPAYMENT OF BOB BECAUSE SEE WHO IS GETTING $7,000 A
YEAR THAT CLEAR? >> HOW COME YOU AND I CALL BACK
AND THAT MONEY GUYS ADVISE ME MR. RIGHT YOUR SPEAKER'S TIME
IS CONCLUDED SO LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER IN ARGUE FOR
TWO HOURS STRAIGHT DIDN'T DO WHEN I RAISED A LITTLE BIT OF
HELP. A COUPLE OF SECONDS LEFT
SOMEHOW. >> GIRL MR. SLEEPER SHANE
MICHAEL SLEEPER HERE I HAVE BEEN FREE FOR TWO MONTHS OF
2025 AND IN THOSE TWO MONTHS I HAVE EXPERIENCED THREE
TERMINATIONS WITHOUT CAUSE OTHER THAN DISCRIMINATION.
IS THAT SUSTAINABLE TO YOU? I'VE YET TO GO AN ENTIRE YEAR
WITHOUT FACING INCARCERATION DURING THE PAST DECADE OF MY
LIFE FOR DOUBLE STANDARDS OF LAW CONTINUOUSLY INFLICTED
UNDER DEMOCRATIC RULE THAT WANTS TO ABOUT TRUMP BEING A
FASCIST AS I BE DEEMED A TERRORIST THREAT FOR TELLING
OTHERS WHAT THEIR ACTIONS CAN CAUSE.
WELL I HAVE NEVER ONCE ATTEMPTED TO OWN A GUN NOR PUT
MY HANDS ON ANY THOSE THAT RETAIN THEIR EMPLOYMENT WITHOUT
ISSUE. TELL ME YOU'RE NOT AMERICAN.
YOU'RE WHITE SUCH AS DIANA DELGADO FROM PERU WORKING AT
FOGG HARBOR FISH HOUSE ANOTHER FEMALE FROM OAKLAND, CRYSTAL
MEZA TELLS ME SHE DIDN'T LIKE SOMEONE SO SHE QUIT TALKING TO
THEM UNTIL THEY QUIT WHILE SHE ALSO SPEAKS OF HER COKE HABIT
ON THE CLOCK AND TELLS ME I TALK TOO MUCH WHEN I KNOW THE
WEEK OF HER CYCLE ANOTHER FEMALE CHELSEA ARCHER HIRING ME
AT EQUINOX SPORTS CLUB A JOB I WAS REFERRED TO WORK AT
AND DENIED DUE WAGES DESPITE BEING ON FILM WORKING BEHIND
THE FRONT DESK FILES AND A RESTRAINING ORDER THAT SHE IS
SCARED SHE MIGHT BE RAPED BY A GAY MAN THAT HAS NEVER HAD A
DESIRE TO TOUCH A BLEEDING BADGE SHOULDN'T THESE BE THE
ONES THAT WE ARE SCARED OF THE ONES TO BE DEFINED AS
PSYCHOPATHS THAT HAVE NO PROBLEM AFFECTING OTHER
CITIZENS ABILITY TO SURVIVE WITHOUT?
I HAD A RIFLE POINTED AT MY FACE FOR THE COUNT THAT SAID
SHE IS SCARED I MIGHT RAPE HER .
IS THAT JUSTICE TO YOU? IT'S NOT ABOUT THE $30 I WAS
OWED. IT'S ABOUT A COMPANY WORTH $7.5
BILLION HAVING NO PROBLEM OFF MY LIFE AS LONG AS THEIR TRUTH
DOES NOT BECOME KNOWN. THAT HAS ALREADY WELCOMED THE
MURDER OF OTHERS GIVEN WHAT IS STILL OUTSIDE OUR WINDOWS IT
COSTS NEARLY $4,000 A MONTH TO KEEP ME INCARCERATED WHICH
EQUALS MORE THAN THREE TIMES OF WHAT I'VE EVER MADE ANNUALLY
OVER THE PAST DECADE OF FORCED POVERTY AN EXPERIENCE THAT
WELCOMES PHYSICAL AND SEXUAL ASSAULTS HAS TO TAKE PLACE
WITHOUT CONSEQUENCE AS LONG AS YOU'VE GOT A BADGE AND ARE
PROTECTED BY A UNION THAT WELCOMES US ALL WE'VE GOT AN
800 AND $40 MILLION POLICE BUDGET WITH MORE THAN THREE
QUARTERS QUARTERS OF OUR POLICE FORCE NOT EVEN BEING RESIDENTS
OF SAN FRANCISCO. I THINK I UNDERSTAND SAN
FRANCISCO'S EXPLOITATION QUITE WELL.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT.
>> HELLO, HOW ARE YOU? I WAS JUST WONDERING IF YOU
GUYS COULD LIKE TAKE A LOOK AT THE LEGISLATION THAT THE
MAYOR IS TRYING TO ENFORCE ON THE ARVS.
A LOT OF US ARE YOU KNOW, LEGAL AND LAW ABIDING CITIZENS AND I
LIVE IN AN RV. MY HOME AND I DON'T WANT TO BE
YOU KNOW, HAVE MY RV TOWED AWAY WHEN I DECIDE TO GO TO WORK ONE
DAY. THERE'S A LOT OF PEOPLE OUT
THERE WHO HAVE ARVS THAT, YOU KNOW, PAY THEIR REGISTRATION
PER YEAR PLUS THEIR INSURANCE AND YOU KNOW, ARE NOT A
NUISANCE. THEY'RE NOT DEFECATING
URINATING AROUND THEIR RV AND THEY'RE UNDER THREAT OF
HAVING IT TOWED AWAY. THERE'S FAMILIES OUT THERE
IN THERE ARE THESE AND YOU KNOW, IT'D BE NICE IF WE COULD
GET SOME REAL LEGISLATION AND SOME REAL LEADERSHIP
BECAUSE WHAT MAYOR LURIE'S DOING IS TOTAL THEFT.
YOU KNOW, I MEAN IF YOU BUY SOMETHING WHICH IS AN RV
AND YOU OWN IT, YOU SHOULD BE ABLE TO POSSESS IT.
YOU PAY THE REGISTRATION TO HAVE IT ON THE STREETS OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND THEN PLUS YOU KNOW, HE'S GOING TO ASK, YOU
KNOW, THE PEOPLE TO MOVE EVERY TWO HOURS.
THAT'S GOING TO CAUSE THEM MENTAL ANGUISH, YOU KNOW?
WHO'S GOING TO MOVE THEIR RV AT 3:00 IN THE MORNING WHEN THEY
GOT TO GO TO WORK? YOU KNOW?
SO IT'S GOING TO CAUSE A REAL YOU KNOW, MAJOR YOU KNOW,
PROBLEM, YOU KNOW, FOR FAMILIES, LAW ABIDING CITIZENS,
PEOPLE WHO ARE TRYING TO REHABILITATE THEMSELVES, YOU
KNOW, AND SO YEAH, LIKE YOU KNOW AND PLUS LIKE I OWN AN RV
THAT IS LIKE WORTH YOU KNOW, SOMEBODY HAVING.
SO IT'S LIKE YOU KNOW THEY WOULD LOVE TO LIKE STEAL TO
HAVE IT TOWED AWAY AND THEN SELL IT TO CITY AUCTION.
SO YOU KNOW IF YOU COULD YOU KNOW, PLEASE HELP US WITH THAT
SITUATION WOULD BE GREAT BECAUSE IT WASN'T A PROBLEM
BEFORE LORI GOT HERE AND NOW ALL OF A SUDDEN THERE'S A BIG
PROBLEM WITH THE RV. >> I DON'T THINK SO.
SO IF YOU COULD I'M REALLY APPRECIATIVE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS ,MRS. BROWN.
WELCOME. >> I GUESS IT'S EVENING NOW.
>> I'M NOT HERE TO TALK ABOUT ANY SPECIFIC LEGISLATION TODAY
OTHER THAN TO EXPRESS MY APPRECIATION FOR THE PASSING OF
THE HOMICIDE REWARD FUNDS LEGISLATION.
BUT I WANT TO TALK ABOUT WHY THIS KIND OF POLICY MATTERS.
I LOST MY SON AUGUST 14TH, 2006 SHOT WITH A SEMI AUTOMATIC GUN,
30 ROUNDS OF BULLETS LEFT THAT GUN.
>> I COME TO THE POLICE COMMISSION EVERY WEDNESDAY
AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WHEN I CAN MAKE IT.
>> I TOOK THE OPPORTUNITY TO PUT UP MY SON'S PICTURE WHILE
THIS PROTEST WAS GOING ON THAT DAY EVEN THOUGH I WASN'T
INVOLVED IN IT. >> BUT I WANT PEOPLE TO KNOW I
JUST I BRING THESE PICTURES WITH THIS PICTURE OF MY SON
AND OTHER HOMICIDE VICTIMS. >> SO I'M SO APPRECIATIVE THAT
I AM A MOTHER WITH NO OF NO NONSENSE THAT I CAN CONTINUE TO
FIGHT FOR MY SON AND BRING THESE PICTURES OTHER OF OF
OTHER HOMICIDE VICTIMS THAT CASES AREN'T SOLVED.
>> THE MOTHER THAT WAS HERE WITH ME LAST WEEK IS STILL
FIGHTING FOR HER CHILD. >> SO IF THIS POLICY PASSES
THIS NOT POLICY BUT THIS POLICY PASSES, WHAT DO YOU THINK IS
GOING TO DO FOR US? >> IS GOING TO HELP ME IS GOING
TO HELP OTHER MOTHERS. AND I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT I
WILL BE BACK TO BRING AWARENESS TO ALL THE UNSOLVED HOMICIDES.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> TERRY, FEEL PATIENCE A
LONGING TO TAUNT FROM PLUCK A FALSE KNEE GEORGE JEAN DE LA
FONTAINE NO MATTER ON OH RESILIENT INDEED THE OTHER AN
INTELLIGENCE IS A NO DISGUISE APPRECIATES MARKETS THAT BEYOND
THAT'S THE WAY YOUR OWN INTELLIGENCE IS IN FACT
NEUTRALIZING NEUTRALIZING ITSELF SUCH AS AN EXAMPLE TODAY
USING THE 17 ONE OF THE FAVORITES A NUMBER OF THE
GLOBAL INTELLIGENCE TO ORGANIZE CLEARLY ORGANIZE A DESCRIPTION
OF THIS MEETING FOR TWO HOURS RIGHT UNDER THE CONTROL OF THE
SHERIFF'S DEPARTMENT INCLUDING AT THE END FETCH STATION WITH A
SMILE ON TO BE COVERED BY THE FAKE MEDIA ARE OWNED BY THE
FAKE SIM AN INTELLIGENCE THAT WE ALL KNOW OF NO NO MATTER
WHAT. >> SO THIS IS CLEAR IT SEEMS TO
ME YOU IS NOT INTERESTED. NO HE WASN'T THERE RIGHT
MAYOR YOU HAVE TWO WEEKS I SAID LAST WEEK TO START TICKING DOWN
REMOVING ALL THE 5G TOWERS THAT YOU'VE BEEN PUTTING ALL OVER
THE COUNTRY MAINLY DURING THE COVID LOCKDOWNS.
>> ALL THIS AGAINST THE PEOPLE'S APPROVAL.
>> THIS IS CLEAR THIS GOING TO HELP YOU OWN INTELLIGENCE TO
KEEP NOTES. >> MORALIZING ITSELF YOU SEE IS
TO HELP YOU HERE YOU NEED A LITTLE HELP.
>> SO AFTER THAT WE'RE GOING TO DO IT OURSELVES AND YOU ARE
GLOBALIST IDIOCY IS BOUND TO FAIL BECAUSE WITH YOUR
TECHNOLOGY TURN AS A WEAPON IT IS GAME OVER.
>> YOU UNDERSTAND? >> SHARON I'M TRYING TO RAISE
THE LEVEL EARLIER TO UPLIFT YOU MERCY MR. ARE THERE ANY OTHER
MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD
DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT? >> OKAY, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 40 THROUGH 44 ITEMS 40 THROUGH 44
WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE A
UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST READING TODAY. ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY
REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT AND WOMAN CAN I SEVER
CAN WE SEVER ITEM 43 YUP AND IT LOOKS LIKE THAT'S IT.
>> SO MADAM CLERK ON THE REMAINING BALANCE CAN YOU
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 40 THROUGH 44 -43 SUPERVISOR
SARTOR SARTOR I'S SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHEN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR AND ENGARDIO
AND ENGARDIO I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I
AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED AND THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL
ITEM 43 ITEM 43 RESOLUTION TO AFFIRM THE PUBLIC'S RIGHT TO
PEACEFULLY ASSEMBLE AND PROTEST ACTIONS OF THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT CONDEMNING THE MILITARIZATION OF CIVIL
RESPONSE TO PEACEFUL PROTESTS AND REAFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO'S
COMMITMENT TO IMMIGRANT JUSTICE AND THE CITY'S SANCTUARY
ORDINANCE. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK
YOU. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN
THINGS FOR EXCUSE ME LAST WEEK. GLAD TO BE BACK.
I JUST WANTED TO MAKE SOME REMARKS ON THIS.
I WANT TO BEGIN BY THANKING SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR
INTRODUCING THIS IMPORTANT LEGISLATION AFFIRMING THE RIGHT
TO PEACEFUL PROTESTS AND SUPERVISORS CHEN WALTON
MELGAR MIDDLEMAN SADR AND AND GADO FOR CO-SPONSORING.
>> AT A TIME WHEN OUR FUNDAMENTAL FREEDOMS ARE UNDER
THREAT, THIS MEASURE SENDS A CLEAR AND NECESSARY MESSAGE.
>> THE REASON I SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION IS THAT I THINK WE
ARE QUICKLY SINKING INTO AUTHORITY ARIANISM BY THE DAY
AND I DON'T WANT SAN FRANCISCO TO PAVE THE WAY FOR TRUMP TO DO
SO. I UNDERSTAND THE DESIRE TO
AVOID GIVING THIS ADMINISTRATION ANY PRETEXT TO
ESCALATE TO DEPLOY THE NATIONAL GUARD BUT THAT CANNOT COME AT
THE COST OF OUR VALUES. >> THAT CANNOT MEAN TARGETING
PEACEFUL PROTESTERS OR DETAINING MEMBERS OF THE PRESS
. >> THAT IS NOT PRECAUTION.
THAT IS COMPLICIT. >> THIS ISN'T JUST A MATTER OF
LEGAL DUE DILIGENCE. IT'S A MATTER OF PUBLIC TRUST.
WE CANNOT AND SHOULD NOT DO TRUMP'S JOB FOR HIM.
>> SAN FRANCISCO MUST STAND FIRM IN DEFENDING THE RIGHTS OF
ITS RESIDENTS AND AGAINST TRUMP'S INCREASINGLY FASCIST
REGIME. >> THESE DEMONSTRATIONS ARE
HAPPENING BECAUSE PEOPLE ARE RIGHTFULLY OUTRAGED, OUTRAGED
THAT THEIR NEIGHBORS ARE BEING TARGETED BY ISIS, HARASSED BY
FEDERAL AGENTS AND TREATED AS THREATS RATHER THAN MEMBERS OF
OUR COMMUNITY. THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO
DESERVE TO KNOW THAT WHEN THEY EXERCISE THEIR FIRST AMENDMENT
RIGHTS THEY WILL NOT BE MET WITH INTIMIDATION OR
DISPROPORTIONATE FORCE. >> THEY DESERVE TO KNOW THAT
THIS CITY HAS THEIR BACK. >> THIS BOARD MUST ENSURE
TRANSPARENCY, ACCOUNTABILITY AND A STEADFAST COMMITMENT TO
CIVIL LIBERTIES. THAT IS HOW WE PROTECT NOT JUST
PROTEST BUT DEMOCRACY ITSELF. >> AND SO I AM PROUD TO SUPPORT
THIS RESOLUTION. THANK YOU AGAIN, SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR
FIELDER. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION PASSES
IS APPROVED AND MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA
ITEMS? >> I HAVE NO REPORT, MR.
PRESIDENT. THEN I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO
THE END OF OUR AGENDA. DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS
BEFORE US TODAY IN MEMORIAM? >> OH YES, WE DO HAVE A
MEMORIAM. MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
READ THE IN MEMORIAM? >> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS.
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR THE LATE RODNEY BOWDEN
AND FOR RETIRED DEPUTY SHERIFF RHONDA GRAVES.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
THEN I THINK THAT DOES BRING US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA AND WE
ARE ADJOURNED